<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Karen Borg: Memoir </title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal>
               <persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
            </principal>
            <principal>
               <persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives, London</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir">Karen Borg, 1768-8147</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-05.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-06.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-07.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-08.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-09.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-10.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-11.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-12.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-13.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-14.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-15.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-16.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-17.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-18.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-19.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-20.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-21.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-22.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-23.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-24.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-25.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300009-26.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>Karen Borg</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head>Page 1 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-01" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Memoir Of our beloved Sister <persName>Karen Borg</persName>, who departed to the Lord at <placeName>Gracehill</placeName>, <date>March 8 1847</date>.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The vice of that blood which</l>
                  <l>Flowed from thee Saviour!</l>
                  <l>Which cries aloud wherein I tread</l>
                  <l>Thy tears for my ransom - all</l>
                  <l>Plead in my favor,</l>
                  <l>Nor call for vengeance on my head.</l>
                  <l>No! grace &amp; free mercy thy looks impart,</l>
                  <l>And this day refresh me taken my heart.</l>
                  <l>In spirit thy once bleeding hands I embrace</l>
                  <l>Which bear me triumphant</l>
                  <l>Though all my distress.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This verse contains in it the history of my course on earth, regarding which I have nothing remarkable to record; but I would acknowledge the mercy of our faithful Friend and
                  Saviour, who sought and found me, <note type="catchword">and</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head>Page 2 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-02" />
               </head>
               <p>and has held his gracious hand over me his poor child. I was born <date>May 18 1768</date> at <placeName>Christiansfeld</placeName> in <placeName>Norway</placeName>, where I was
                  carefully bro up by my dear parents till my 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year. I remember where I was only 7 seeing them weeping, and when I inquired the cause, my Brother told
                  me that it was because they were thinking of our Saviour, and she discoursed to me on his love to children and to poor sinners in a way which made a deep impression on me. _
                     <date>June 2 1778</date> my dear Mother brought me hither to <placeName>Christiansfeld</placeName> for education. I felt overjoyed on my arri- val here, though I could not tell
                  why, but I have since thanked the Lord with tears a thousand times for choosing me out of the world and bringing me to his people. I soon felt myself at home with my companions, and
                  was very happy. The children's prayer class were days of especial blessing to my heart. <date>
                     <abbr>Febr</abbr> 16 1780</date> I received permis= <note type="catchword">year</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head>Page 3 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-03" />
               </head>
               <p>year was <del>permitted</del> added to the choir of Girls. I felt much on leaving the chil- dren's choir, in which I had enjoyed so much of my Saviour's nearness, where we brought
                  him our united supplica- tions, or when I retired to weep for him in private. <date>July 9</date> following, I was <abbr>rec</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>d</abbr>
                  </hi> into the <abbr>Cong</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>n</abbr>
                  </hi>; but having to wait some time for admission to the Lord's supper, I could not understand it, as I had made it a subject of frequent prayer, and hitherto the Lord had always
                  heard me. On reflection, I said it was to teach me not to trust in my own strength, or diligence, or virtue, or good educa- tion, and to wean me from the danger- ous self complacency
                  which I cherish- ed on account of these things. And my faithful Saviour <corr>succeeded</corr> in convincing me that I was possessed of nothing good. When I attained to the first
                  enjoy- ment of the Holy Communion, <date>
                     <abbr>Oct</abbr> 10 1782</date>, I felt how blessed it is to be poor in spirit, and to receive his mer- <note type="catchword">its</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head>Page 4 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-04" />
               </head>
               <p>-its as a fit of undeserved grace. I begged him to preserve me in this frame of spirit, and to grant me low thoughts of myself at all times, seeing that to poor needy sinners he was
                  so gracious. In this disposition my days passed happily away, until my innate de- pravity began to awaken within me. Hitherto I had often acknowledged myself a sinful creature, but
                  now I <hi rend="underline">felt</hi> that from the heart proceed wil thoughts, and sorely was I tor- mented with un-christianlike thoughts, so that I had no rest day nor night. To
                  disclose my trouble to others, would I thought inevitably deprive me of their good opinion; my confidence in my Saviour also vanished, and I knew not how to bear myself for distress
                  of mind. In this pitiable condition, I shut my- self up in a room alone - it was a sacrament-day <date>
                     <abbr>Dec</abbr> 24 1785</date>, threw myself at my Saviour's feet and <note type="catchword">begged</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head>Page 5 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-05" />
               </head>
               <p>begged him with a flood of tears to have mercy on his wandering child, and give me to feel the pardon of my sins. And never shall I forget, I trust, the look of grace with which I
                  was cheer- ed on this occasion lay my crucified Re- deemer. It was as though he said to me himself "I have heard thy prayer and seen thy tears - thou art mine." "Might all his loving
                  heart but see, And know his bowels of compassion To sinners, straying carelessly, Or such as mourning seek salvation." From this time I was like one new-born; I felt my short-comings
                  in- deed very frequently, but the Lord inspir- ed me with faith in Him, so that I could lay all my wants before Him. I was also enabled to speak confiden- tially with my
                  choir-laborer, which was a great care to me. I now went on my course, not indeed without va- riation, yet always finding comfort and peace at my Saviour's feet. And his patience,
                  mercy and compassion are <note type="catchword">more</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="6">
               <head>Page 6 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-06" />
               </head>
               <p>more than everything to me. <date>May 4 1786</date> I was received into the <abbr>Sgle</abbr>. <abbr>Srs</abbr>. choir, on which occasion I had an inexpressibly blessed percep- tion
                  of the Lord's nearness, and gave myself up to him anew as his eternal property, imploring him to keep posses- sion of my heart, that all his thoughts of peace with me might be
                  attained. Towards the end of the same month, I had the pleasure to see my dear father here on a visit, and many a pleasing recollection of the conversation I had with him on
                  spiritual subjects, is im- printed on my memory. <date>July 2</date> in the same year, I received a proposal to as- sist as teacher in the Girls' school, which caused me many heavy
                  hours, feeling as I did my insufficiency and inex- perience, and knowing that there were others more suitable for the situation. The Lord however enabled me to take the proposal as
                  from His hand, and helped me graciously through all dif- ficulties. It is true I had much to <note type="catchword">learn</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="7">
               <head>Page 7 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-07" />
               </head>
               <p>learn, and this mere school for my heart caused me many a sleepless night. All however worked together for my good, and calls for my humble and heartfelt gratitude. My inter- course
                  with the dear children whom I cordially loved, and whose love I felt in return, was very pleasant to me, and the Lord was after in our midst in our social worship. When things of an
                  unpleasant nature occurred, it was my prayer, that if I could do no good, I might at least lay no stumbling-block in the way of these little ones. _ The early part of the year
                     <date>1789</date> was a peculiarly blessed season for my soul, my mind being much occupied with the thought of going home to the Lord. This idea was greatly strengthened, when, in
                  the beginning of <date>April</date> I had an attack of spitting of blood. Many were the hours of blessed in- tercourse with the Friend of my soul, which I enjoyed at this period.
                  Thank to Thee my faithful Saviour, for the manner </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="8">
               <head>Page 8 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-08" />
               </head>
               <p>in which thou was pleased to own me, thy poor child: thou hast followed me with love and tender mer- cy from my youth up; be my confidence still, and suffer not my faith to fail,
                  till the happy hour shall strike which summons me to meet thee, when I shall say: "Here comes a sinner who would fain <abbr>Thro</abbr>' the Lamb's ransom entrance gain."; I would
                  rather have gone home at this time than recovered, and both mind and body felt the effects of this illness for a long period. In the following <date>
                     <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                  </date>. several things combined to weigh down my spirits, and every one thought I was in a decline. As I kept my trouble to myself, the burden was the heavier, and I began to doubt
                  my Saviour's willingness to help. But he appeared again to comfort me and put my anxious grieving to shame. I was especially cheered at this time, by the privilege which he
                  vouchsafed[?] me, of joining in the celebration of the <date>16 of <abbr>Sept</abbr>.</date> with the servants of our Church. <note type="catchword">Thus</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="9">
               <head>Page 9 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-09" />
               </head>
               <p>Thus far was written <date>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>. 1789</date>. <date>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr> 1 1798</date> was a very blessed New- years-day to me. The Lord gave me to feel his forgiveness of all my transgressions and mistakes so sensibly, that my heart
                  overflowed with gratitude and joy, and I devoted myself to his service amongst the little ones with new courage, heavy as my situation had been in many respects in the past year. On
                  the <date>12</date> I received a call to <placeName>Ebersdorf</placeName> as Co-labourer of the <abbr>Sgle</abbr>
                  <abbr>Srs</abbr>. choir, which, notwith- standing my insufficiency, I ventured to accept in reliance on the Lord's help, which I had experienced on many a former trial. On casting a
                  retrospective glance on the 20 years which I have spent in this dear <abbr>Cong</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>n</abbr>
                  </hi>, I cannot but adore my Saviour with the deepest hu- mility and gratitude for his great long- suffering, patience and faithfulness. The love and friendship testified towards me
                  by my sisters, notwithstanding all my failings, humbled me greatly, and made the parting painful. Nor <note type="catchword">could</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="10">
               <head>Page 10 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-10" />
               </head>
               <p>could I have the dear children commit- ted to my care without a pang. My sin- cere wish is that they may all prosper for the Lord, and yield themselves to him as his property. On my
                  dear fa- ther's happy depature at <date>Christmas 1794</date>, my dear mother removed hither to my no small gratification and joined the <abbr>Cong</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>n</abbr>
                  </hi>. I had now to quit her and all my dear friends, leaving <placeName>Christans- feld</placeName>
                  <date>May 5</date>, and on the <date>30</date> of the same month, I arrived in <placeName>Ebersdorf</placeName>. I felt a strange sensation on catching a first view of the place in
                  the distance, but I said "Dear Saviour, thou hast called me hither, and thou must help me. Thou best knowest my weakness, I know none here but thee alone, and thou permitted me to
                  cling to thee." Notwithstanding my fears, I was received with much love. Previous to my being introduced to the choir, I cast myself at the feet of Jesus and besought him with many
                  tears to be my Guide, and enable me to walk before </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="11">
               <head>Page 11 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-11" />
               </head>
               <p>before him in lowliness and humility. I then entered the choir-hall, and never shall I forget what I felt on being blessed for my office. It was as if our Saviour himself laid his
                  pierced hands upon my head, and gave me his benediction. What rendered it still more impressive to me was, that it occurred just at the entrance upon Passion week. I soon felt at
                  home in this dear peaceful settlement, and spent 3 years very happily. The La- borer and Warden of the choir were two old experienced sisters, whose counsel and assistance were of
                  essential service to me. Their love, as well as the love and confi- dence of my sisters generally, made my abode here very pleasant. <date>March 30 1801</date> I received a call to
                     <placeName>Fulnec</placeName>, which was again a hard trial to me. Gladly would I have declined it but I did not feel at liberty to do so. I therefore accepted it in implicit
                  reliance on my gracious Lord. In May I received an invitation to be present at the Synod of the <abbr>Brn's</abbr> Church, which was to be held <note type="catchword">this</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="12">
               <head>Page 12 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-12" />
               </head>
               <p>this year, and found it a means of new grace and encouragement for my weak faith. On the <date>24</date> of the same month, I took farewell of my choir, dividing with them the cup of
                  covenant, and next day proceeded to <placeName>Herrnhut</placeName>. <date>
                     <abbr>Sept</abbr> 3</date> I pursued my journey in company of <persName>
                     <abbr>Br</abbr>. and <abbr>Sr</abbr>. Moore</persName>, and arrived in <placeName>Fulnec</placeName>
                  <date>October 3</date>. Thus far our late sister continued her memoir in German, though of the introductory verse she has furnished both the original and the version. Sever- al other
                  verses are interspersed in the memoir, which show her ready talent in this species of composition. She continues in English as follows: <placeName>
                     <hi rend="underline">Fulnec</hi>
                  </placeName>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="underline">
                        <abbr>Oct</abbr> 3 1811</hi>
                  </date>. Calling to mind this day, that it is 10 years since I arrived in this place, various thoughts occupy my mind. In taking a short view of that period, <note type="catchword"
                     >I</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="13">
               <head>Page 13 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-13" />
               </head>
               <p>I sink down abased before my Lord and Saviour, for numberless proofs of his love, faithfulness and forbearance, which I have experienced in many ways. The first year I spent here
                  appeared very heavy in- deed; everything seemd so different to what I was accustomed, and not know- ing the language, was altogether a heavy task. However my best Friend did not
                  leave me nor forsake me, but lent a gracious ear to all my wants and com- plaints. In <date>
                     <abbr>Oct</abbr>. 1802</date> I was afflicted with an epidemical fever, and so ill, that little hope was given of my recovery. Though I had no clearness that I should go to my
                  dear Saviour, yet I wished for that favor to see him face to face, and felt happy in the thought of leav- ing this world. But it pleased him to restore me again, and I found much
                  reason to thank and adore him for his paternal love and care, which was made manifest to me. <date>
                     <abbr>Dec</abbr>. 15</date> the same year we celebra- ted the anniversary of this house </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="14">
               <head>Page 14 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-14" />
               </head>
               <p> 50 years ago. This surely was a day which the Lord himself made; the blessings we enjoyed will always be remembered with gratitude by those who were present; and I can truly say it
                  was the first day I felt quite at home here. In <date>1803</date> and <date>1804</date> it pleased our Saviour to call home to himself both my fellow-labourers. This was a heavy
                  stroke, which was very se- verely felt by me: but thanks to my dear Lord, who supported me, as I now in a way felt as standing by myself. The love and support and confidence, which I
                  under these afflictions experienced from my dear choir, will never be forgotten by me. Sinner-tears bedew my cheek now while I write these lines, and call to mind numberless proofs
                  of my Redeemer's love and patience towards me, the poorest of the needy; which my </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="15">
               <head>Page 15 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-15" />
               </head>
               <p> pen cannot relate. Oh! in the dust I thank and adore him, though I blush with shame when I look to myself and see how often I have greived him in my own course and what belongs to
                  my office. Oh! my Saviour, pardon all my neglects and mistakes; thou knowest my wants, thou seest my tears; ah! re- member me who are but dust and ashes; blot out my sins and
                  transgress- sions with thy precious blood, and endou me with new grace to act ac- cording to thy mind, to be faithful to my calling, to walk before thee in hu- mility and loveliness
                  of heart. Strength- en my confidence in thee, that midst all trials I may rely unshaken up- on thy faithfulness. In <date>1806</date> I had the pleasure to welcome <persName>
                     <abbr>Sr</abbr>. Connor </persName>here, who had received a call to be Warden of this choir. With her I have till this day lived in love and peace, and we could jointly bear the
                  concerns Com- <note type="catchword">mitted</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="16">
               <head>Page 16 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-16" />
               </head>
               <p> mitted to us, which have often been a subject for prayer and supplication, but to Him who has thus far in my trials and heavy circumstances help- ed through, I commit every concern,
                  with faith and full assurance that He as a tender Father, as the friend of the poor and needy, will in time to come care for his dear bought fam- ily and choir, both with spiritual
                  and temporal blessings. My sincere prayer is expressed in these lines: On that day of consummation May we sinners mercy find; Saved with complete salvation And not one be left behind
                  As wise virgins May we all before thee stand. Within these 10 years I have wit- nessed 39 instances of <abbr>Sgle</abbr>. <abbr>Srs</abbr>. who happily departed to the Lord. On such
                  occasions I have often felt more than I can express. They <note type="catchword">have</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="17">
               <head>Page 17 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-17" />
               </head>
               <p> have been solemn opportunities to examine my own heart before the Lord; and when I shall have the favor to see him face to face, my stammering tongue shall praise him for these and
                  thous- and other blessings. I have also had the pleasure to see several become useful in our Saviour's service; may He still prepare many to be witnesses of his redeem- ing love. </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <date>August 5 1833</date>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> After a period of 22 years, I take up my pen once more still to acknowledge the mercy and goodness of my dear Saviour. <date>
                     <abbr>Sept</abbr>. 26 1816</date> I received a call to <placeName>Gracehill</placeName>, which I accepted in reliance on the Lord's help and support. When I look back on the <note
                     type="catchword">period</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="18">
               <head>Page 18 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-18" />
               </head>
               <p> period of 15 years spent in <placeName>Fulnec</placeName>, my eyes flow over with gratitude for the numberless proofs of my faith- ful Saviour's love and forbearness he has proved
                  my Counsellor and friend, my Advocate to plead my cause, my Comforter in all trouble. O that I had been more faithful to his Spirit's teaching, and of more use to those committed to
                  my care. Here shame fills my inmost soul, and I can only say "Lord be merciful to me a sinner! O blot out my sins and transgressions with thy precious blood and remember them no
                  more." <date>
                     <abbr>Dec</abbr> 5</date> I set out for my new post; the evening before was a meeting for taking leave of my dear choir, whose joy and grief were always deeply felt by me; and my
                  earnest prayer is and shall be, that the Lord may keep his protecting hand over that family and house, and that his thoughts of peace may be <note type="catchword">ob-</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="19">
               <head>Page 19 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-19" />
               </head>
               <p> obtained with every individual soul. I believe we all felt on that occasion what is expressed in the hymn: "Blest be that sacred covenant love to." <date>
                     <abbr>Dec</abbr>. 10 1816</date> I arrived safe in <placeName>Grace- hill</placeName> after a troublesome journey and voyage, wind and weather being very severe. I was received in
                  love, and soon found myself at home; but finding the house in a very distressed state with regard to ex- ternals, it would often sink my spirits; but thanks to my dear Savi- our, the
                  giver of my good gift, who also in this respect has helped us far above all that we would ask or think.</p>
               <p>This has often been a subject to me for much gratitude and hu- miliation. He also inclined the heart of our much beloved late <persName>Mr</persName>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <persName>s</persName>
                  </hi>
                  <persName> Bates</persName>, to lend a helping hand to our distress, for which no doubt he will richly reward have. Many prayers also for the spiritual pros- <note type="catchword"
                     >perity</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="20">
               <head>Page 20 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-20" />
               </head>
               <p> perity of this choir, and particularly the younger part, I trust, O Lord, thou hast heard and when thou hearest. O forgive - O pardon me when I have been to a lenient or too severe.
                  O forgive All - All. </p>
               <p>A loose paper un-dated, adds: It has often of late been im- pressed on my mind, that my time here below may perhaps not be long, perhaps sudden. This is an awful meditation, but also
                  a happy one. I have nothing to say but the Publican's plea - "God be merciful to me a sinner!" Still I have that divine assur- ance, that he will receive me in mercy and cleanse me
                  in that precious fountain, which by faith I opened see, and do the me in his blood and righteousness. O my Saviour, I am in thy hands, hide <note type="catchword">me</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="21">
               <head>Page 21 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-21" />
               </head>
               <p> me till the storm of life is past, and then I shall be with thee in evermore. O happy lot. What heavenly joy and consolation This hope affords unto my heart to. <hi rend="underline"
                   /> Thus far our late Sister has con- tinued her memoir.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="underline" />
               </p>
               <p>It was only on the <date>22</date> of last month that our dear sister was taken ill, having probably caught cold on the preceding day where she was walking in the burial- ground
                  lane. She was soon obli- ged to keep her bed, though no immediate apprehensions were entertained as to the result. After a whole week however had elap- sed, the unabated continuance
                  of the febrile symptoms, and the to- tal loss of appetite occasioned by <note type="catchword">the</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="22">
               <head>Page 22 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-22" />
               </head>
               <p> the malady, filled our minds with anxiety, and she herself began to en- tertain the hope that her Saviour was about to call her to himself. On the <date>2 </date>of this month, she
                  quo- ted the well known lines of <persName>C. Wes- ley</persName>: _ "O could I catch a smile from thee And drop into eternity."</p>
               <p>She said she should be glad to go to him if it were his pleasure. In reply to a remark made on the loss which we should feel if she were removed from us, she disclaimed all idea of
                  worthiness in herself; her short-com ings she said, were many, and she had nothing to trust to but our Sa- viour's merits. On the following day though very weak so that she had not
                  spoken all the morning, she rallied a little when <persName>
                     <abbr>Br</abbr>. Edwards</persName> called in the afternoon, and uttered a few broken sentences, the purport of which was, that she longed to go home soon to be with the Lord.
                     <note type="catchword">The</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="23">
               <head>Page 23 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-23" />
               </head>
               <p> The farewell blessing in reference to her departure, was now given, and her dear bought soul recommended to the hands of her Redeemer, who had led her so graciously throughout her
                  course, and made her so rich a means of blessing to others. She was again favored with an inter- val of consciousness on the 6th (Sat- urday last) and requested her
                     <corr>visitor</corr> to pray with her. From that time she gradually sunk away, until on <date>Monday the 8</date> it pleased the Lord to release her from her worn-out ta- bernacle
                  in a very gentle manner, and translate her who the presence of his glory with exceeding joy _ Her age was 78 3/4 years. There is no need for us to en- large on the character of our
                  late justly beloved and venerated sister. Her praise is in all the Churches, and her works do follow her _ We have lost in her a Mother in our spiritual
                  <placeName>Israel</placeName>, who was truly and deeply </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="24">
               <head>Page 24 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-24" />
               </head>
               <p> deeply intrusted in the welfare of the <abbr>Cong</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>n</abbr>
                  </hi> collectively and individ- ually. Consecrated to the Lord from early infancy, she spent a long life in fellowship of spirit with her Saviour, and accounted it a privi- lege to
                  serve him with all the power and faculties which he had given her. What above all distinguished her character and made her so emi- nently useful in his church, was the large measure
                  of the spirit of love, which was poured out upon her. Her service as choir-laborer in <placeName>Ebersdorf</placeName>, <placeName>Fulnec</placeName> and
                     <placeName>Gracehill</placeName>, will long be treasured in the recollection of those who were favored to enjoy her kind and faithful care. By far the greater portion of her life
                  has been dedicated to active service in the family of Christ below. Not to mention her services as Teacher for for 11 1/2 years, her labors in her own choir comprise a period of 48
                  years from her entrance <note type="catchword">on</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="25">
               <head>Page 25 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-25" />
               </head>
               <p> on office as Co-laborer at <placeName>Ebersdorf</placeName> to her final resignation on account of increasing infirmity in <date>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>. 1845</date>. It may be truly said of her, that it was her greatest happiness to do good, and the manner in which she performed her deeds of kindness, made them
                  still more valuable. Humility, indeed, was likewise a very leading feature in her character, and nothing would have distressed her more than the thought of being made the subject of
                  eulogy. Still, it is meet to acknow- ledge the grace of God and the un- feigned faith which dwelt in her so much, and to set before our minds for invitation, the humility, simplicity
                  and love, which graced her walk and conversation, as she went in and out amongst us. We may still admit to her sincere and steady love for the Lord's house and ordinances. His place
                  in Church was never vacant, when she was able to venture out; and to stay <note type="catchword">away</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="26">
               <head>Page 26 <seg ana="MemLon_300009-26" />
               </head>
               <p> away from the meetings, was a depri- vation and a grief to her. On the Thursday after she was seized with her last illness, she expressed her regret at being debarred this priv-
                  ilege and repeated the first line of the verse, <abbr>N</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>o</abbr>
                  </hi> 732 _ One wish with holy transport warm My heart hath formed &amp; still doth form One gift I ask, that to my end Thine hallowed house I may attend to She is now more highly
                  favored in being admitted to the great <abbr>Cong</abbr>
                  <hi rend="superscript">
                     <abbr>n</abbr>
                  </hi> and the true sanctuary. May we follow her path, and so, through grace, be permitted to share her happiness! </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
