<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/moravianlives/master/TEI_Memoirs/XML/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Martin Berg: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marita Gruner</persName>
               <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sarah Kannemann</persName>
               <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives Bethlehem</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" xml:id="mlper000025">Martin Berg</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0185a-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0185a-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0185a-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0185a-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0185a-05.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>name</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0185a-01">1</head>
               <p>
                  Personals of the Single Brother Martin Berg
                  Who departed to our Saviour the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of February 1768
                  at New Dietenderff. He has left the following account
                  of his Path thro time:</p>
                  <p>I was born at Strahlsund the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of October 1711. My Father who
                  was a Captain of a Vessel, dying when I was very young, and <add place="above">my</add> Mother dying
                  in the Plague, our Relations took care to place my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. and <del>??</del> <corr>me</corr> in the
                  Orphan House, where my Brother soon after dyed  died very happy. But I became
                  a wicked Child. As I was in full Career towards all evil, wild and thoughtless,
                  I saw one day the <sic>Apearance</sic>  <corr>Appearance</corr> of a Person whose Face was <sic>wrapt</sic>  <corr>wrapped</corr> in Red
                  Callico. As I look'd earnestly at it, It seemd to me as the Blood broke out
                  at every Pore. I ran away from this sight, and full of Surprize and 
                  Terror, Jump'd down a high pair of stairs. My Fright was so great
                  that I had one Dainty Fitt after the other, and was sick several Days
                  yea I lost my speech 3 days, and could tell no one what had befallen me.
                  Soon after I fell ill of a violent Fever, in which I was lightheaded and
                  thought I saw nothing but Devils, and it was to me as if I was really
                  in Hell. In this distress I beg'd of God to spare me this time, I would
                  be converted and be a good Child. I repeated all the Ejaculations I had
                  learnt  learned, and pray'd heartily for my recovery, and the Lord heard my Prayers
                  and gave to feel his grace and Pardon of my Sins. As soon as I regaind my
                  Health, I set faithfully about performing the promise I had made to God,
                  with the Assistance of his Holy Spirit, who was my faithful Bystand,
                  at which the Guardian of the Orphan House grew displeas'd and endeavoured
                  to distress me all maner  manner of ways. As I durst not pray Openly, I crept
                  into Holes and Corners, wept and pray'd to the Lord whom I had griev'd
                  so long, but who was now so gracious to me, that I had a Heaven upon
                  Earth. I could not refrain letting my School fellows know what pass'd
                  with me, which was a means of Increaing my Persecution. When I
                  was alone at Prayers the other Children would listen, and that prov'd
                  a means of bringing several to think as I did, that their Hearts was
                  touch'd and they was of the same Mind with my self; their number
                  was 8. Here upon the Enemy was enraged, and as I was accused of being
                  the cause of this stirring among the Children, I suffered a great deal,
                  and receiv'd more stripes than as tho  though I had done evil. I had no one
                  <note type="catchword">To</note></p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0185a-02">2</head>
               <p>to make my Compaint to, but the Lord Jesus, and he made my heart still
                  more happy from day to day; the more I was beat, the greater was my Joy as
                  I thought I should the sooner come to the Lord Jesus. More Children joining
                  with me, and The Guardians finding they could not settle this Affair
                  by leaking and <sic>useing</sic>  <corr>using</corr> me roughly, they thought We was all bewitch'd
                  and that I was possess'd with the Devil, for which reason they would fain
                  have beat me to death, at length they concluded to confine me in Prison which they did accordingly. How happy I was in that dark Hole
                  where I was fed with Bread and Water, I cannot describe, my Companions
                  often singing a Hymn and weeping at the door of my Prison. After I had
                  been 8 Days confin'd, I was sent for, and required to promise that I would
                  no longer sing, Pray nor weep, nor lead others astray. As I could not
                  promise this, I was examined into the first cause of my change. I gave
                  them a full Account of what had befallen me, but they gave no Credit to my Words. Just then, there was a New <sic>Minester</sic>  <corr>Minister</corr> at S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Marys
                  Church named Siebeth, I was brought before him, and he examined 
                  me out of the Cathechism, which I answerd pretty well. This Man
                  whom I look'd upon as my Deliverer, order'd me to be set at Liberty
                  and told me to come and spend an Hour with him every Day [??]
                  whenever I came, he used to kneel and pray with me, and gave me
                  a Bible which was a great Joy to me, for I never had one in my hand
                  before. In my 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year a Young Nobleman desired a Boy out
                  of the Orphan House, and they being glad to get rid of me, sent 
                  me to him. I travelled with him to Greifswalde where he was
                  in office. In 6 Months time he sent me back, and I met with
                  great difficulties before I could again be Admitted into the Orphan
                  House. I found my Companions still cheerful and we was very happy
                  together I rejoicing much to be with them. As the Enemy could
                  not Overcome me with sharp treatment he now tried another
                  Method, 6 Months was scarce over, before the Chief Judge of the
                  City took me to live with him, He was much kinder to me than my
                  former Master, yea he was for <sic>makeing</sic>  <corr>making</corr> a Young Gentleman of me
                  and had a Master to teach me Languages and dancing with his only
                  Daughter, this pleas'd me mightyly  mightily, but I lost my former Grace &amp; Blessing.
                  Reading in the Bible, and going to Church grew irksome to me, Sin &amp;
                  Corruption got the <sic>uperhand</sic>  <corr>upperhand</corr>, and I had <sic>Oppertunitys</sic>  <corr>Opportunities</corr> enough to Commit Evil. As I fell out with my Master, I left him and lived
                  some
                  
                  <cb/>///<lb/>
                  
                  some time with another gentleman who led still a worse life from.
                  Hence I went to learn the Anchor Smiths Trade, but this being <sic>to</sic>  <corr>too</corr>
                  hard for me I ran away, and went on board a Ship bound to Stockholm. There I met with my Mothers Brother, who was a very rich
                  Man and as I was his only Near Relation, He took to me as his own
                  Child, would have made me his Heir and Educated me with his 2
                  Step Sons. But as we could not agree together, he sent me to Upsal
                  to study Divinity, but this would not do, as I was much to Wild and determined to follow the Seas; My Uncle made another Trial and brought me
                  to another of my uncles, who was Captain of the Guards, here I was
                  to use my self to a high Life, but this did not please me, and I was
                  no where easy. After I had been 2 Years at Sweden, I became a
                  Mocker of all good, and Endeavourd to Opress the Pious Souls all that
                  I could. I resolved to go to sea, and all things being ready, the day
                  before we was to sail, I fell into the river with an Iron barr in
                  my hand, and was brought back to the city for dead. I could not 
                  go this time, but was obliged to spend the winter there. The next
                  Spring I saild to Spain, and continued following the Sea as that
                  was my Delight, one winter I spent in London. In my 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                  Year, a rich Man offerd me his Daughter, with a Ship and Cargo
                  but when all things was ready for Conclusion, some one broke it
                  off- This has been often my Lot, that when good Fortune has
                  seem'd to court me, it has suddenly vanish'd and left me as I
                  was before. One Time being on board a Vessel bound from Diourheim to Newcastle, we lost our Course and narrowly escaped foundring on the Norway Rocks, with much difficulty we reach'd Helsingoer were we repaird our Vessel, and then saild to Gothenburg &amp; from thence
                  to Gibraltar In this voyage we fell among the Pirates, but happily escap'd
                  them. From thence I went in another Vessel by the way of Rouen
                  to Reval, from thence to Abo, and then to Bourdeaux; Here I saw a
                  <sic>Minester</sic>  <corr>Minister</corr> suffer death for the <sic>Gosple</sic>  <corr>Gospel</corr>, which went very near me but
                  I soon got rid of that Impression. At Copenhagen a sermon I heard
                  made me uneasy, but I soon recoverd again. From here I went to
                  Lisbon then to Amsterdam. After this I was cast away in a Vessel
                  <note type="catchword">that</note>
               </p>
         </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head type="page" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0185a-03">3</head>
               <p>
                  that saild from hence to Bergen in Norway, we lost all we had and was
                  Obliged to beg our Bread, till we could get on board another Vessel.
                  I came almost Naked to London, where I met with a Merchant who
                  tok me with him to Greifwalde- In our way to Stralsund we was
                  Obliged to cast our Leading overboard, and had no rest Night nor day.
                  After we came to Stralsund, I stay'd there the winter over, but my
                  wicked Life soon brought me into Prison. After I had been 4 Weeks
                  confin'd, and reflected on my wrteched state, My hard heart broke &amp;
                  and I fell into despair, yea I would fain have put an end to my Life.
                  I resolv'd to turn Soldier, but no One would take me because I was
                  too Wicked for them. Upon this I ran away from Stralsund to Anelam In a
                  deep snow, without a coat to my Body, or a shoe on my feet. I bargaind
                  with a Captain of a <sic>Vesel</sic>  <corr>Vessel</corr> to sail in his ship, and offerd to work for
                  him tell the Vessel sail'd, but he was afriad of me, and took me to
                  be a thief and a <sic>Murtherer</sic>  <corr>Murderer</corr>, yet when I honestly told him how it had
                  gone with me, He <sic>keept</sic>  <corr>kept</corr> me out of Compassion tell the Vessel saild,
                  when we went to Danzig. Here I came among the Seperatists who
                  advised me to become Religious, telling me I was lost, if I continued my
                  present way of Life, which was my own thoughts. Coming a [2]d time
                  to Danzig I log'd with a pious Menonist, who was a Merchant and who hip
                  good Orders in his House. Out of kindness he offerd me his House, and
                  as I could write and keep Accounts would have employ'd me in his Home
                  but my Love to the sea, made me refuse his offers, Notwithstanding he
                  endeavour'd to <sic>diswade</sic>  <corr>dissuade</corr> me, and represented a Seamans Life very wicked.
                  Finding I was not be prevaild on to change my Mind, he <sic>recomended</sic>  <corr>recommended</corr> me
                  to the good Captains at Shettin and Konigsberg. But finding them
                  saild at my <sic>Arival</sic>  <corr>Arrival</corr> at Shettin, I went with Another who pretended
                  to much goodness, but I found him quite otherwise when we came
                  out to sea. The Pious Clergy at Konigsberg, often made me restless
                  and uneasy, I grew very Anxious concerning my situation, not only
                  the Law, but my own wicked heart condem'd me, yea the very Stones
                  in the Street seemd to Cry out against me, yea I was in my Own Eyesight the scum of all Mankind. In this situation I came to Shettin
                  and was bruoght to Pastor Sehinmeyer, he employ'd me in teaching the
                  Children at the free School, till the Orphan House he was then
                  <note type="catchword">Building</note>
                  
                  <cb/>
                  ///<lb/>
                  
                  Building was finish'd In to which I was also Admitted, here I was thoroughly
                  Awakened, and under such Concern for my Salvation, that I was day &amp;
                  Night at Prayers, so that my knees swell'd from constant kneeling.
                  I fasted often and shed thousands of tears for my Past Sins. In this
                  Distress our Saviour drew so near my heart, that it was to me as <sic>tho</sic>  <corr>though</corr> I saw
                  Him Bodily and embraced him. Yet I could not be at Rest, <sic>untell</sic>  <corr>until</corr> He
                  gave me the Certainty of His Forgiveness of my Sins, and Grace in his
                  Blood. My unbelief often caused doubts, and finding all manner of
                  Evil dwelling in me, I began to strive against <del>??</del> but all in Vain.
                  this <sic>weakned</sic>  <corr>weakened</corr> my Body greatly and I fell sick, neither did I recover <sic>untill</sic>  <corr>until</corr>
                  our Saviour gave me to feel his grace, which was a great Consolation
                  to me. After staying here a year and a half, I receivd a call to Landsberg on the
                  Water Where I taught in the Orphan House. From here I was call'd to
                  Zillichau where I saw the first B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>: from Herrnhuth, at my return to
                  Landsberg I receiv'd an Invitation to the Orphan House at Herrnhuth,
                  but had no Inclination to accept it. But receiving a second Invitation
                  and being advised not to decline the offer, but to follow Gods wink, I went.
                  At the first things did not go well with me, for I attaind not that
                  for which I came, and I could not forgo the Comdious Life I had been
                  used to, and suit my self to a poor way of Living. After staying there
                  half a Year I went to Sorace, and from thence to Chrishanstadt, where
                  I staid  stayed some time, and then pursued my Course to Stralsund, where I
                  found One of my Relations Living, who offerd me her House: But as
                  I was no longer of the World, our Friendship was soon at an end. At
                  Dargam I often visited the Awakened Souls, and the Clergy made
                  much of me. One of them took me to the Princess, to whom I gave 
                  an account of my Awakenining, and likewise some Information of
                  Herrnhuth. The next day she made me the offer of her Service, and
                  While I took the Matter into Consideration, I often held Meetings which
                  the Princess and her Court attended. But a New <sic>Minester</sic>  <corr>Minister</corr> coming
                  from Wernigerode, brought the Princess so many falsehoods from
                  Herrnhuth, that It was given me to understand I should depart:
                  upon which I went into Prusian Pomerania, and became Preceptor
                  to a Clergymans Children, <sic>keept</sic>  <corr>kept</corr> Meetings and had many hea[???].
                  Complaints was soon made to the Regency and the Clergy Examined
                  <note type="catchword">me</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head type="page" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0185a-04">4</head>
               <p>
                  me and alton'd me to ?????????? right, at which one of them was so en???
                  that he held a pistol to my Breast, but our Saviour preservd me from
                  getting hurt. This affair moved the General Field Marshal Tehweir
                  to send for me, but as soon as I was there, I was spoke against in every
                  Pulpit. The General not being able to quiet the rage of the Clergy,
                  I was examined by the Consistory, and aliho they could prove nothing
                  against me, was forbid to keep Meetings at the Castle. The General
                  often <sic>Perswaded</sic>  <corr>Persuaded</corr> me to Communicate, but the Parson would not allow
                  it; and when the Consistory gave him orders to Admit me, I was first
                  of all examined, in the <sic>Publich</sic>  <corr>Public</corr> Church, as tho  though I was to do Pennance
                  for some Crime, upon which I receiv'd the Sacrament. The general
                  finding that the Alarm concerning me increas'd, put me to an organist at Shettin, that I might learn to play on the organ. But here
                  Pastor Tehinmeyer <sic>perswaded</sic>  <corr>persuaded</corr> me to abide with Him, which I accordingly did. The year following a comapny of B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>: Pass'd <sic>thro</sic>  <corr>through</corr> Shettin
                  to Copenhagen. I visited them by Night, and my heart was so taken
                  with them, that I would fain have gone with them. Sometime after
                  The Consistory took me as a Preparant, but I would not Accept of
                  any Theological Office, the offer was made me of the first Civil or
                  Military Office that should present itself, after waiting 3 Years to
                  no purpose, I became Preceptor to a Gentlemans 7 Children here it
                  did not fail on good proposals, and I <sic>belive</sic>  <corr>believe</corr> I should have settled there
                  had not the Children been Seperated  Separated, after their Mothers Decease the
                  Relations taking of them. The prince of Anhaltzerlst, Governor of
                  Shettin, with whom I was acquainted, Procurd me a Controllers Office
                  which brought me a good Income, This Prince was very kind to me
                  and offer'd me a Helpmake out of his House, but that was on such
                  Conditions that I could not accept and for which reason I went to
                  Wolgast, and Altho a letter was sent after me, to <sic>enform</sic>  <corr>inform</corr> me that
                  all Difficulties was remov'd, yet I pursued my Journey to Stralsund,
                  intending to go to Stockholm. But Lieutenant Crassau had me
                  sought after, and took me with him to Rügen, where I taught
                  Children 2 Years and an half, and became acquainted with B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.
                  Schick. Here I learn'd to know myself more thoroughly, and found
                  <note type="catchword">that</note>
                  
                  <cb/>
                  ///<lb/>
                  
                  that I was no ???? poor?????? ?????? former Path was self made and
                  formal goodness, as I had many Na???? gifts. Now my Preaching was
                  sinful to me, and I found out my Envious heart because I was angry with
                  Brother Schick, notwithstanding he let me keep all the Meetings. On
                  account of these Meetings, myself and a Pastor was cited before the consistory, who forbid us keeping any more. B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Schick going soon after to the
                  Congregation, I would fain have gone with him, but as I had still many
                  doubts remaining concerning my livelihood, I suffer'd myself to be preswaded  persuaded
                  to stay with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Crassau, who was not willing to part with me. But soon
                  after the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>: Becklind and Linde comeing  coming to us, all my difficulties
                  Vanish'd, and I apointed  appointed the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May for my departure with the
                  Watch Word: <hi rend="underline">Is there any one that will go take him with ye</hi>. As I was
                  going to set out, 3 Sisters came who would go to the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. which the
                  B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>: thought Proper to send with me, tho  though I had no Inclination to do it
                  and really thought how to leave them on the way, but as I was crossing
                  a small Bridge over a <sic>Ditsch</sic> <corr>ditch</corr>, I fell into the water, and should have
                  been drown'd had not the Sisters been with me. The first'h Year
                  that I was at Herrnhaag, I was often in confusion concerning my outward affairs, and once on a Prayer day not being receiv'd into the
                  Congregation, I thought to go away, but our Saviour who had brought
                  me to the Cong.n drew so near my Heart, that I was quite bow'd in the
                  Dust before him, and the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of April 1744 I had the unspeakable
                  grace to be receiv'd into the Congregation. The B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>: going once to the
                  Lord Supper at Marienborn, had desired me to assist the Masons who
                  was building a Chimney, and I fell down from the upper story to the
                  ground, so that I was 15 weeks confined before I recoverd myself, as soon
                  as I got well, I went out to daily Labour, but could not hold it out and
                  was ill 7 weeks. The B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>: then put me to learn the Needle Makers
                  Trade. The 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of November 1746 I partook the holy Sacrament, from
                  which time on, I had a quiet cheerful and happy Path, and in the
                  year 1747 brother Johannes admitted into the single Brus Covenant.
                  In the Sifting Period 1748 I remaind still and quiet. The B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> would
                  fain have sent me on board the Irene as Cook of the Ship but my
                  Body was too weakly. In the year 1747 I came to Herrnhuth where
                  I was employ'd to sweep the House and Sleep Hall. In which year I was
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head type="page" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0185a-05">5</head>
               <p>    
                  was receivd among the ????? right at In the year 1753 I ???
                  to Ebersdorf where I work'd som????? at my Trade till in the year 1755 I ???
                  had the care of the Dining Room an Sleeping Hall.
                  In the year 1766 I became School and Recouing Master at Irebus,
                  But my ill State of Health preventing me from attending this Business so
                  faithfully as I could have wish'd, I gave it up to Another Brother, and
                  removed to my Choir House at Neisky, where in the year 1766 I was
                  receiv'd an Acccoluth. After I had a little regain'd my Health I was called
                  to an Employment at Barby, where I arrived the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of March 1767</p>
                  <p>Thus far his Own Words.</p>
                  <p>His continual Ill Health preventing his Business, He desired to be
                  taken again in the Choir House . and therefore accepted the call
                  to the B<hi rend="superscript">rns</hi> House here, with great Joy, and came hither the 3d of
                  October 1767 <sic>tho</sic>  <corr>though</corr> his ill Health continued here, yet he performd
                  the Office of Watchman of his Choir, with great faithfulness, had a
                  quiet cheerful and happy Walk among us, and testified a Desire
                  to go to Astracan; But it soon appeard our Saviour had other Intentions with him, for the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of October he took to his Bed. His
                  Illness which began with pain in the side, increas'd so, that it
                  was plain our Saviour hasten'd with his happiness; That blessed
                  Moment came the 19 Instant, in the afternoon when he departd
                  to ever Lasting Rest, during a fine Lihirgie, with the Blessing of
                  his Choir, and the Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. in the 57<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year of his Age.
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
