<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Georg Jacob Engelbach: Memoir <lang>English</lang>
            </title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator 2015-2018<orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives, Bethlehem</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir">Georg Jacob Engelbach (1709-1768)</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0186a-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0186a-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0186a-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0186a-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0186a-05.jpg" />                  
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text type="memoir" xml:id="MemBeth_0186a">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <head>Georg Jacob Engelbach</head>
         <div type="page" n="1" xml:id="div1">
            <head>Page 1 <seg ana="MemBeth_0186a-01" />
            </head>
            <p xml:id="p1">

                  Personals of our d.<hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> deceased Brother <hi rend="underline"><persName>George Jacob Engelbach</persName></hi> who departed to the
                  Joy of his Lord at <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName>
                  the <date>12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of November 1768</date>. The account he has left behind is as follows: </p>
            
               <p xml:id="p2">
                  Nothing but obedience moves me to give an account of my Path <sic>thro</sic>
                  <corr>through</corr> this dying Life. I had rather be Unknown and un= =noticed, to all but that loving heart beyond compare! to be known to <hi rend="underline">him</hi>
                  is all my wish and desire. </p>
            
               <p xml:id="p3">
                  I was born the <date>24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of October 1709</date> at <placeName>Auenheim</placeName> a Village near the <placeName>Rhine</placeName>, in which
                  Place my Father was Parson. My Mothers maiden Name was <persName>Michaelis</persName> and descended from <placeName>Polish Lissa</placeName>. In the year <date>1711</date>
                  myself and a younger Brother was deprived of our Father in our Tenderesh Infancy. After 3 years Widdowhood my Mother Married an Intendant of the Finaces named
                     <del>Aulber</del>
                  <persName><corr>Aulber</corr>
                  </persName>who removed in the year <date>1716</date> to <placeName>Bussweiler</placeName>
                  where he became <sic>Councellor</sic>
                  <corr>Counselor</corr> of the Finaces. Here I was sent to the Gymnasium where I saw and heard much evil, and as I grew older became sensible of the Hurt it was to me,
                  myself my own Brother, my Step Brother and a Relation of ours a <sic>Minesters</sic>
                  <corr>Ministers</corr> Son, soon found out that we was utterly corrupt= ed children. We 4 <abbr>join'd</abbr> together in a <del>Resolution</del> to give our Hearts to the Lord
                  Jesus, often we rose before day, went out into the Fields, <sic>kneelt</sic>
                  <corr>knelt</corr> down on our knees <sic>Weept</sic>
                  <corr>Wept</corr> and <abbr>pray'd</abbr> for better Hearts. As we saw no help for us it came in our Minds to go into the thickest <sic>Forrest</sic>
                  <corr>Forest</corr> to feed on grass and pray day and Night, that our poor Souls might be saved; But the severe and cruel treatment we met with from our Masters shifted
                  every thing. It is true that from time to time, we often felt anew the drawings of divine grace and I remember with shame and Bowedness, what my heart felt whenever
                  I read or heard any thing of our Saviour and his bleeding wounds, that presently melted my heart and Draw tears from my Eyes; Yet the <hi rend="underline"> in=
                     =dwelling</hi> Evil, and the <hi rend="underline">outward</hi> Descations which surrounded me <abbr>seemd</abbr>
                  to render my Conversion an Impossibility. Therefore I thought I would trust in the Lords long <abbr>suffring</abbr>; and hope that the Lord Jesus who once for all
                  had <abbr>suffer'd</abbr> death for me, would not suffer the <sic>Merrits</sic>
                  <corr>Merits</corr> of his bitter Passion to be lost on me, But would receive me to his </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="2" xml:id="div2">
            <head>Page 2 <seg ana="MemBeth-0186a-02" />
            </head>
            
            <p xml:id="p4">
                  his Mercy at the End of all Distress, as he did the Penitent Thief. In the Year <date>1726</date> I was sent to the University at <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>; In
                  the year <date>1727</date>
                  to <placeName>Jena</placeName> and <date>1728</date> to <placeName>Wittenberg</placeName>. Here that Corruption broke loose like a Deluge, which had hither to been
                     <abbr>restrain'd</abbr> by the Laws Severity, and I ran blindly into Sin, the wages of which quickly <abbr>follow'd</abbr>; some= =times I wept and cried to Jesus for
                  deliverance, but Sin became still more Sinful, till at length I was <sic>litterally</sic>
                  <corr>literally</corr> the express Picture of the Prodigal Son! and in the Year <date>1730</date> I actually set out for home with these Thoughts: I will return to my
                  severe Step Father; he may if he pleases make me his Servant! To such a pass I was come! Oh thou Merciful Lamb! thou has taken a poor Creature indeed to thy Mercy!
                  I was immediately put under the care of a Man who had formerly been our House Preceptor, but was now become Parson in a Country Village, who continued his usual rigorous
                  treatment of me. At length I grew weary of the distress which Sin occasioned humbled myself, and <abbr>beg'd</abbr> the Lord Jesus for support, would fain have been
                  converted but knew not where to begin, and to my Sor =row had no one to Inform me. I came into works, <abbr>pray'd</abbr> and wept, yet sin not being brought under
                     <sic>thro</sic>
                  <corr>through</corr> the Blood of Jesus con =tinued to rage the more in heart. In the year <date>1731</date> I was sent to the Seminary of the Candidates to the Pastoral
                  Office and was a Teacher in the Gynmnasium. O that I had but then been ac =quainted with my Bleeding Redeemer perhaps I should have been of Service to the Youth
                  under my care as they all loved me. In the Year <date>1733</date> I <abbr>receivd</abbr> ordination to a Preacher of the <sic>Gosple</sic>
                  <corr>Gospel</corr>
                  and in the Year <date>1734</date> was introduced as Deacon at <placeName>Ingweiler</placeName>
                  and teacher at <placeName>Ripperhweiler</placeName>. The office of a Teacher was weighty to me, I was <sic>truely</sic>
                  <corr>truly</corr> Sensible of my <sic>unworthyness</sic>
                  <corr>unworthiness</corr> and <sic>innability</sic>
                  <corr>inability</corr>
                  knew not which way to turn, <abbr>pray'd</abbr> frequent and fervently and yet continued unconverted, was forever Restless wept in private before the Lord Jesus and
                     <abbr>beg'd</abbr> for Mercy; my poor <abbr>distress'd</abbr>
                  heart <abbr>cleav'd</abbr> to him, and nothing was more pleasing to me than to preach of his Death and bleeding wounds, which I <sic>allways</sic>
                  <corr>always</corr> did <note type="catchword">with</note>
               
               <pb/>

                  with great Emotion, well knowing nothing but Jesus blood and wounds could sanctifyme poor wretched and corrupted Man; and I experi= =enced, that the word of his
                  Suff'rings was thunder which <sic>shoock</sic>
                  <corr>shook</corr>
                  my Soul and the Souls of my hearers. After I had been 16 Weeks at <placeName>Ingweiler</placeName>, I <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> a call to
                     <placeName>cron=Weissenburg</placeName>, I should have gone thither a year before, but as I was only <abbr>ask'd</abbr>
                  <sic>wether</sic>
                  <corr>whether</corr> I had a Mind to go there, and was not duely voted I thought I was free to refuse, and parson <persName>Heinold</persName> came there in my stead. I
                  had rather have <abbr>stay'd</abbr> in a Mean Village and known to few, but as I <abbr>observ'd</abbr> it was the Lords will, I concluded to accept the call,
                     <sic>altho</sic>
                  <corr>although</corr> I should follow my dear Step Brother <hi rend="underline"><persName>Aulbern</persName></hi> to his grave, who had been senior <persName>Aulber</persName>
                  in that city and <abbr>dy'd</abbr> in the Epedemical Fever which then <abbr>rag'd</abbr>
                  there. With the disposition of heart and Mind I went thither in <date>February 1735</date>. The largeness of the City, the number of Sick and abundance of Labour I
                  saw prepared for me made me Tremble, and I shall never forget with what a feeling, and with how many Tears I <sic>entred</sic>
                  <corr>entered</corr>
                  into my office. In <date>April 1756</date> I married my Step <abbr>B.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>
                  <persName>Shillers</persName>
                  <sic>Widdow</sic>
                  <corr>Widow</corr>
                  I knew not how to conduct myself according to our Saviours Mind in a Married State, notwithstanding we lived cheerful and happy together in our way, and every Body
                  regarded us as a Happy Pair. In <date>February 1737</date> our Saviour gave us a Daughter <persName>Marie Margaretta</persName>
                  and 13 Months after took her to himself in the Small Pox. In the same Year a Neghbouring Doctor of Physick sent me a Treatise against the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi
                     rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> Hymns. I <abbr>look'd</abbr> it <sic>thro</sic>
                  <corr>through</corr> and was for the first time convinced that <add>such</add> a people existed. At first I thought these are <persName>Schwenkfields</persName>
                  descendants, if their doctrine is false, it will evaporate Gods Word, and Luthers doctrine will never be <abbr>abolish'd</abbr>. But I found so much of Jesus Blood and
                  Wounds in these Hymns, that I was quite doubtful what to think, yea <add>was</add> quite confused for I could not remember that I had ever read in Church History of
                  a People that <sic>keept</sic>
                  <corr>kept</corr> to the word of Jesus Patience. <note type="catchword">And</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="page" n="3" xml:id="div3">
            <head>Page 3 <seg ana="MemBeth_0186a-03" />
            </head>
            
            <p xml:id="p5">and as my poor Heart, notwithstanding its Corruption was always <abbr>soften'd</abbr> and my Eyes swam in Tears whenever I read of Jesus <abbr>Suffring</abbr>
                  for the Sins of the World, I felt the same Emotion at reading these Hymns and had a desire to hear more of these people, and this I <abbr>obtain'd</abbr>
                  by means of my dear deceased Uncle <sic>Councellor</sic>
                  <persName><corr>Counselor</corr> Engelbach</persName> who was in <sic>Connexion</sic>
                  <corr>Connection</corr> with the <abbr>Brn</abbr>: I intreated him to send a <abbr>Br</abbr>. to me and in the year <date>1749</date> Old <persName>Brother Gold</persName> came
                  at My Request to my House on his Journey <sic>thro</sic>
                  <corr>through</corr> Our City. This Simple Country Man was a great Blessing to me. He <abbr>look'd</abbr> cheerful and happy, that I was not, and myself made confidence
                  in Jesus <sic>Merrits</sic>
                  <corr>Merits</corr> would not stand the Test, nor quiet the uneasiness of my heart. After this the <abbr>Brn</abbr>: freqeuntly <abbr>calld</abbr> to see me and when they
                  was gone my Conclusion was I am not like them, I do not know our Saviour. I wept and <abbr>pray'd</abbr> and <abbr>conferr'd</abbr> with my Colleague <persName>Pastor
                     Reinold</persName> but <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> poor comfort, often I <abbr>stretch'd</abbr> myself in the Dust and <abbr>beg'd</abbr> our Saviour to look graciously on
                  me, but in the Midst of my groans and Lamentations <add>it was</add> as <sic>tho</sic>
                  <corr>though</corr> a Voice within me said arise, you are not in Earnest, If I give you Honour, and leave you in your High Life, then I may be your Saviour of choice, but
                  it would not suit you to forgo all things for my sake, so as I have for your sake. I felt the Truth of this Reproach, and must be Silent. Mean time the uneasiness
                  of my Soul still <abbr>increas'd</abbr>
                  I began to mourn and lament again, but as it <sic>allways</sic>
                  <corr>always</corr> turns out Fruitless; the Enemy put it in my Mind that I was a cast away, our Saviour neither would, nor could be Merciful to such a sinner. This
                  went so far that I was actually be= =tween Atheism and Desperation. I could no longer Pray but wherever I <abbr>turn'd</abbr> cried out: Oh Jesu Oh Jesu! The <date>26<hi
                        rend="superscript">>th</hi>
                      of October 1744</date> when my distress <abbr>seemd</abbr> to be at the highest Pitch, I was reading the French News Paper, and all at once I was struck with
                  these words which <abbr>seemd</abbr> as <sic>tho</sic>
                  <corr>though</corr> they was spoke in my heart: canst thou read that, and hast no Saviour <note type="catchword">This</note>
               
               <pb/>

                  This <abbr>shock'd</abbr> me so, that I let the Paper fall out of my Hands and fell after it to the Earth. I had no utterance for words, but wept for Mercy, and
                  gave myself <sic>intirely</sic>
                  <corr>entirely</corr> up to our Saviour without the least limitation, that with me he might do, whats pleasing in his sight, and from me take <sic>whatere</sic>
                  <corr>whatever</corr> he will, <sic>whatere</sic>
                  <corr>whatever</corr> he thinks not right. To me it was as <sic>tho</sic>
                  <corr>though</corr> I then <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> permission to kiss the Prints of the Nails in his sacred Feet! I felt a Di= =vine assurance of the forgiveness of my
                  Sins, and <add>the</add> covenant I then made, is still sure and firm, my heart is no longer mine, but His. I shall not say much of what <abbr>follow'd</abbr> this
                  change. The want of a true poor Sinner heart often <abbr>caus'd</abbr> me to commit great failings. The <abbr>Awaken'd</abbr> Souls keeping to me, Brought on
                     <add>me</add> the displeasure of the School Master, My Colleague, the Mayor of the City and all the Mages= =tracy of the Lutheran Side, One Honest
                     <sic>Councellor</sic>
                  <corr>Counselor</corr> excepted. The Process at <placeName>Strassburg</placeName>
                  <persName>D.</persName><hi rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>Froereisen</persName> would have me <abbr>turn'd</abbr> out of my Office by the Civil
                  Magistrates, and so it went on, till the year <date>1748</date>. Mean time our Saviour gave me more <sic>oppertunitys</sic>
                  <corr>opportunities</corr> of becoming acquainted with the <abbr>Brn</abbr>: and in the year <date>1747</date> I made a 12 days visit at <placeName>Herrnhaag</placeName>
                  to my great Blessing. I was soon convinced that I be= =longed to this People, but how, or when, my dear Saviour would bring me thither, that I did not dare to Consider
                  on, this I knew; it must <sic>thro</sic>
                  <corr>through</corr> a Miracle, otherwise it could not come to Pass. After this Blessed Visitation, the Enemy grew more <sic>inraged</sic>
                  <corr>engraged</corr>, and I became a detestation to the whole City except the <abbr>Awakend</abbr> Souls; but my heart was <sic>chearful</sic>
                  <corr>cheerful</corr> and happy, I supplicated and <abbr>obtain'd</abbr> of my dear Lord a Promise, which was a great Consolation to me. In <date>Au=  =gust 1749</date>
                  my dear Wife took to her Bed, and in this her last Ill= =ness she felt she was a wretched Sinner, <abbr>begd</abbr> for Mercy and openly <abbr>confess'd</abbr> she had
                  sought the World more than our Saviour, and fell asleep with this fervent wish: Shelter my Soul most gra= =ciously within thy <abbr>open'd</abbr> Side; In the 36 year of
                  her age. <note type="catchword">As</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="page" n="4" xml:id="div4">
            <head>Page 4 <seg ana="MemBeth_0186a-04" />
            </head>
            
            <p xml:id="p6">as I <abbr>observ'd</abbr> above, I had <abbr>obtain'd</abbr> a promise from our dear Saviour that I should come to his People, but that did not come to pass till
                  the year <date>1756</date>. In the year <date>1751</date> I came to <placeName>Treweiler</placeName> as Chaplain and Inspector. Here at length the Hour of my deliverance
                  struck. I was severly taken to task for my <sic>Conexion</sic>
                  <corr>Connection</corr> with the <abbr>Brns</abbr>
                  <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> and after several storms I was required to seperate myself from them, to quit The Herrnhuters Errors, to deny
                  the People of God and condemn their Doctrine. This I could not do, but chose rather to bear the Reproach of Christ and was also removed, and sat out for
                     <placeName>Newwied</placeName> in the Year <date>1756</date>. Here I became partak- =er of the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> Grace and the
                  same year attaind to the Parti= =cipation of the Greatest Good in the Holy Sacrament, with the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> The Next Year
                  I <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> a Call from the Countess to be her Chaplain and to preach a Sermon every Sunday at her <sic>Chapple</sic>
                  <corr>Chapel</corr>, which I accepted with the Consent of my <abbr>Brn</abbr>: and continued in this office <sic>untill</sic>
                  <corr>until</corr> the year <date>1759</date> In which year I attended the Disciples Household which spent some weeks to all and Particularly to my great Blessing at
                     <placeName>Newwied</placeName> and went with them to <placeName>Holland</placeName>. Shortly before Christmas I <abbr>returnd</abbr> with the same hither to
                     <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> and removed into my beloved Choir House in which during an abode of near 4 years I have had the Happiness to enjoy Numberless
                  Blessings and <sic>Benifits</sic>
                  <corr>Benefits</corr>. </p>
            
               <p xml:id="p7">
                  Thus far his own Words. By reason of the Vacancy at <placeName>Berthelsdorff</placeName>
                  <abbr>occasion'd</abbr> by the death of <abbr>Br</abbr>. <persName>Groh</persName>our<abbr>d.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> Brother often
                     <abbr>preach'd</abbr> there with great Blessing so as he likewise frequently <abbr>Preach'd</abbr> here in <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> on Sundays. In the Fall of
                  the year <date>1763</date> he <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> a call to preach the <sic>Gosple</sic>
                  <corr>Gospel</corr>
                  at the little church in <placeName>Altona</placeName> which he cheerfully accepted of from our Saviours Hands and sat our for that place in <date>September</date>.
                  His much blessed service in the <sic>Gosple</sic>
                  <corr>Gospel</corr> at that Place our <abbr>Brn</abbr> and Sisters have heard in the Journals. His Sermons was so much fre= =quented that Room often <abbr>faild</abbr>
                  the Hearers, And we have many <note type="catchword">living</note>
                  <pb type="double_right" />
                  being witnesses which prove that his Testimony was attended with Spirit and power. In the Year <date>1767</date> he visited the Directorey at <placeName>Zeyst</placeName>
                  where he stayd 2 Months to his great Blessing as he has <abbr>expres'd</abbr> both verbally and in his Letters. Towards the Latter end of <date>June</date> this year
                  He came hither with our <abbr>d.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> Lords Approbation for to rest and refresh himself. He <abbr>enterd</abbr> his Choir
                  House in a weakly state of Body but with Joy and thankful Tears, moved into his former Chamber, com= =mended himself to his <abbr>Brns</abbr>: Love and Favour and told
                  them our Saviour would prepare and soon take him to Rest. He was very tender and Affectionate and saluted every <abbr>Br</abbr> he saw with much Love. Often express
                  how happy he was in living among his People and <sic>injoying</sic>
                  <corr>enjoying</corr> all good things in the Lords House daily. He never <abbr>miss'd</abbr> the Meetings notwithstanding his weakness often <sic>keept</sic>
                  <corr>kept</corr> the Morning and Evening Meetings in his Choirs house and spoke tender Evangelical with such <abbr>Brn</abbr> as he was particularly
                     <sic>accquainted</sic>
                  <corr>acquainted</corr> with and was Legitamated as a faithful Heart towards our Saviour and the <abbr>Brn</abbr>. His Heart was devoted to our Saviour, and
                     <abbr>attach'd</abbr> to his <abbr>Suffrings</abbr> as a poor Sinner, and <abbr>cleav'd</abbr> to him with Body and Soul. Often this Expression was <sic>dropt</sic>
                  <corr>dropped</corr> from his Lips: Oh that Mer= =ciful and Long <abbr>Suffring</abbr> heart of Jesus! O that Merciful and long <abbr>Suffring</abbr> Heart. The
                        <date>8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>of October</date> he was at the Love feast and the Holy Sacrament. The next day it <abbr>appeard</abbr> plainer that he would
                  not continue here much Longer, he set his outward <sic>afairs</sic>
                  <corr>affairs</corr>
                  in order that he might be quite easy in regard to what he should leave behind him. The <date>10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> he joyfully took to his Bed and be-
                  =gan to speak fervently to our Saviour and said with numberless Tears: Oh thou most beloved Heart! Merciful Long <abbr>Suffring</abbr> and of great Goodness and
                  Truth; Oh Lord Jesus how shall I sufficiently thank thee; I am not worthy of such Love grace and <sic>Benifits</sic>
                  <corr>Benefits</corr>
                  which thou has <abbr>bestow'd</abbr> on me. After a little pause he resumed his Disourse which had been interrupted by the Floods of Tears which <abbr>flow'd</abbr>
                  from his Eyes and concluded with this verse Oh did each Pulse thy Praises beat, each breath my thankfulness repeat. <note type="catchword">He</note>
               </p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="page" n="5" xml:id="div5">
             <head>Page 5 <seg ana="MemBeth_0186a-05" />
             </head>
            
            <p xml:id="p8">He spent his time in earnest longing to be with his beloved Jesus His Memory had been for some time pretty much <abbr>d</abbr> and he seldom attended to what was
                     <abbr>talk'd</abbr> off, But when the Discourse <abbr>turn'd</abbr> to heart Matters, he was presently cheerful and attentive expressing himself in such a Manner that
                  it was a pleasure to hear him He <abbr>believ'd</abbr> his most beloved and Faithful Friend would soon call him to his Presence, and would not take any Medicines: Sayings
                  nothing keeps me and nothing helps me Yet when he was <sic>perswaded</sic>
                  <corr>persuaded</corr> not to refuse the Application of Medicines <sic>intirely</sic>
                  <corr>entirely</corr>, then he was childlike and said do what you will with your poor Engelbach you are good Bretheren, Oh you give yourselves so much trouble I know it
                  very well and am sorry for it I will be obedient but you must have a great deal of Patience with me. Often he <abbr>pour'd</abbr> out his heart before our Saviour and
                  repeated incessantly this Request Oh take me hearts beloved Saviour there is nothing between us we understand each other I am ready. After the <sic>Injoyment</sic>
                  <corr>Enjoyment</corr> of the Holy Sacrament on the <date>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> Instant he counted the days and hours and <abbr>sigh'd</abbr> in a moving
                  Manner come dear Saviour come and take me. The Oppression at his Breast deprived <add>him</add> of the freedom of Speech but he was attentive to all that
                     <abbr>pass'd</abbr> and made signs and <abbr>smild</abbr> on the <abbr>Brn</abbr>: that came to see him in which manner he likewise <abbr>express'd</abbr> his desire
                  to receive the Last Blessing, and with great difficulty pronounced the words: He hastens! The <date>12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date> at noon he folded his Hands
                  and received the Blessing of the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> and his Choir and God. With the verse: Now let his Mouth Expiring on thy
                  dear Breast recline &amp;c<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> his Breath <abbr>stopd</abbr> and he fell sweetly <sic>assleep</sic>
                  <corr>asleep</corr> leaving a fine look on his Countenance Aged 59 Years 19 days. </p>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
