<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>John Friedrich Gocht: Memoir
            </title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator 2015-2018<orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives, Bethlehem</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0199">John Friedrich Gocht</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-04.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>John Friedrich Gocht</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head>Page 1 <seg ana="MemBeth_0199a-01" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap />Personals of our <hi rend="underline">Worthy <persName>Brother John Friedrich Gocht</persName></hi> who departed this Life the <date>31<hi rend="underline"><hi
                           rend="superscript">st</hi></hi>. of January 1769.</date> at <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName>. <gap />He left the following written Account of his Path I was born at
                     <placeName>Ni</placeName><hi rend="underline"><placeName>eder Oderwiz</placeName>
                  </hi>the <date>30<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" />. of December 1697</date> and brought up by my Parents to all good. From my Infancy
                  I had no Talent for the World, yet my Corruption lay the deeper. In time I had an insight into the Holy Ghosts seeking my heart which I then did not understand. At length I became
                     <abbr>concernd</abbr> for my Salvation, more particularly in my 14<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" />. Year when I partook the Holy
                  Sacrament the first time at which I shed many Tears. <gap />After this I came into a Light wordly minded way and went on some Years under Divine Patience, <abbr>Till</abbr> Divine
                  Love <abbr>Touch'd</abbr> my Heart, and convinced me of my unbelief in the time of <date>Lent 1719</date>. <gap />In the Passion Week my Continual Prayer was, that our Saviour would
                  have Mercy on me, and grant me the <sic>Benifit</sic>
                  <corr>Benefit</corr> of his Precious Blood Shedding. My Request that he would graciously Pleased to look favourably on me was granted and I <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> Comfort, It came in
                  my Mind that I could be <abbr>helpd</abbr> if I would apply to our Saviour as a poor Sinner. But the Sinner =ship was a Mystery, I rather <abbr>employ'd</abbr> myself in Reading and
                  An= =xious seeking. To this was added thy intention to Marry. After praying to God to give me a Person wholly devoted to him, I married the <date>19<hi rend="underline"><hi
                           rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" />. of <abbr>Novem</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"
                         /><abbr>.</abbr> 1723</date> |:the present <sic>Widdow</sic>
                  <corr>Widow</corr>:| Our Saviour <abbr>bless'd</abbr> us with 3 Sons and 1 Daughter, but has taken Them all 4 to himself I <abbr>endeavourd</abbr> to the Uttmost of my Power to act
                  up to the best of my know= =ledge, yet my heart was without feeling, <sic>untill</sic>
                  <corr>until</corr> Eternal Love brought a Text of Scripture to my Mind at the time I was <abbr>employ'd</abbr> in my Business the Text was this: as many as are led by the Spirit
                     <add>they</add> are the Sons </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head>Page 2 <seg ana="MemBeth_0199a-02" />
               </head>
               <p> of God. This <abbr>caus'd</abbr> me great Concern. I <abbr>pray'd</abbr> and Sigh Shew me thy ways <abbr>O</abbr> Lord that I may <sic>walth</sic>
                  <corr>walkth</corr> in thy Truth! He <abbr>answerd</abbr> me I will direct thee and shew the way thou shalt go, I will guide thee with my Eyes. About this time there was a great
                     <abbr>awakning</abbr> at <add><placeName>Oderwitz</placeName></add> which I would fain have <abbr>joind</abbr>, but at first, fear of Man gave me much trouble, yet I was convinced
                  in my heart that I should find what I sought. I went to <placeName>Berthrelsdorff</placeName> and heard <persName>Pastor Rothe</persName> preach |:which I had done once before:| and
                  in his Sermon he gave me such a plain description of my State of Soul as <abbr>tho</abbr> I had before told him of it. And now the <sic>perscecution</sic>
                  <corr>persecution</corr> began which did not terrifyme, I felt peculiar Grace in my heart, and had I <abbr>remaind</abbr> in my Simplicity, I should have avoided many a heavy hour
                  But instead of that I came into self Workings, I went to the Parson and told him my whole State he often told me I was in the right way I should only pray to God to bring me further
                  in his Grace but no sooner did he see that I conversed with souls who were convinced how wrong their former Life had been then he <abbr>indea-</abbr>
                  <abbr>=vourd</abbr> to hinder me all he could. The Meetings at <placeName>Oderwitz</placeName> was forbidden, and a great Number was Arrested and taken to
                     <placeName>Zittau</placeName>. As I was much <abbr>concern'd</abbr> about these people I went a few days after to enquire <sic>wether</sic>
                  <corr>whether</corr> they were set at Liberty or not. Just as I came to <persName>Gottlieb Webers</persName> House 2 Men laid hold of me and would carry me before a Justice, not
                  knowing for what cause, I refused to comply, they broke their Sticks over my head and so evil intreated me that I fell to the Earth without <sic>Sensce</sic>
                  <corr>Sense</corr> or Motion, a Number of People being <abbr>gatherd</abbr> the Men made off, as soon as I came to myself my first thought was:Lord forgive them. I went home and felt
                  very happy The Next day I could scarce hold up my Head for Pain. I now <sic>keept</sic>
                  <corr>kept</corr> quiet at home and only went now and then to Church some time after the Lord of the Place sent an Officer to bring me before him and <abbr>ask'd</abbr> me,
                     <sic>wether</sic>
                  <corr>whether</corr> I acknowledged the Articles <abbr>deliverd</abbr>
                  <pb /> at <placeName>Zittau</placeName> against The Clergy. <gap />I could not then do otherwise but Answer Yes. <gap />Hereupon he committed me to Prison. I was quite alone there,
                  and was often <abbr>ask'd</abbr> if I would not change my Mind, but I could not. The Justice tried the Serpents Wisdom and told me I should only Ask Pardon and all would be well. I
                  was in a great Strait yet promised to do so. An Officer brought me then to the Parson to Ask his Pardon. I thought with my tongue I will do it, but my Heart shall not give its
                  Consent. But no sooner had the Words <abbr>pass'd</abbr> my Lips then my Distress was greater than I can Express. I <abbr>begd</abbr> and <abbr>pray'd</abbr> Oh dearest Saviour! do
                  not cast me off forever. I went to the Parson and told him how I felt since my Rescinding, that the blessed Application of Jesus Merrits and death to my heart, was now quite gone and
                     <abbr>Vanish'd</abbr> He tried to make me easy by saying It would be all well again in a short time soon After Notice was given me by An Officer sent from the Lord of the Place,
                  That I should in a short time leave the Town I went to <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> and found there an <sic>Habbitation</sic>
                  <corr>Habitation</corr>. In <date>August 1728</date> I moved thither with my Family <abbr>altho</abbr> with a Wounded and grieved Heart, and went on in my Misery and Distress above 3
                  Years, and then My heart was Softened and Melted <abbr>thro</abbr> the Love and Grace of the <sic>faithfull</sic>
                  <corr>faithful</corr> Friend of Sinners so that I had some hopes of Comfort. <gap />One Morning when I took my little <persName>Anna Rosina</persName> out of Bed I <abbr>ask'd</abbr>
                  her what Verse she would give me, and she repeated such a Sweet Comfortable one that my Heart was enlarged so that I could lay myself as a poor lost Sinner at the Feet of Jesus and
                  find all the Blame in me then I found enough cause to be a Sinner and obtained an insight into the bleeding and Sacrifice of Jesus in which alone I could obtain Grace Mercy and
                  forgiveness of Sins. <gap />Soon after the dear Disciple sent for me and <abbr>ask'd</abbr> me <sic>wether</sic>
                  <corr>whether</corr> I was willing to be in a Band which <persName><abbr>Br.</abbr> Tobias Friedrick</persName>
                  <sic>keept</sic>
                  <corr>kept</corr>? This I <abbr>look'd</abbr> upon as a great <note type="catchword">Favour</note>
                  <note type="catchword">and</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head>Page 3 <seg ana="MemBeth_0199a-03" />
               </head>
               <p> and our Saviour <sic><abbr>oppend</abbr></sic><abbr> </abbr><corr><abbr>opend</abbr></corr> my Heart which was formerly <abbr>seald</abbr> up so that I could tell my whole
                  Situation. I likewise <abbr>obtaind</abbr> the unspeak =able Favour to partake the Holy Sacrament with the Congregation That was a happy Moment. I <abbr>look'd</abbr> on myself as a
                  poor Sinner who <abbr>obtaind</abbr> Salvation purely out of free Grace and Mercy and com= =mended myself to the failthful care and Protection of our dear Saviour, and the Maternal
                  Tuition of the Holy Spirit. when I arose in the Morning my first thoughts were <gap /><abbr>O</abbr> that I might neither think speak or hear of any thing but thy Love and thee,
                  <gap />and his Grace lead me happily, yet still a time came <sic>wherin</sic>
                  <corr>wherein</corr> I felt myself so cold and in such dryness that I <sic>staid</sic>
                  <corr>stayed</corr> away from the Holy Sacra =ment. I was much troubled and <abbr>beg'd</abbr> our dear Saviour for forgive =ness, and he again <abbr>bless'd</abbr> me with his
                  Peace. Just then the Word for the Day was, Ye Husbands pray without doubting My Prayer was. <abbr>O</abbr> let me in thy Nail <unclear>prints</unclear> see, my Pardon &amp; Election
                  free and I heard the Blessed words in my Heart: behold I have gra= =ven thee in the Palms of my Hands. In the Year <date>1736</date> I was admitted among the <orgName>hourly
                     Intercessors</orgName>. Then I experienced what that is to be with the Spouse quite lonely and to pray for the whole <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"
                           ><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" /><abbr>. Yea</abbr> for our dear Saviours whole Kingdom. 3 Years after I became Sick Waiter. I <abbr>beg'd</abbr> our
                  Saviour to give me wisdom and an humble lowly Sinner Heart I was in this Important Office near 10 Years and <abbr>perform'd</abbr> it with great Will =ingness. In the Year
                     <date>1741</date> the <orgName>Priesterly Office of Night Watch =man</orgName> came to be my Lot. My Bodily Weakness made me at first somewhat <sic>Scrupelous</sic>
                  <corr>Scrupulous</corr> but I soon <sic>recolected</sic>
                  <corr>recollected</corr> the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><abbr>.</abbr> has <sic>apointed</sic>
                  <corr>appointed</corr> the to it, if it is our dear Saviours Will that thou shalt serve him in this Office he will give the Strength to execute it, I therefore undertook it in his
                  Name on the <date>7<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" />. of August</date> I <abbr>resign'd</abbr> myself to our Saviours Grace and the
                  Angels Protection: And our dear Saviour gave me his poor Sinner who had nothing but his Grace to feel and see that <note type="catchword">He</note>
                  <pb /> He was with me and supported me. <gap />Soon after the Office of <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"
                      /><abbr>.</abbr>
                  <sic>Desciples</sic>
                  <corr>Disciples</corr> being introduced My Wife and I had the favour of being the first Married Pair that had this Priesterly <sic>Honnour</sic>
                  <corr>Honour</corr> this <abbr>bow'd</abbr> my heart in Dust before our Saviour. <gap />And Since then, as Often as I have had the fa= =vour of being Congregation or Choir Disciple,
                  My heart has <abbr>enjoyd</abbr> a new Blessing and my Cheeks has been wetted with Sinner Tears. <gap />In the Month of <date>June 1760</date> such a Weakness came over me, that I
                  was obliged to resign my important <orgName>Office of Watchman</orgName> in <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> the <date>15<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" />. of June</date> being the last Night in which I <abbr>watch'd</abbr>. My Weakness <abbr>increas'd</abbr> so, that I was in great hopes I should soon
                  depart from this Vale of Tears, but that Hour is not yet come. I have been obliged to miss many fine Meetings it is true yet his sweet Nearness has often made me many a Happy Hour in
                  my Chamber the <date>15<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" />. of February 1762</date> I had a most peculiar Hour of Grace which I no more
                  expected in this Life, which was that <persName><abbr>Br.</abbr> Gregor</persName>
                  <abbr>surrender'd</abbr> the Con= =gregation Discipleship to me in my Sick Chamber It was as <abbr>tho</abbr> a Stream of Mercy and Grace was <abbr>pourd</abbr> out over me and I
                     <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> that favour with Sinner Shame &amp; bowedness and with many Tears! <gap />Thus far his Own Words. </p>
               <p> Our dear Brothers <sic>Charactor</sic>
                  <corr>Character</corr> is known to the whole Congregation. He was indeed a faithful Heart, quite in Love with the most Fairest and Beauteous Saviour He was Legitimated as such and we
                  can give him the Attestation of his being a true Liturgus. <gap />He <abbr>pray'd</abbr> without ceasing, and made it his real concern to Commend to our dear Lords Blessing and
                  Protection the increase of his Kingdom The whole <abbr>Brns told</abbr>
                  <note type="catchword">the</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head>Page 4 <seg ana="MemBeth_0199a-04" />
               </head>
               <p> the Congregation and Choirs and especially the Directorium. He often <abbr>express'd</abbr> how weighty the <orgName>Office of Watchman</orgName> had been to him.
                     <gap /><abbr>Thro</abbr> our Saviours Grace every Night for 19 Years he <abbr>watchd Pray'd</abbr> and <abbr>perform'd</abbr> the High priestly office of off= <sic>=ring</sic>
                  <corr>=ering</corr> the Incense of Tears &amp; Supplications and edified the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi
                     rend="superscript" /><abbr>.</abbr> with his agreeable Singing which has often been a means to make Strangers praise the Name of the Lord, He has <abbr>refreshd</abbr> the Sick in
                  their sleepless Nights and reminded them of the faithful Keeper of Israel the Watchman of Soul &amp; Body. The more this Office was of Weight to him, the greater was his Grief that
                  his weakly Body obliged him to give the Post of Watchman to the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><abbr>.</abbr> He then went on
                  his Path in Converse with the Man of Sorrows which <abbr>shorten'd</abbr> the days of his waiting at the healing Ponds. <gap />About 3 Months ago <gap />he was out the last time and
                     <abbr>refresh'd</abbr> his Heart at the Post Communion in the Hall. Since then he spent his time in Stillness hoping and Longing for departure and as often as he was
                     <abbr>askd</abbr> how he found himself his Answer was that he was happy in the Wounds of Jesus- <gap />The <date>31<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" />. of January</date> his last Hour <abbr><sic>aproachd</sic>
                     <corr>approachd</corr></abbr>
                  <persName><abbr>Br.</abbr> John Nitschman</persName> held him a much blessed Liturgy and imparted to him the Blessing of the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi
                        rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript" /><abbr>.</abbr> and his Choir- During the Singing Hour his Soul took its flight to Jesus Arms and Bosom and
                  left the Body a fine Priestly Countenance after have dwelt in this Mortal Tent near 72 Years. - </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
