<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[NAME]: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Social Sciences Librarian</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Courtney Paddick</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Arts &amp; Humanities Librarian</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribers and encoders, HUMN100 Fall 2018</resp>
               <persName>Allison Butler</persName>
               <persName>Bhagawat Acharya</persName>
               <persName>Brendan Matthys</persName>
               <persName>Caleb Broughton</persName>
               <persName>Carly Pavoni</persName>
               <persName>Caroline Walsh</persName>
               <persName>Clayton Wright</persName>
               <persName>Ethan Conklin</persName>
               <persName>George Tyler</persName>
               <persName>Hailey Zimmerman</persName>
               <persName>Jacob Hubbard</persName>
               <persName>Jessica Hom</persName>
               <persName>Julianna Kim</persName>
               <persName>Mauricio Martinez</persName>
               <persName>Mitch Gavars</persName>
               <persName>Meg Koczur</persName>
               <persName>Morgan Graning</persName>
               <persName>Nathan Ware</persName>
               <persName>Olivia Smith</persName>
               <persName>Paige Whitney</persName>
               <persName>Raleigh Singer</persName>
               <persName>Rosemary Rong</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Salazar</persName>
               <persName>Zakee Willis</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>              
            </respStmt>   
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Repository Name</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir">Name Date</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-03.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>Elizabeth Grundy</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head>Page 1 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  -Vo.10. G. Gd Life I. Holmes<br />
                  of the widow <persname><abbr>Sr.</abbr> Elizabeth Grundy</persname>, late Alvd,<br />
                  who departed thei life at <placename>Nayldon</placename> in <placename>York-<br />
                     shire</placename>, <date>May&nbsp;<u>the 9<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;1799</u></date><u>.</u><br />
                  She has dictated the following account of her<br />
                  life to her son, our <abbr>Br.</abbr>&nbsp;<persname>James Grundy</persname>:<br />
                  I was born <date>February 6. 1717</date>. near <placename>Chowbent</placename><br />
                  in the parish of <placename>Leigh</placename> in <placename>Lancashire</placename>, and<br />
                  brought up in the Presbyterian persuasion.<br />
                  My parents were very pious, and educated their<br />
                  children with great strictness. I was the youn-<br />
                  gest of their daughters. Whenever I did any<br />
                  thing amiss, my mother used to preach the Law<br />
                  to me, which made me look upon <persname>God</persname> as an an-<br />
                  gry Being. In my 8<sup><u>th</u>&nbsp;</sup>year that I had the follow-<br />
                  ing dream: I dreamed it was the day of judg-<br />
                  ment, and I saw an innumerable multitude<br />
                  around me. I wished to see our Savior but was<br />
                  afraid of being seen by him; however, as I thought,<br />
                  I moved forward, and thrust myself between&nbsp;<br />
                  two persons to have a right of him. This I had<br />
                  no sooner done than he turned to me, as he&nbsp;<br />
                  was sitting at a table, and smiled. Hereby I was<br />
                  to much encouraged, that I went strait up to<br />
                  him, and now I saw two books lying before
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head>Page 2 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  34<br />
                  seductive spirit of the world prove a comfort and joy to<br />
                  this venerable assembly of his Servants, it will then be<br />
                  likewise a joyful reward to them for all their trouble, and<br />
                  Labour, which will thereby be rendered more easy and pleasant<br />
                  to them. I now wait as a poor pardoned and happy sinner<br />
                  for that blessed moment, when my dear and merciful Saviour<br />
                  who has done unspeakably much for me, will come and<br />
                  fetch me to be where he is himself (which word of his<br />
                  <emotion>made once a very comfortable and blessed impression upon<br />
                     my mind,</emotion> so that it has occured to me again, continually<br />
                  with the same sweet impression.) I know of no other pre-<br />
                  -paration for that momentous and awful change [?]<br />
                  that he has washed me from my sins in his own blood, and<br />
                  preserves me in the enjoyment of his grace and the communion<br />
                  with his own dear Person, <abbr>till</abbr> my last breath. <abbr>O</abbr> may he gracious<br />
                  -ly grant it me for his own sake Amen.<br />
                  &nbsp;&nbsp; <date><abbr>Dec</abbr></date><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><date><abbr>r</abbr></date></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi><date> 4</date><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi></hi><date><br />
                     &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp; 1798.</date><br />
                  Our dear late Brother has given so full an account of him<br />
                  -self and of his course amongst us, that we have little to add.<br />
                  During the remaining 3 years of his life, he remained insanably<br />
                  the mind, praying for, and recommending the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="superscript"></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi> in <placename>Fulneck</placename><br />
                  the <abbr>H. E.</abbr> Conference the whole Unity with all its divisions, and<br />
                  heathen Missions, to the guidance and blessing of our dear Lord<br />
                  <sic>untill</sic>&nbsp; <corr>until</corr> his very last moments. His public Sermons and his<br />
                  Discourses to the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi> were anointed, and as they came<br />
                  from a heart, of which it was very perceptible that it lives<br />
                  in the enjoyment of that which he recommended to others,<br />
                  they were blessed to those who heard him. And there never<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head>Page 2 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  him. One of them he opened, which I took to be the<br />
                  book of life, as it appeared written with blood. Upon<br />
                  this I awoke, but the dream left an impression<br />
                  upon my mind, that our Savior was very loving<br />
                  however, I left it again by having the law prea-<br />
                  ched to me. Thus I spent my years of child-<br />
                  hood like most others. I wanted to be good,<br />
                  but could not. Still I depended much on be-<br />
                  ing born of religious parents, as being the seed&nbsp;<br />
                  of the righteous, upon which the <orgname>Presbyterians</orgname><br />
                  of that day laid great stress.<br />
                  My father dying in my 12<sup><u>th</u></sup>&nbsp;year, my mother<br />
                  was left to care for our education, and to provide<br />
                  for our maintenance. The latter she did by kee-<br />
                  ping a school, and the former she performed in<br />
                  the strictest manner, and she sometimes cor-<br />
                  rected us very sharply, as she took <persname>Solomon&#39;s</persname><br />
                  words for her rank: &quot;He that shareth the rod,<br />
                  &nbsp;hateth his son &#39;_&#39; Train up a child in the way<br />
                  he should go, and when he is old he will not de-<br />
                  part from it.&quot;<br />
                  Before my fathers death I had a fever, which,<br />
                  with occasional intermissions, lasted 18 weeks,<br />
                  but I always thought I should recover.&nbsp;<br />
                  When I was 14 years old I went to nurse a child<br />
                  of a relation; and going on to see my mother<br />
                  our Savior drew me in to my heart on the road:<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head>Page 3 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  and in my prayer I addressed him as the God of<br />
                  <persname>Abraham</persname>, <font color="#c86309">Isaac</font>&nbsp;and <persname>Jacob</persname>. It came into my<br />
                  mind to make a covenant with him, and then<br />
                  being some stones in the place, I took them for<br />
                  a witness of it. But I soon broke this covenant,<br />
                  for getting into company I lived like others,<br />
                  yet my conscience always condemned me.<br />
                  Thus I formed good resolutions and as often brake<br />
                  them again; still the Lord pursued me with<br />
                  infinite patience.<br />
                  In my 22<sup><u>nd</u></sup>&nbsp;year I <sic>comenced</sic>&nbsp; <corr>commenced</corr> school keeping<br />
                  under the inspection of the <abbr>Revd</abbr>. <abbr>Mr</abbr>. <persname>Valentine</persname>,<br />
                  a <orgname>Presbyterian</orgname> Minister. He being an <persname>Arian</persname>,<br />
                  tho not of the worst soul, I imbibed some of his<br />
                  principles. I argued with my mother about<br />
                  Predestination, and their great show of religion;<br />
                  and told her, among the rest, that thou who<br />
                  held that doctrine were hypocrites. This made<br />
                  her examine herself, as she told me of on her<br />
                  deathbed, thanking me for it and declaring<br />
                  that she had found my observation true with<br />
                  regard to herself. During her last illness she<br />
                  felt great condemnation, all her sins appea-<br />
                  ring to her view, which made her turn to our<br />
                  Savior and cry out: &quot;Dear Savior, where is<br />
                  thy precious blood, that blood which thou did/
                  
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head>Page 4 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>            
                  shed to cleanse me from my sins?&quot; Scarce<br />
                  had she uttered this ejaculation, when our Sa-<br />
                  vior appeared to the eye of her faith, in his&nbsp;<br />
                  bleeding attitude, which the soldier opened his<br />
                  side with the spear, and she felt as it were<br />
                  his blood trickling upon her heart. Now she<br />
                  was enabled to rejoin in God our Savior. Short<br />
                  ly before her end she said: &quot;Come, Lord Jesus,<br />
                  come quickly,&quot; and then fell asleep in Jesus<br />
                  with a lovely smile upon her countenance.<br />
                  Her happily departure made so deep an impres-<br />
                  sion upon me that I could never forget it,<br />
                  at the same time begetting a strong desire<br />
                  within me, to profess real religion; but to<br />
                  this the vanities of the world proved a great<br />
                  hindrance. Nevertheless, my mind was strong-<br />
                  ly convicted of my folly; one night in par-<br />
                  ticular, which at a dance, I was so terrified,&nbsp;<br />
                  that I was obliged to withdraw, being struck<br />
                  with the reflection, what would become<br />
                  of me, if I should be cut off in that state.<br />
                  Another time I was so alarmed at my situation<br />
                  that I went to the above mentioned minister<br />
                  after midnight and called him up; but he told<br />
                  me that I had nothing to fear, as I had always<br />
                  been a good woman, and that God was merciful<br />
                  and would not mark iniquity so strictly.
                  
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head>Page 5 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  Thus I was rightly served for having applied<br />
                  to him instead of our Savior. I expected he would<br />
                  have put me in the way of doing something<br />
                  whereby to merit heaven; but instead of this,<br />
                  he <corr>addressed&nbsp;</corr>me to put it off by going into cheer-<br />
                  ful company, lest I should grow melancholy.<br />
                  I foolishly took his advice, endeavoring to shake<br />
                  off conviction as much as possible. In this<br />
                  way I proceeded till I was married, and even<br />
                  after that, for a while, followed the fashions of<br />
                  the world. But, my husband, being a religious&nbsp;<br />
                  member of the church of <placename>England</placename>, protested against<br />
                  that mode of living. His Minister being an un-<br />
                  awakened man and performing divine service<br />
                  only in the morning, we went in the afternoon<br />
                  to a <orgname>Baptist</orgname> chapel. Under a sermon in that<br />
                  place on the words: &quot;Almost thou persuadest<br />
                  me to be a <orgname>Christian</orgname>,&quot; we were both so affected<br />
                  that we wept, which the Minister showed, how far<br />
                  a person may go, and yet be only almost a<br />
                  <orgname>christian</orgname>. We continued to hear him till the<br />
                  birth of my first child, when he wanted to per-<br />
                  suade us not to have it baptized, to which my<br />
                  husband would by no means agree. My hus-<br />
                  band read frequently in the New Testament<br />
                  and when he loved the book, used to say : &quot;I
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="6">
               <head>Page 6 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>  
                  thank God for <persname>Paul&#39;s</persname> Epistles; best this of<br />
                  my taste at that to live,&nbsp;for I would rather&nbsp;<br />
                  read of Goliath, Lampoon, Joseph, he&#39;s brethren<br />
                  on of battles; however he continued reading&nbsp;<br />
                  <persname>Paul</persname>&#39;s Epistles, without minding one.<br />
                  My husband being an officer is the&nbsp;exercise<br />
                  his duty was frequently too hard for, so<br />
                  that he was often ailing. In <date>January 1749</date>.<br />
                  he ever taken seriously ill, and sent, that<br />
                  he should like to deposit, adding, thou am<br />
                  happy, who can soon leave the world in<br />
                  peace.&nbsp; I complained that he had lost<br />
                  his regard for me, but he assured me,<br />
                  that his love for me was not decreased;<br />
                  but he saw nothing in this world worth existing<br />
                  to stay in it for. I then asked him,<br />
                  &#39;whether he was first to leave?&#39; He replied,<br />
                  &quot;All my fitness is what Jesus&nbsp;<persname>Christ </persname>did for<br />
                  we on the cross.&quot; This I did not then under-<br />
                  stand. In that state of heart he departed,<br />
                  which was accompanied with such a happy<br />
                  feeling, as filled me with astonishment.<br />
                  His death took place <date>Feb. 22, 1748</date>. In the<br />
                  29th year of his age.<br />
                  After his Departure, their words: &quot;I will be<br />
                  a husband to the widow, and a father to the fa-<br />
                  therly&quot;, were interpreted upon my mind; you&nbsp;<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="7">
               <head>Page 7 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  I was full of disbelief and not say, &quot;Thy<br />
                  will be done.&quot; Then I was left with out&nbsp;house<br />
                  or home, having one child, called&nbsp;<persname>William,</persname> and&nbsp;<br />
                  far advanced in pregnancy with another. I&nbsp;<br />
                  soon set off for my native plan, which was<br />
                  200 miles different, and travelled on foot nine&nbsp;<br />
                  days, in frost and snow. On the arrival at<br />
                  the home of one of my sisters, my husband&#39;s<br />
                  father sent for me and took me into his&nbsp;<br />
                  family.&nbsp; Here I was in about three weeks<br />
                  brought to bed of my son, James, with whom<br />
                  I now live, and who is a member of the brother<br />
                  church and one of their preachers.<br />
                  After the birth of my son, confidently that&nbsp;<br />
                  he had now no father to care for him, it was<br />
                  as tho&#39; our savior stood at my bed side and com-<br />
                  forted me. I laid my hand on the childs&#39;<br />
                  head and devoted him to the Loved and his ser-<br />
                  vice and to the entirety his. This ever accom-<br />
                  panied with the deepest sensation I had ever&nbsp;<br />
                  had of the presence of Jesus, and yet it was<br />
                  as if he said to me, &quot;Thou does not know me<br />
                  yet.&quot; Indeed I did not know him, even by the&nbsp;<br />
                  name of Jesus, but only as the God of Abra-<br />
                  ham, Isaac and Jacob; and when I did a-<br />
                  gain and again, I found no comfort; but
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="8">
               <head>Page 8 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  at last, it was impressed on end to call<br />
                  when&nbsp;Jesus, which I did, saying, &quot;Lend Jesus<br />
                  have mercy upon me!&quot; No sooner had I cal-<br />
                  led upon him by that name, them my condem-<br />
                  nation was all taken away, and I rejoiced<br />
                  wondering at there at the same time, that I had read<br />
                  my Bible so often, and had never called u-<br />
                  pon Jesus before. Now then words came<br />
                  into my mind, &quot;He shall be called Jesus, for<br />
                  he shall save his people from their sins, and<br />
                  I rejoiced in God my Savior.&nbsp; This impression&nbsp;<br />
                  was so deeply fixed in my heart, that when&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />
                  relieving to rest, I always looked to him in<br />
                  spirit on hanging of, on the cross.<br />
                  For sometime after, I had been concerned&nbsp;<br />
                  for my salvation, and now I felt delirious&nbsp;<br />
                  to be connected with a people of God. In<br />
                  this view I went to&nbsp;bear the Methodists, loo-<br />
                  king upon the, as a people of God.&nbsp; I read<br />
                  Mr. Whitfield&#39;s Sermon and saved several<br />
                  of Mr. Wesley&#39;s preachers. I joined the Me-<br />
                  thodists, and with great Zeal frequented their<br />
                  meetings tho I had sometimes to walk<br />
                  four miles in the dark. But by and bye,<br />
                  observing how they differed among themselves<br />
                  about points of doctrine, I left them,<br />
                  thinking they were not a people of God.<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="9">
               <head>Page 9 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  because they were not of one heart and mind.<br />
                  About this time I heard of the Brethren,<br />
                  getting my first impressions of them by&nbsp;<br />
                  means of their hymn book of which I was ve-<br />
                  ry&nbsp;fond, especially of that hymn:&nbsp;<br />
                  &quot;O tell me no more of this world&#39;s veins story;<br />
                  The time for such trifles with me now is o&#39;er.<br />
                  I wished much to know, where to find thou<br />
                  people, who had published their hymns. At<br />
                  lengths I learned that they had a chapel in<br />
                  Dierkenfield, and that they were expected<br />
                  soon to preach at a home in Thackerley, a<br />
                  with different from when I live. I waited<br />
                  with the greatest pleasure and satisfaction&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />
                  and spent the whole day in his company.<br />
                  Indeed I received him in another Apostle<br />
                  Paul.&nbsp; Immediately thought, &quot;this people<br />
                  shall be my people, their God my God, with&nbsp;<br />
                  them. I will live and die and be buried&quot;; and&nbsp;<br />
                  of this resolution I never repented. This<br />
                  was fulfilled what my dear late mother<br />
                  said to me, shortly before her departure<br />
                  for calling me alone to her bedside she said:&nbsp;<br />
                  &quot;I have waited with our savior, and was
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="10">
               <head>Page 10 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  assured that thou shall be his and belong to the<br />
                  people of God, but what people and where and&nbsp;<br />
                  when I cannot tell; but it will not be yet;&nbsp;<br />
                  After this Mr. Valentine, the abovementioned<br />
                  Arian Minister, told me, I had changed for the<br />
                  women by joining the Brother. I sent him the&nbsp;<br />
                  nine discourses on Christ&#39;s Divinity, by Count<br />
                  Zinzendorf; but they did not please him. Soon<br />
                  after he fell sick; I felt great concern for<br />
                  him and went often to&nbsp;converse with him.<br />
                  whenever I mentioned anything&nbsp;about the&nbsp;<br />
                  discourses I sent him, he was out of&nbsp;patience<br />
                  and desired me to visit him no more;&nbsp;neverthe-<br />
                  less, I told him, that I was concerned for him<br />
                  and should call again to see him.&nbsp; However<br />
                  stayed away for sometime, but hearing that<br />
                  he grew very weak, I resolved to visit him a-<br />
                  gain, as I felt very anxious about his happi-<br />
                  ness. Coming to his home I was informed by<br />
                  his daughter, that he endured her to suffer<br />
                  more to come&nbsp;to him, not even his own chil-<br />
                  dren.&nbsp; I therefore sent my&nbsp;love to him, which<br />
                  was ongoing after his health.&nbsp; This being deli-<br />
                  vered, he desired his daughter to send me to him,<br />
                  as he wished to see me.&nbsp; When I came to his<br />
                  bed side, he put out his hands to me, and ap-<br />
                  peared&nbsp;like an affectionate, loving child, and&nbsp;<br />
                  said &quot;We have had many arguments, but&nbsp;<br />
               </p>
            </div>

            <div type="page" n="11">
               <head>Page 11 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  now I know that Jesus Christ is my Savior.&quot;&nbsp;I re-<br />
                  plied. &quot; He is a Savior to them that believe.&quot; To<br />
                  this he replied: &quot;I do believe, and I have no me-<br />
                  rit of my own; but trust alone in my Savi-<br />
                  or&#39;s death and merits. There is something to<br />
                  go through in death, but the prophet beyond it<br />
                  is bright; but I cannot say much, I was very<br />
                  weak. &quot;We then took a tender leave of each other,<br />
                  and soon after he departed in peace.<br />
                  My oldest son, William, died the same year,<br />
                  after a long illness.&nbsp; Shortly before his departure,<br />
                  being very sensible of his approaching dissolution,&nbsp;<br />
                  he called on to his bed, expected his desire to<br />
                  go to Jesus, bade each other farewell, and looked his&nbsp;<br />
                  eyes and fell happily asleep in the Lord, in&nbsp;<br />
                  the 7th year of his age.&nbsp;<br />
                  In 1755 a congregation of the Brother was settled at<br />
                  Dierkenfield, at which solemnity I was profound<br />
                  and my heart was offered like that of Lydia.<br />
                  From that time connection with the church of&nbsp;<br />
                  the Brethren became very weighty&nbsp;to me and has re-<br />
                  mained&nbsp;so ever since,&nbsp;one which account I was<br />
                  the more greived&nbsp;at not being received a mem-<br />
                  ber of them; this&nbsp;favour was, however,<br />
                  granted me the year following.<br />
                  At Thackeray, I opened a little shop for my man<br />
                  and had a good prophet of doing well;<br />
                  but feeling my heart in danger of being drawn&nbsp;<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="12">
               <head>Page 12 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  away by worldly prosperity, and being afraid of<br />
                  losing by any means that happiness, which<br />
                  was then and has been ever since of the last im-<br />
                  portance to me, I gave my shopkeeping in the<br />
                  midst of prosperity, and these words of our savior<br />
                  followed me continually, &quot;What shall it profit<br />
                  a man, tho&#39; he gains the whole world and loves<br />
                  his own soul.&quot; And I think it would because<br />
                  for many, even members of the Brethren church,&nbsp;<br />
                  of this was barely considered. I can say with<br />
                  truth, that from that day to this, our savior,<br />
                  and fellowship with his people have been more<br />
                  important to me than anything else in<br />
                  the world.<br />
                  In August 1756. I moved to Dukenfield, as<br />
                  a member of that congregation. Here I found it very<br />
                  difficult to come through. I had not only to go<br />
                  twenty miles for the work, by which I earned a<br />
                  livelihood, but the necessities of life, parti-<br />
                  cularly bread ran to double the price, they had<br />
                  been sold for a fifth before. Yet I never re-<br />
                  pented of having moved hither, but was con-<br />
                  tent and happy with a small portion of<br />
                  very mean, fare; and my son, who was now<br />
                  nine years old, was the same. Our savior<br />
                  abundantly blessed us internally, and we<br />
                  spent our time, while at work, with singing<br />
                  of Him and his sufferings, being enabled to<br />
                  take our refuge to him in all our circumstances.<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="13">
               <head>Page 13 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  When things were at the worst we would sing:<br />
                  &nbsp; &quot;As small birds are - a hole to cheer<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; In hollow trees for cover,<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp;When whirlwinds blow - when hail and snow<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; O&#39;er man and beast do hover:<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp;So I to then, - Lord Christ, do flee,<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Within thy wounds retired;<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp;When sin and death - did stop my breath,<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Here I again reposed.&quot;<br />
                  This time was indeed a blessed period.<br />
                  In January 1758. I had the favour to par-<br />
                  take of the H.C. for the first time in the<br />
                  Brethren church. I felt so unworthy of it, that<br />
                  I hardly durst venture;<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&quot;Heav&#39;nly joy and holy trembling<br />
                  I felt in me past dissembling.&quot;<br />
                  This divine repast proved a great blessing to me.<br />
                  Hitherto I had been in a certain rapturous<br />
                  way, which in some measure was there more<br />
                  looked for, than a sinners&#39; believing reliance<br />
                  on the all sufficient merit and atonement<br />
                  of Christ. I had made a fine covenant with<br />
                  our savior to be his in all circumstances, both<br />
                  adverse and prosperous, not questioning but I<br />
                  could stand any trial, for I fear, that he had<br />
                  possession of my heart, and I had an assurance<br />
                  that he would safely lead me. Not withstand-
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="14">
               <head>Page 14 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>            
                  ding this I had soon after a severe trial, which<br />
                  was augmented by my want of selfknowledge.<br />
                  Falling sick and feeling myself very poor, and full<br />
                  of unbelief, I began to question the love of our<br />
                  Savior, thinking, if the Lord be with me, why<br />
                  am I thus? Hitherto I had imagined that belie-<br />
                  vers had a fund of support within themselves,<br />
                  so that I thought, it was inconsistent with a&nbsp;<br />
                  child of God to have any doubts and fears. Thus<br />
                  I was so confounded as to be almost driven to<br />
                  despair, and because like a shipwrecked mariner,<br />
                  thrown at once from the pleasing prosperity<br />
                  the promised land upon a desolate rock, where<br />
                  nothing appeared but horror &amp; devastation.<br />
                  The gloom, which had thus overspread me, con-<br />
                  tinued a good while, and tho&#39; I had frequent<br />
                  visits from our Savior, still I could not re-<br />
                  gain my cheerfulness, for I had not yet lear-<br />
                  ned to cleave daily by faith as a needy sinner<br />
                  to Jesus. Indeed this point was not then so<br />
                  well moderated by some of us, as it has been<br />
                  since; After it was expected that a child of God<br />
                  should be cheerful and happy without any in-<br />
                  terruption, and this idea afforded me suffici-<br />
                  ent cause for selfcondemnation. But since<br />
                  then I have learned to know more of the<br />
                  priveledge, enjoyed by a believer, of turning<br />
                  with all his selfishness, to our Savior and finding<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="15">
               <head>Page 15 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  in him a present help in time of need, which<br />
                  is an inexhaustible fund, where we may take<br />
                  grace for grace, and not look for it in any<br />
                  of our own attainments.<br />
                  Some time after I was appointed to begin<br />
                  a school for girls in Dukenfield, which<br />
                  gave me great confidence in our Savior,<br />
                  considering it as an answer to my prayer;<br />
                  for I was at times so full of unbelief, that<br />
                  I thought myself beneath his notice. I opened<br />
                  this school with eleven girls, children of some<br />
                  of the Brethren church, and continued it fifteen<br />
                  years. This was a happy period both for me<br />
                  and the children, several of the latter after-<br />
                  wards became members of the Congregation and<br />
                  likewise some of their parents.<br />
                  At length, not being able to procure a proper<br />
                  place for my school, and having to give up the<br />
                  hours I had hitherto occupied, I was, to my<br />
                  great grief, obliged to drop it. In conse-<br />
                  quence of various disagreeable occurrences,<br />
                  it appeared as if the time for my conti-<br />
                  nuing the school was over.<br />
                  About this time my son, whom from his<br />
                  birth I had entirely devoted to our Savior,<br />
                  moved into the Brethen house in Dukenfield,<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="16">
               <head>Page 16 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p> 
                  in the year 1760, and in 1766. He went to Ful-<br />
                  neck, This last removal went very near me,<br />
                  but I durst not stand in our Savior&#39;s way, be-<br />
                  lieving it would be for the best.<br />
                  Having lodged for sometime with a private<br />
                  family [at some distance] from Dukenfield, who behaved very<br />
                  well to me, I began to grow tired of having<br />
                  so far to go to the meeting. I therefore,<br />
                  sought leave to live in Fulneck, which I<br />
                  obtained. I went thither in 1778, and lodged<br />
                  as a visitor in the widow&#39;s house. Here I had<br />
                  to learn a new business, for the sake of earn-<br />
                  ing a livelihood, which made it heavy<br />
                  to me in the beginning, and I was at times<br />
                  unhappy in my mind. But the chief reason<br />
                  of all my dsitress was, that I did not in every<br />
                  circumstance turn as a poor sinner to our Sav-<br />
                  ior; He, However, at length, enabled me, con-<br />
                  confidently to come to him, as my unchangea-<br />
                  ble friend, who had always approved himself<br />
                  to me as my merciful Believer and Savior.<br />
                  I was much assisted at this time by the<br />
                  advice given me by a certain Brother, who<br />
                  with the tenderness of a father encoura-<br />
                  ged me, assuring me that I would gradu-<br />
                  ally regain my wounded cheerfulness; and<br />
                  this I found verified. But what gave me<br />
                  comfort above all other things, in my greatest
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="17">
               <head>Page 17 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  trials, was the imperfection that my Savior had<br />
                  died for me, and this, I trust will remain so<br />
                  unto the end. I say indeed from my inmost soul:<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &quot;His death and passion ever,<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Till soul and body sever,<br />
                  &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Shall in my heart engrav&#39;d remain.&quot;<br />
                  This has been indelibly impressed upon my<br />
                  mind, ever since he first manifested himself<br />
                  to my soul as my Redeemer.<br />
                  In May 1780. my son recieved a call to begin<br />
                  a school and care for the Brethren Society in<br />
                  Bayldon. In consequence of this he married.<br />
                  My daughter in less growing consumption after<br />
                  her first delivery, moved for her health to her pa-<br />
                  rents in Huddersfield, where she departed this<br />
                  life, and the child soon followed her into eternity.<br />
                  I therefore went to live with my son in Octo-<br />
                  ber 1787. and began a school for girls; and in<br />
                  this situation I have remained till now, when<br />
                  I live in daily expectation to be dismissed<br />
                  from all labour and sorrow, eternally to rest<br />
                  and rejoice in the presence of my God &amp; Savior.<br />
                  &nbsp; In this place a new period in my life com-<br />
                  menced, and I learned to know, more than ever,<br />
                  that I must lean on my Savior, and him only.<br />
                  It was clear to me that I had a call to Bayl-<br />
                  don, and that I was in my proper place when<br />
                  teaching school; our Savior who often visited<br />
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="18">
               <head>Page 18 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  me and blessed my endeavors. I became more<br />
                  stripped of my self righteousness, and learned to&nbsp;<br />
                  rely more fully on the merit and faithfulness<br />
                  of Jesus, in all circumstances for which I&nbsp;<br />
                  can never thank him sufficiently. Neverthe-<br />
                  less I now and then got into a way of self<span style="background-color:null;">wor-</span><br />
                  <span style="background-color:null;">king</span>, which caused me no small anxiety:<br />
                  but my all merciful Savior has helped me<br />
                  and been very gracious to me, amid it all<br />
                  my infirmities of soul and body. I have often<br />
                  been troubled with needless perplexities when&nbsp;<br />
                  reflecting on old age, and how I should get a&nbsp;<br />
                  maintenance in that case; for I was always<br />
                  afraid of being burdensome; which I have never<br />
                  been to anyone, not even when I had two&nbsp;<br />
                  children to support by my own hand-labour.<br />
                  But in this respect also the Lord has been<br />
                  better than my fears and put me to shame,<br />
                  by prospering my endeavors, so that I have<br />
                  more abundance now in my 83rd year, than&nbsp;<br />
                  I have has at any time, since I became&nbsp;<br />
                  a widow, which is 51 years: and I cannot<br />
                  but acknowledge it as a singular favor,<br />
                  that I am able, tho&#39; in much weakness,<br />
                  to teach children as well as ever in any&nbsp;<br />
                  part of my life; so that my old age has<br />
                  been signally favored with respect both&nbsp;<br />
                  to external and internals; for which I&nbsp;
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="19">
               <head>Page 19 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  feel myself excited to the greatest grati-<br />
                  tude to my Savior.<br />
                  The above account of her life she dictated<br />
                  to her Son a short time before her end.<br />
                  She was much beloved and respected by all who<br />
                  knew her both here and at Duckenfield, and<br />
                  had proved a blessing to many. Soon after her&nbsp;<br />
                  arrival at Bayldon, she heard of an old lady,<br />
                  in one of whose tenements we had our former<br />
                  meeting place, one of our Brethren occupy-<br />
                  ing the house; but being unfriendly and pre<br />
                  judiced against us. she gave us warning to&nbsp;<br />
                  quit&nbsp;the premises, which proved the occasions<br />
                  of our building the present small chapel<br />
                  and schoolhouse. Our late sister verified this<br />
                  lady and by means of her conversations gained<br />
                  her entire affection and confidence. The old<br />
                  lady became sensible of her lost condition,&nbsp;<br />
                  sought for grace a the commission of sins<br />
                  thro&#39; the atoning blood of Jesus, which she<br />
                  also found and departed this life in peace.<br />
                  She was greatly interested in the prosperity<br />
                  of the Society at Bayldon, and when her son&nbsp;<br />
                  and the preacher, who occasionally attended<br />
                  there from. Fulneck, where ready to <span style="color:null;">lou</span>&nbsp;con-<br />
                  verge by the small number who came to the&nbsp;
               </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="page" n="20">
               <head>Page 20 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
               </head>
               <p>
                  chapel, and the apparent want of fruit to choir<br />
                  labours, as for some years there had been no in-<br />
                  crease to the Society, but rather a diminution<br />
                  in member, owing to the departure of several<br />
                  of the first member; she animated them to&nbsp;<br />
                  do their part faithfully, saying the Lord would<br />
                  not be wanting on his side, adding: &quot;You will<br />
                  see (better) brighter Days, after I am gone.&quot;*.<br />
                  <lb />
                  *Their expectation was strikingly verified.<br />
                  At the funeral oration, previous to their-<br />
                  terment, which I was favoured to Deliver on<br />
                  May 15. 1799. I had the please to see<br />
                  all the seats in the chapel occupied, tho&#39;<br />
                  it was at the early hour of 7 in the morn-<br />
                  ing, to gain time for conveying her re-<br />
                  mains to Fulneck, where she wished to be<br />
                  interred, and which is at the distance of<br />
                  8 miles. The numerous procession, which&nbsp;<br />
                  followed her by high and low in Bayldon. And<br />
                  when on Lord&#39;s Day, June 9, I again offi-<br />
                  ciated there, and previous to the after-<br />
                  noon sermon, read the above narration<br />
                  of her life, the meeting place was crowded<br />
                  and many stood before the door. From<br />
                  that time the preachings continued&nbsp;<br />
                  to be numerously attended, so that the&nbsp;<br />
                  
                  <div type="page" n="21">
                     <head>Page 21 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        She had for many years been troubled with a&nbsp;<br />
                        violent cough, which sometimes deprived her<br />
                        of natural rest; yet she never murmured,<br />
                        lest her complaint be ever so great; but al-<br />
                        ways prayed for resignation, and relied on<br />
                        Him, who had never forsaken or disappoin-<br />
                        ted her.&nbsp;<br />
                        <lb />
                        Her son saying to her on the Day of her&nbsp;<br />
                        Departure: &quot;My Dear mother, I wish our Sa-<br />
                        vior would raise you up even more;&quot; she<br />
                        replied: &quot;Do not keep me back, let me go<br />
                        freely; it will be best for me now; I want<br />
                        to be gone and to see my Dear Savior.&quot;<br />
                        At noon, her son wishing her to take some<br />
                        <lb />
                        chapel was found too small, and the founda-<br />
                        tion stone for a new one was laid March.28.1806.<br />
                        The Society also increased. A few weeks after&nbsp;<br />
                        her Departure 8 new members were added to&nbsp;<br />
                        the same. At her Death their number was 17.<br />
                        exactly as many as she found in connexi-<br />
                        on with the Brethren, other find coming<br />
                        to Bayldon. And when I left Yorkshire<br />
                        in 1804, their&nbsp; number was between 40&lt;50.<br />
                        and I learn by letters that they continued to<br />
                        increase in number and grace.<br />
                        <br />
                        Copier.&nbsp;<br />
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  
                  <div type="page" n="22">
                     <head>Page 22 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
                     </head>
                     <p> 
                        nourishment, she said:<br />
                        <br />
                        &quot;I&#39;ve no mind for eating or for drinking,<br />
                        Food, which might corrupt again;<br />
                        If God&#39;s bread that&#39;s heavenly I am thinking<br />
                        Jesus&#39; flesh I would obtain,<br />
                        Who was made man of the Lord of David,<br />
                        And his blood is drink, O how I crave it&nbsp;<br />
                        From earth&#39;s life to be set free&nbsp;<br />
                        In loves&#39; immortality.&quot;<br />
                        <lb />
                        She added, &quot;That is what I want.&quot; At 8<br />
                        in the evening she found breathing very diffi-<br />
                        cult. Her son looking at her with earnest con-<br />
                        cern, she turned her eyes to him, as it were, to&nbsp;<br />
                        comfort him and said:<br />
                        <lb />
                        &quot;Tho&#39; waves and storming o&#39;er my head,<br />
                        Tho health a strength a friend, be gone,<br />
                        Shortness of breath preventing her from fini-<br />
                        shing this her favourite verse, she said to hersin, Go on; which he did as follows:<br />
                        <lb />
                        &quot;Tho&#39; joys be withered ill and fled,<br />
                        Tho&#39; every comfort be with withdrawn;<br />
                        Stedfast on this my soul relies,<br />
                        Jesus, thy mercy never dies.&quot;<br />
                        <lb />
                        She joined in the last lines, and then said,&nbsp;<br />
                        that is it. For sometimes after this she&nbsp;<br />
                        continued labouring under great difficulty&nbsp;<br />
                        of breathing, and at length was very desi-<br />
                        rous to have her bed made. Being placed on&nbsp;
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  
                  <div type="page" n="23">
                     <head>Page 23 <seg ana="Repo#_page# from GitHub" />
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        another, she appeared covered with a cold sweat.<br />
                        When put again into her own bed, she prayed<br />
                        intimately: &quot;Dear Savior, come and fetch me<br />
                        thy poor sinner home; come, Dear Savior,<br />
                        and fetch me.&quot; Soon after this her son<br />
                        thought she had been asleep, but her breath<br />
                        grew shorter and shorter. Thus she expired&nbsp;<br />
                        in the most gentle and peaceful in manner<br />
                        and went over to see him, whom here she<br />
                        loved, and whom she also served to the ut-<br />
                        most of her power, with great faithfulness<br />
                        Her pilgrimmage here below lasted 82 years<br />
                        3 months and 3 days.<br />
                        <lb />
                        &quot;She is now with the Son at home;<br />
                        Bow humble expectation<br />
                        Is, that he&#39;ll let us also come,<br />
                        To join that congregation.&quot;<br />
                        <lb />
                        |The Engl. Cong~. Accts of 1799.|
                     </p>
                  </div>
                        
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
