<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Hammond: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Repository Name</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025">Name Date</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-05.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-06.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-07.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-08.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-09.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300025-10.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>William Hammond</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-01">1</head>
               <p> Narrative of the Life of<lb /> Br William Hammond<lb /> written by himself in<lb /> Greek.<lb /> I was born Jan<hi rend="superscript">ry</hi> 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1719 -
                  And from my first infancy felt drawings towards my dearest Saviour in my heart. The occasion to this was, as I remember, a Sermon in which the minister treated largely of the
                  Conversions &amp; Salvation of men, Saying, that those that were born Christian must be saved by their works, but such as were heathen born, by faith alone. O how often have I
                  ardently wished, that I might have been born a heathen, that I thereby might be entitled to that justification, that is procured alone by faith in the most precious blood of my d<hi
                     rend="superscript">r</hi> Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p> When I grew up, and saw that the bible was however esteemed, the word of God, I wondered greatly, that at divine Service in the church the common prayer book was much more made use
                  of &amp; read, than the bible. However some passages of Scripture that I once heard read in the Church of England to which I belonged, made a deep impression upon my mind, and these
                  were the precious pearls, that by the grace of God, I found and reserved in my heart, meditating frequently upon </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-02">2</head>
               <p> At School I was attacked by a violent fit of sickness, being an <sic>inflamatory</sic>
                  <corr>inflammatory</corr> fever, which reduced me so far, that all despaired of my recovery, but God in his great loving kindness &amp; mercy had compassion on me &amp; healed me.
                  However from that time I obtained a weakness in my tongue &amp; a pressure upon my breast, which to this hour renders speaking at times rather difficult to me: This was also a great
                  disappointment to my parents, who had destined me for a preacher of the Gospel, and I myself thought, it would hinder me from [?] such a holy &amp; pious life, as was becoming a
                  Servant of God, rendering me also incapable of doing the duty of this important office, aright.</p>
               <p> In the year 1730, a most tremendous tempest arose, which threatened destruction to our whole neighbourhood. It is known to have laid waste almost the whole south part of England,
                  did great damage at Sea, &amp; also to the houses &amp; barns carrying many of them away, Trees were blown down, &amp; plucked up by the roots; Yea it swept, as it were every thing
                  before it. I slept that night in a lofty garret, heard the rolling of the thunder, the violent rustling of the rain, saw the dreadful flashes of lightning, yea even felt the house
                  tremble in which I was, but God in mercy preserved is from all danger, &amp; his hand covered us. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-03">3</head>
               <p> As I was to leave the school in which I had been hitherto: I <sic>travelled</sic>
                  <corr>traveled</corr> in this year to London I had here serious calls of grace in my heart, to turn from my wicked way, to that Lord, who had bought &amp; saved me. 2. Pet. 2. 1.
                  but, overpowered by the weakness of the flesh, &amp; the depravity &amp; corruption of my heart, I suffered myself to be still tossed to and fro, tho' I was often told in the school,
                  to be obedient to the Voice of the H. Ghost in my heart. However our Lord delivered me out of many dangers I was exposed to, during this period; in the water; among robbers; amongst
                  wicked men, &amp;.c. yea he helped me in all distress. At home and abroad I experienced his powerful protection. Once, being in the country, I fell into a well, and narrowly escaped
                  being drowned; Another time I fell into a large tub in a tanners yard in the city, and was but just saved from sinking entirely. Once a fire breaking out in my house, I with
                  difficulty escaped; another time I was saved from the murdering hands of some robbers on the highway, tho' I lost all my baggage. Besides the violent storm I spoke of above, I was
                  graciously pre= -served in some other terreble terrible tempests in the years 1735, 1763, &amp; 1779.</p>
               <p> Many distresses of soul, and dreadful grievances </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-04">4</head>
               <p> of mind, which affected my life &amp; spirits, have been soothed &amp; alleviated by that only true Physician of Soul and Body, whose love I can never sufficiently reward, tho' I
                  love him ardently. If I had always acted conformable to the dictates of my conscience, I should have been happier than I was, constantly opposing them. O my righteous Lord Jesus
                  Christ! Have mercy upon me, vile Sinner!</p>
               <p> When I went to the University, I awoke. I began to explore the state of Mankind in general, fallen by sin, into misery &amp; unhappiness &amp; in particular my own corrupted heart;
                  and this caused me to seek the face of the Lord in truth: yea in all I did at the University, it became my first, middle &amp; last concern &amp; my chief hearts desire, to find
                  peace and salvation, remission of sins &amp; eternal life in Jesus my Saviour. The load of my Sins lay heavy upon me, and the condemnation I felt in my conscience was so bitter &amp;
                  dreadful to me, that during that whole time, I conversed but little with those around me. The anxiety of my soul was exceeding great, so that I could not find words to express it,
                  nor could I speak of it to any one. The fear of death, external Judgement &amp; hell seized </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-05">5</head>
               <p> and persecuted me for a whole Year together I spent the whole day in fear &amp; trembling, and when I went to bed at night, I shuddered at the thought that I might wake the next
                  morning in Hell, and was destitute of all comfort. -- But the holy Ghost in great mercy trained me up as a child, and gave me hope &amp; resolution, midst all my doubts &amp;
                  unbelief, to press forward to obtain eternal salvation. I followed his gracious leading and at length found, or rather was found by that great Saviour, Jesus Christ, who revealed
                  himself unto me Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1739 as the friend of publicans &amp; Sinners, and justified me, thro' faith in him, and the
                  Atonement by his death, and imparted unto me the kiss of peace, he gave me the assurance of the forgiveness of my Sins.I immediately began to testify to those around me, of the
                  greatness of the depravity of human nature by the disobedience of man, &amp; of the necessity of faith in our crucified Redeemer, by which we obtain forgiveness of sins, and new
                  life. In the following year I left the University, &amp; went back to my native country, where I lived subject unto my parents. I spent my time there in instructing children in
                  different languages. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="6">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-06">6</head>
               <p> After that I spent still 3 years at the University at Cambridge, preaching publicly and in private houses, both in town &amp; country, of the great [?] of the power given unto man,
                  by the service of sin since the fall, and of the only true justification by faith in the [?]; of the necessity of the H. Ghost dwelling within us, and the righteousness grounded upon
                  our [?], &amp; inseparable from the regeneration by the Holy spirit. All this I col= lated and painted in 2 volumes, the first of which was published in London, the other in Bristol.
                  As a minister I was constantly attentive, not to forsake the word of God; and serve [?], but to dedicate all my time to the study of the word &amp; to prayer. Being known by name in
                  the country every where, I now published the following books in the English language: Christian Holiness; Behold the Lamb of God.Only believe, &amp; Christian -- Liberty. All these
                  were published, before I set out for Germany.</p>
               <p> I <sic>travelled</sic>
                  <corr>traveled</corr> from England with a certain german &amp; some English Brn &amp; after a Voyage of 3 days arrived in Holland, where I found more B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi>
                  and <sic>staid</sic>
                  <corr>stayed</corr> with them several days, then going, partly by water &amp; partly by land I arrived in Germany, where I remained several years, being occupied partly by teaching
                  the English language to several young &amp; old people, partly by [?] letters &amp; [?] good old hymns and Verses, &amp; [?] them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="7">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-07">7</head>
               <p> I was then called away suddenly, &amp; set out for my native country. Several B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> accompanied me as far as the next town. I arrived, after a pleasant
                  journey with some German B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> &amp; several of other nations in Holland; went there on board, and after having been 3 days at sea, arrived in Harwich. We
                  proceeded immediately to London, and there I lived in the house of the disciple. During my stay here, I partly assisted in preaching, partly in translating the Cong<hi
                     rend="superscript">n</hi> Accounts; and also took a journey to visit my aged mother &amp; other relations in the country.In the year 1740 two earthquakes happening in London, I
                  was preserved from needless fear &amp; anxiety by the grace of our Lord. --- My future call requiring a change of my situation, I was married in the Year 1750 to the S<hi
                     rend="superscript">le</hi> S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> June Chambers. We then moved together to Northampton, where we staid stayed some years. I preached both in town &amp;
                  Country the gospel, and having collected some of my Sermons, I went to London, and delivered the original of them to the Brethren there. They were afterwards published in the year
                  1770. Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1752 my wife was happily delivered of a daughter, which rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> the name of Mary in
                  holy baptism, but was taken home by the Lord some hours after her birth. In my distress I said to my d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thou hast given
                  her &amp; thou hast taken her hence, blessed be thy name. Thy will be done. and thus resigned to his will I felt comforted &amp; happy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="8">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-08">8</head>
               <p> 1753 I left Northampton and moved to Chelsea, where I laid the orginal of my Collection of Hymns &amp; Psalms, <sic>wrote</sic>
                  <corr>written</corr> by me in Latin &amp; English before the B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> for their perusal. This &amp; the second volume of them, containing psalms &amp; hymns
                  containing the Saviour of the World, the holy Trinity &amp;c. &amp;c. written some in Latin, Greek, Hebrew &amp; English, begun in the year 1754 &amp; continued to 1756, I brought
                  into more order at Chelsea where I <sic>staid</sic>
                  <corr>stayed</corr> some time. I also translated some German discourses into English &amp; added a preface to them. I continued to preach both here &amp; in the country, and visited
                  likewise my native place, where I saw my mother &amp; other relations. 1757 we left Chelsea &amp; London and went to Bristol &amp; Wales. I preached in many places; some of my
                  Sermons I collected and they were printed in London in 1761. Having <sic>staid</sic>
                  <corr>stayed</corr> some time in Wales, I <sic>travelled</sic>
                  <corr>traveled</corr> to Yorkshire. Here I had a fit of illness owing to the fatigue of travelling traveling, from which I did not recover in less than 6 months. About this time I
                  likewise published several books, consisting of hymns &amp;c. After time we travelled traveled again to London where we arrived Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 22<hi
                     rend="superscript">d</hi>. 1760, The year following I paid again a visit to my old mother in my native country. I preached here &amp; my sermon was then printed in London in the
                  year 1763. Upon my return to London, I was one day bathing </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="9">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-09">9</head>
               <p> in the Thames, when Suddenly the current overpowered me, and loosing ground I was carried away for some time by the water. However the Lord graciously preserved me, so that I
                  escaped from being drowned. Thus also when a child I once fell headlong into a deep pond, but was miraculously saved. At Sea I was sometimes in danger of shipwreck but in this &amp;
                  all other cases, my gracious Lord has delivered &amp; preserved me.</p>
               <p> 1763 I made a journey with my wife into the country, to visit my eldest Sister at her earnest request. I also saw my other relations, &amp; spoke with them of their eternal
                  salvation. In all their houses I delivered freely a testimony of the Kingdom of God, and of the conversion of poor undone Sinners to God, of the atonement made by our Lord Jesus
                  Christ, &amp; of his precious wounds Sufferings and death. After having spent 12 days with my Sister we returned to London. I spent my time in <sic>connexion</sic>
                  <corr>connection</corr> and intercourse with our Sav<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> yea my very dreams were often blessed to me. Especially I remember one, in which I thought I found
                  myself amongst my B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> with the whole d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cong<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> standing around the throne of the Lamb, crying,
                  Praise and adoration be unto thee, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="10">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300025-10">10</head>
               <p> for thou hast redeemed us by thy blood. I had then a heavenly feeling of happiness; which accompanied me the following day, which I spent in sweet &amp; silent contemplation.</p>
               <p> My comfort now is that I shall soon go to see him on whom I have believed, and depart to enjoy that eternal happiness procured by him for all believers. Amen. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
