<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/moravianlives/master/TEI_Memoirs/out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peter Jacob Planta: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator
                  <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018
                  <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer, 2016-Present</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-Present</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder, 2018-2019</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Jess Hom</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University, 2018-Present</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marita Gruner</persName>
               <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sarah Kannemann</persName>
               <orgName>University of Mainz</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Justin Schaumberger</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant, encoder, ontologist, 2019-Present</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0
                  International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Repository Name</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="#">Name</msName>
                  <!-- <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/##-03.jpg" />-->
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>name</head>
            <p>I was born at <placeName ref="#mlpla000085">Jonköping or town in Sweden</placeName>,
                  <date when-iso="1721-12-5" calendar="Julian">Dec. the 5th, old style in the year
                  1721</date>. My Father's name was <persName>Jacob Planta</persName> &amp; my
               Mother's maiden name <persName>Martha Ruda</persName>. They were both of the
                  <orgName>Lutheran Religion</orgName> I had two sisters, the [one] was born during
               my <persName ana="Martha Ruda">Mother</persName>'s marriage to her first husband,
               whose name was <persName>Peter Shilling</persName>. Our <persName
                  ana="Martha Ruda Jacob Planta">Parents</persName> spared no pains in giving us a
               religious &amp; genteel education; we had morning &amp; evening <name type="event"
                  >prayers</name> in the family, to which the <roleName>servants</roleName> were
               also admitted. </p>
            <p>My dear <persName ana="Martha Ruda">Mother</persName> would often read in the <name
                  type="religion">bible</name>, &amp; after prayers, read to me - take [] to us
               pleasing scritoral his- tories, especially such as had a reference to the life,
               suffering &amp; death of our dear <persName>Lord</persName> &amp; <persName
                  type="diety">Saviour</persName>, &amp; also his [connection] <note
                  type="catchword">with</note>
            </p>
         </div>

         <div type="page" n="2">
            <head type="page">2</head>
            <pb n="2" facs="url"/>
            <p>with his <roleName>disciples</roleName> &amp; some of the [] time which the latter
               had to endure for his sake. On such occasions I used to sit on <persName
                  ana="Martha Ruda">her</persName> lap, &amp; sometimes asked what reward the
                  <roleName>disciples</roleName> had for this faithful-ness to our
                  <persName>Saviour</persName>, to which <persName ana="Martha Ruda">she</persName>
               replied: "They are richly rewarded for they are now exceeding happy with <persName
                  type="diety">Him</persName> in his <placeName type="biblical">heavenly
                  kingdom</placeName>, singing his praises, &amp; <name type="emotion">adoring</name> him for ever." I said with
                  <name type="emotion">tear</name>, O my dear <persName ana="Martha Ruda"
                     >Mamma</persName>, I wish that I had lived at the time our <persName
                     type="diety">Saviour</persName> was upon <placeName>earth</placeName>, I also would have served him
                  &amp; suffered for his sake. My <persName ana="Martha Ruda"
                  >Mother</persName> replied <name type="emotion">weeping</name>, "my dear <persName ana="Peter Planta">child</persName>, if you had lived at that time
               you might perhaps have been of the number of those who cried out, crucify hiim!
               crucify him! " I said, O no, I never would, but I should have <name type="emotion"
                  >loved</name> him dearly. She then <name type="emotion">blessed</name> me, &amp; prayed the <persName
                  type="diety">Lord</persName> to keep me as his property, &amp; to preserve me
               throughout my future life from sin, &amp; the seductions of this evil world, until I
               should be with him in his <placeName type="biblical">heavenly kingdom</placeName>,
               &amp; then added that all those who <name type="emotion">loved</name> &amp; served
               him here, would share in the same blessings which his <roleName>disciples</roleName> did. This made a deep
               impression on my mind, &amp; was the first time when I [] <note type="catchword"
                  >but</note>
            </p>
         </div>

         <div type="page" n="3">
            <head type="page">3</head>
            <pb n="3" facs="url"/>
            <p>but to have felt a real &amp; <name type="emotion">tender love</name> &amp; <name
                  type="emotion">attachment</name> in my heart to our dear
                  <persName>Saviour</persName> &amp; in the sequel I always wished &amp; <name
                  type="empotion">prayed</name> that I might become &amp; remain a true child of
                  <persName>God</persName>. <date when-iso="1725">When I was about 4 years of
                  age</date>, I experienced a remarkable preservation of my life. Having run out of
               the house [], with a spoon in my hand, I came to <placeName>Lake Witter</placeName>,
               which was not far distant from our house, &amp; there being a broad plank laid over
               the water I got to the end of it, &amp; was sitting on it playing with the spoon,
               admiring the drops which appeared to me like pearls. </p>
            <p>A woman who came to fetch water, called out to me to take care that I did not fall
               into the water, to whom I replied: I will not fall in, but she had scarcely returned
               to the house before she thought that she heard a plunge in the water, upon which she
               set down her pail, &amp; ran towards the lake. Perceiving me in the water, she
               ventured in, &amp; with difficulty caught hold of me by the hair of my head, &amp;
               drawing me out, she laid me across the plank, believing me to be dead. She then
               carried me home to my <persName ana="Martha Ruda Jacob Planta">Parents</persName>,
               who, with the whole family were <note type="catchword">greatly</note></p>
         </div>

         <div type="page" n="4">
            <head type="page">4</head>
            <pb n="4" facs="url"/>
            <p><name type="emotion">greatly alarmed</name>, &amp; exceedingly <name type="emotion"
                  >distressed</name>, as they could perceive no signs of life in me. I was however
               put into a warm bed, &amp; after some time, while they were <name type="emotion"
                  >lamenting</name> over me, I came to myself &amp; said dear <persName
                  ana="Martha Ruda">Mamma</persName> don't cry for me. I am here, &amp; to the great
                  <name type="emotion">joy</name> of the whole family, I recovered. As I increased
               in years, I experienced several preservations of my life, having been in danger of
               losing it, both by fire &amp; water, &amp; once escaped being murdered. My <persName
                  ana="Martha Ruda Jacob Planta">Parents</persName> being desirous to give me a good
               education, procured a private Tutor in the house, until I went to a large school, in
               which I continued till my <persName ana="Jacob Planta">Father</persName>'s happyp
               depar-ture, which took place in my 10th year.</p>
            <p>My <persName ana="Martha Ruda">Mother</persName>'s intention was that I should
               continue my studies, wishing me to be a <roleName>Minister of the Gospel</roleName>,
               which also accord-ed with my inclination. However a Relation persuaded my <persName
                  ana="Martha Ruda">Mother</persName> to put me apprentice to an eminent
                  <roleName>Surgeon</roleName> &amp; <roleName>Apothecary</roleName> in <placeName
                  ref="#mlpla000086">Gothenburg</placeName>. Here I had a favourable opportunity to
               learn Pharmacy &amp; chemistry, &amp; as my master had very extensive practice, &amp;
               employed me to visit his patients, I gradually began to practice myself, &amp; gave
               considerable <name type="emotion">satisfaction</name> to my employer. Having been
               awakened to a sense of <note type="catchword">my</note>
            </p>
         </div>

         <div type="page" n="5">
            <head type="page">5</head>
            <pb n="5" facs="url"/>
            <p>my lost condition, I was for several years much concerned for my salvation, yea I may
               say ever since I was a child, the <persName type="diety">Holy Ghost</persName>
               carried on his work in my heart, by which I was presented from many sinful things. I
               did frequently fall into sin, repenting &amp; sinning alternately, so that when I
               would do good, ever was present with me. I felt frequently a great desire to separate
               myself from the world, &amp; used to walk in the fields, where I could be alone,
               praying to our dear <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName> in which I took great
               delight. At such times I felt much pleasure in singing praises &amp;
                  thank<del>sgive</del>ing <persName type="diety">God</persName>; &amp; nothing
               afforded me greater <name type="emotion">joy</name>, than to thank our <persName
                  type="diety">Saviour</persName> for the many preservations I had experienced from
               him, when in danger of my life. However I also, alas! often forgot myself, &amp; gave
               way to levity when playing with my companions. But the good spirit of <persName
                  type="diety">God</persName> frequently reminded me to seek the <hi
                  rend="underscore">One thing needful</hi>. I felt strong desire to be a child of
                  <persName>God</persName>, &amp; when I was invited with my <persName
                  ana="Martha Rud and">Parents</persName> to entertainments, at which was music
               &amp; dancing, I felt afterwards, great uneasiness, &amp; like one who is sick, not
               understanding properly the accusations of my conscience. <date when-iso="1734">When I
                  was about 13 years of age</date> I ahd a great desire to enjoy the Holy Com<add
                  place="above">n</add>, for which preparing </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="6">
            <head type="page">6</head>
            <pb n="6" facs="url"/>
            <p>I underwent an examination &amp; was encouraged to partake. The first time I had the
               favor to approach the table of the <persName type="diety">Lord</persName>, it was
               with <name type="emotion">fear</name> &amp; trembling, lest I should receive it
               unworthily, but at the enjoyment of this divine repast, I felt exceedingly <name
                  type="emotion">happy</name>, yea more so than I can express. In the sequel, whilst
                  the<persName type="diety"> Holy Ghost</persName> was operating upon my heart, I
               frequently examined myself, <name type="emotion">fearing</name> I was not yet a child
               of <persName type="diety">God</persName>, &amp; yet earnestly desiring to be one.
               Such was the state of my mind when I came to <placeName ref="#mlpla000086"
                  >Gothenburg</placeName>. I experienced, at first much attention from the family in
               which I resided as an <roleName>Apprentice</roleName>, so long as I conformed to ever
               thing in it. How-ever the great concern I had for my salvation &amp; the thought of
               not being a child of <persName type="diety">God</persName>, gave me much <name
                  type="emotion">uneasiness</name>. I was always glad whenever I could be alone,
               &amp; pour out the desire of my heart before <persName>God</persName>, &amp;
               frequently prayed in stillness to him. I also resolved to withdraw from all worldly
               amusements &amp; to spend the little time I had to myself, in spiritual exercises,
               longing to be assured that I was a child of <persName type="diety">God</persName>.
               Sometimes I arose in cold frosty nights, frustrating myself before <persName
                  type="diety">God</persName>, &amp; praying most fer-vently unto him, but it
               afforded me no relief. I thought then that my <name type="emotion">sorrow</name> for
               my sins was not yet great <note type="catchword">enough</note></p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="7">
            <head type="page">7</head>
            <pb n="7" facs="url"/>
            <p>enough. I often repeated the <name type="biblical">10 Command-ments</name>, in order
               to see &amp; feel my deviations &amp; sins, but as I could not cry &amp; weep like
                  <persName type="biblical">David</persName>, who all the night made his bed to
               swim, &amp; watered his couch with his tears, I thought my <name type="emotion"
                  >grief</name> was not intense enough. But all my endeavours were in vain, because
               I [], in supposing that if I could but weep much over my sins &amp; repent of them,
               then the <persName type="diety">Lord</persName> would receive me as his child, &amp;
               com-fort me. I was convinced of the all sufficing of our <persName type="diety"
                  >Lord</persName> &amp; <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName>'s sufferings for
               sinners, but thought I must be their qualified before I could receive this blessing.
               I became now very zealous, frequently reproving others for sin, &amp; my singular
               conduct brought on me much persecution &amp; hatred, which however I gladly suffered,
               bearing all with patience &amp; never resenting any ill treatment, but on the
               contrary did such persons all the service I could, &amp; whenever opportunities
               offered, spoke to them concerning our <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName>. Two
               persons in the family where I lodged being awakened to a sense of their lost
               condition, one of them caused me much trouble &amp; <name type="religion"
                  >uneasiness</name>, on account of his fears &amp; unbelief, thinnking he could be
               not forgiven. He fell at last into a melancholy, frequently hiding himself, <note
                  type="catchword">and</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="8">
            <head type="page">8</head>
            <pb n="8" facs="url"/>
            <p>&amp; even attempted to take away his life so that he appeared in a state of mental
               derangement.</p>
            <p>I used my utmost endeavours to nurture him, <name type="emotion">fearing</name> that
               in case he should commit suicide a great dishonor would be brought on the <name
                  type="religion">gospel</name>.</p>
            <p>One time he sent me a message with <del>of</del> his last fare-well, having locked
               himself up with a view to self-destruction. This caused me unspeaka-ble <name
                  type="emotion">distress</name>, &amp; tho' I was at that time en-ggaged in very
               urgent business &amp; in company with several persons, yet I took the key of the
               cellar, ran down &amp; locked the door, &amp; knelling down by a hogshead of
               turpentine I <name type="emotion">wept</name> &amp; prayed most fervently to our
                  <persName type="diety">Saviour</persName>, (with great confidence), that he would
               preserve the poor man's life, &amp; it seemed to me as if I heard a voice saying - Be
               comforted, no evil shall hurt him. This I believed, &amp; arose, giving thanks to
                  <persName type="diety">God my Saviour</persName>, &amp; returned cheerful-ly to my
               business, till about 12 o'clock at night, being [] in my mind, I [] some boards &amp;
               other things, when I found him alive &amp; feeling <name type="emotion"
                  >thankful</name> to <persName type="diety">God</persName> for his preservation, I
               asked him why he had not performed <add>executed</add> his intention, to which he
               replied, that when he was about to attempt it, he fell &amp; all his strength was
               taken from him, so that he could neither move a limb, nor speak a word, till I came.
               I spoke comfortably to him, encouraging him to take his refuge to our <persName
                  type="diety">Saviour</persName>, &amp; conducting him to his room, I prayed with
               him, &amp; in the sequel he grew better. The other person <note type="catchword"
                  >who</note></p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="9">
            <head type="page">9</head>
            <pb n="9" facs="url"/>
            <p> who was awakened was the <roleName>Cook</roleName>, who died suddenly, but very
                  happ<del>y</del>ily. She had been much beloved by her Mistress' Mother, &amp; her
               sudden death caused the old Lady to swoon away. I was then, (altho I had been much
                  <name type="emotion">despised</name> &amp; derided on account of religion) called
               upon to speak comfort to the old lady, &amp; as soon as she recovered, she took me by
               the hand &amp; begged my pardon, adding: "I have been the cause of the persecution
               you have suffered." I replied, "I have no occasion to forgive you, for you have done
               me more good than harm, since it has caused me to [] [] my <persName type="diety"
                  >Saviour</persName>, who will hear the prayers of all repent-ing sinners. Thus her
               hatred &amp; persecution were turned into great <name type="emotion">love</name>
               &amp; <name type="emotion">kindness</name>. About this time I attended the preaching
               of the <persName>Revd Mr Lindberg</persName> in <placeName ref="#mlpla000086"
                  >Gothenburg</placeName>. He observed in his <name type="event">sermon</name>, that
               there were several kinds of people, who were hindered from enjoying the <name
                  type="emotion">happiness</name> which the <persName type="diety">Lord</persName>
               would willingly bestow upon them, if they would but come in the way &amp; order of hi
               appointment. Among one of those sorts of well meaning souls, I found myself so
               completely described as if I had opened my whole mind to him. He remarked that some
               people thought that if they could arrive at a certain degree of ex-cessive <name
                  type="emotion">grief</name> &amp; <name type="emotion">anguish</name>, &amp; could
               shed repenting tears night &amp; day, that then the <persName type="diety"
                  >Lord</persName>
               <note type="catchword">would</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
