<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christiane Eleonora Seidel: Memoir
            </title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, PA USA</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives, Bethlehem</repository>
                  <idno />
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MAB/MemBeth_0138">Christiane E. Seidel</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-05.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-06.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0138-07.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <head>Christiane Seidel memoir</head>
         <div type="page" n="1">
            <head>Page 1 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-01" />
            </head>
            <p> 2. The Widow <persName>Christine Eleonore Seidel</persName>. (her Maiden Name was Peistel) She <sic>wrot</sic>
               <corr>wrote</corr> of herself: I am born the <date>28</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of May 1707</date> at <placeName>Litowiz</placeName> in
                  <placeName>Misonie</placeName>. Myn Vater has been <persName>Carl Fridric Peistel</persName> and my Mother <persName>Eleonore</persName> born of <placeName>Bradenstein</placeName>,
               of the generation Zoeshen by Merseburg. We have been 5 <del rend="strikethrough">Brethren &amp; Sisters</del>Children, two of them are gone home in their tender Ages, and we three have
               been brought up at home, and <add>we</add> came according to our Pradestination to the Congregation. We had a Lovefull but a serious Mother, who had our true best at Heart, She was a
               Lover of the Cross of Christ &amp; <sic>aknowlegd</sic>
               <corr>acknowledged</corr> Christ crucified for her only <sic>Happeness</sic>
               <corr>Happiness</corr> in time &amp; Eternity for every Body. She had a <sic>Conexion</sic>
               <corr>Connection</corr> w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> our Saviour &amp; did not Love the World, &amp; This has been the Subsect of <add>her</add> discoursing w.<hi rend="superscript"
                  >th</hi> us, in a very evangelical Manner &amp; this effected towards our Mother by us <name type="emotion">a great Love</name> &amp; respect. By <sic>occassion</sic>
               <corr>occasion</corr> She very often declard to us: that our Saviour certified her Heart, that not one of her Children should be lost, but all should become his Property &amp; live for
               him in this World. This made some times a deep Impression on our Hearts, I for my Part was not without Feeling, nevertheless I did not know my Redeemer. In the Time following the Lust
               to the World begun to stir &amp; I <sic>begun</sic>
               <corr>began</corr> to like the World &amp; the World liked me &amp; seekd for me. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="2">
            <head>Page 2 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-02" />
            </head>
            <p> Alone my true Saviour did't leave me Rest in Pleasure whatsoever but transformed all wordly <sic>Plesures</sic>
               <corr>Pleasures</corr> into Bitterness, Grief &amp; Mourning. I knew very well I was not converted &amp; therefore <sic>toock</sic>
               <corr>took</corr> one Resolution after the other, but without Effect; then I <sic>allways</sic>
               <corr>always</corr> begun driven by the Restlessness of my Heart w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> my own Power, therefore I never found rest or get into a true <sic>Conexion</sic>
               <corr>Connection</corr> w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> our Saviour. By the <unclear>infattigable</unclear>
               <sic>Disire</sic>
               <corr>Desire</corr> of our dear Mother our Saviour provideth for us, and we got a Proceptor from <persName>D</persName><hi rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>
                  Buddei</persName>, Named <persName>Hofman</persName> (a intimate Friend to our blessed <persName>B.</persName><hi rend="superscript"><persName>r</persName></hi><persName>
                  Vierroth</persName>) who <sic>recommented</sic>
               <corr>recommended</corr> contualy <sic>continualy</sic>
               <corr>continually</corr> the Love of our crucified Saviour w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> a burning Heart to us; and was of one <sic>Opinon</sic>
               <corr>Opinion</corr> w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> our Dear Mammy. </p>
            <p> A.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>
               <date>1735</date> our dear Saviour took our dear Mother on a sudden but very happy home to himself. We, her three Children where present, because our Brother to the same time a Prussian
                  <sic>Officir</sic>
               <corr>Officer</corr> came home by a instinct unknown for what, he found her still well, but had not long to wait to see her <sic>clossing</sic>
               <corr>closing</corr> her Eyes happy &amp; in Peace. Her so happy &amp; <sic>Joyfull</sic>
               <corr>Joyful</corr>
               <sic>Far well</sic>
               <corr>Farewell</corr>, had such a Effect on our Hearts that we three together <sic>tock</sic>
               <corr>took</corr> the resolution at once, to have no part w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the World, but to give our whole Hearts to our Saviour Jesus Christ. But I for my part did't
               know this true Friend of <sic>Siners</sic>
               <corr>Sinners</corr>. I tried all the means I could, I read very often the History of the Suffering &amp; Death of our Saviour not without Effect upon my Heart; but I <sic>allways</sic>
               <corr>always</corr>
               <sic>begun</sic>
               <corr>began</corr> by becoming Pious &amp; to Show my Duty to God, and so I came by all my restlessness not farther. Then I became <sic>aquainted</sic>
               <corr>acquainted</corr> with Separatists, &amp; would undoubtedly have fallen deeper &amp; deeper in my own Working; had not our Saviour directed, that <persName>Magister Seidel
                  </persName><add>was calld</add> as Deacon to <unclear><placeName>Mutschen</placeName></unclear><placeName /> as the Place of our Residence. He begun to preach our Saviour w.<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> Power &amp; Grace &amp; our Sav.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> regulated it so that I became his Wife, <sic>noth_ withsanding</sic>
               <corr>notwithstanding</corr> all the <sic>Dificultys</sic>
               <corr>Difficulties</corr> which would arise in this respect. This Marriage was a great Blessing to my Heart. My Husbands' tender Conversation w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> our
               Saviour moved my Heart anew, that as he ask'd me in the first Days of our Marriage: how it would be with me? if <sic>Poeple</sic>
               <corr>People</corr> would drive him <add>out</add> for the <sic>Sacke</sic>
               <corr>Sake</corr> of our dear Saviour out of the Town &amp; Country? I made a Covenant w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> him, to follow him willingly [.] and partake w.<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> him for our Saviours Sake what would follow. A. <date>1740</date>. He went to see the Congregation in <placeName>Hhuth</placeName>. This Visit brought a
               great Blessing about his Heart and I got my Share by that dreams to. From this Time quite a new a happy Period begun w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> us. A.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>
               <date>1741</date>. The <date>22</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>d</date></hi><date> of March</date> as he was Preaches to the Garrison at the
                  <sic><placeName>Castel</placeName></sic><placeName> of Königs Stone</placeName> our dear Saviour took him home in his eternal <unclear>favoty</unclear>. He Witnesseth still on his
               Sick Bed towards all </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="3">
            <head>Page 3 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-03" />
            </head>
            <p> who came to see him, from the Power of the Blood of Christ with a becoming Tenderness. His happy &amp; <sic>Joyfull</sic>
               <corr>Joyful</corr> Departure to our Saviour renewd &amp; fastened the Impression, I had, of the blessed Con_ versation w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> him. </p>
            <p> Now my former Inclination to the had fixd <add>in me</add> such a Fear of myself, that I no where trusted to live, &amp; imagined Danger every where; but the Friend of my Soul soon
               recollected to me, that I lookd more on my blessed Husband as on the <sic>Conexion</sic>
               <corr>Connection</corr> w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> him. This made me prostrate myself before &amp; I begged w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1000 Fears forgiveness over all what
               passed. He Mercy took me as I was, &amp; I had from thence a more happy Period. By all that, I could not get rid of my Scrupulosity by the feelings of my Misery &amp; like a Child draw
               near to him according to my Wish, <sic>therfore</sic>
               <corr>therefore</corr> the Fear of myself darkneth my happy Hours very often. In this very Year, I &amp; my Sister went to see the Con_ gregation at <placeName>Hhuth</placeName>, there
               I <sic>feeld</sic>
               <corr>felt</corr> the very Peace of God, and the Brethren &amp; Sisters I <sic>loockd</sic>
               <corr>looked</corr> on as Children of God and had a great respect towards them &amp; I wishd incognito to live in this Place. <date>1742</date>. We came to see
                  <placeName>Hhuth</placeName> a second time &amp; there we <sic>detemind</sic>
               <corr>determined</corr> to remove thither. But by setting out for <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> some Accident happened &amp; we <sic>possponed</sic>
               <corr>postponed</corr> our Journey. Hereby a dangerous Period for my poor Heart begun, a false <unclear>Poeple</unclear> filled our Minds with so much dangerous Expectations and Things
               against the Congregation, that our Journey was quite <sic>dropt</sic>
               <corr>dropped</corr>. By all that our Saviour was so <sic>gratious</sic>
               <corr>gracious</corr> to beware that I did't sin against his Church, &amp; my <sic>Disire</sic>
               <corr>Desire</corr> still remaining to <sic>spent</sic>
               <corr>spend</corr> my Days under this <unclear>Poeple</unclear>. I was busy in reading the <sic>Deciples</sic>
               <corr>Disciples</corr>
               <sic>Semons</sic>
               <corr>Sermons</corr> deliverd at <placeName>Berlin</placeName> &amp; begged our Saviour very often that if I belonged to this Folks, he would himself find means to bring me
                  <sic>thiter</sic>
               <corr>thither</corr>. As my Brother moved from <placeName>Wetteravia</placeName> to <placeName>Bertholsdorf</placeName>, I &amp; my Sister paid him a Visit there for some Weeks, by that
               we saw what false Opinions had for foundation. But for all that I <sic>knowd</sic>
               <corr>knew</corr> very well that some <sic>Poeple</sic>
               <corr>People</corr> who came to the Con_ gregation have been sent by &amp; by back again, this made me terribly afraid to venture asking Leave nevertheless I <sic>feeled</sic>
               <corr>felt</corr> a Instinct in my Heart that I belonged to this People. At last I &amp; my Sister desireth Leave to stay in <placeName>Bertholsdorf</placeName> (only to be near
                  <placeName>Hhuth</placeName> &amp; to try if we belong to the Congregation or not) We got Leave &amp; then the <date>9</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of Jan.
                  1747</date>. we arrived in <placeName>Bertholsdorf</placeName> to stay there. </p>
            <p> Exact a Month <sic>past</sic>
               <corr>passed</corr> as the <date>9</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of Febr</date>. in a <note type="catchword">Meeting</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="4">
            <head>Page 4 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-04" />
            </head>
            <p> Meeting at the Hall in <placeName>Hhuth</placeName> as they sung this <sic>vers</sic>
               <corr>verse</corr>: Wie bin ich doch so herzlich froh. My bloody Redeemer on a sudden appeard before me, &amp; my poor Heart melted away by feeling his blessed Nearness for Shame about
               my deep Misery &amp; Sinful Condition. I never can forget this blessed Moment &amp; I shall remember it &amp; adore my Saviour therefore in Eternity. </p>
            <p> From this Time the Sisters took more particular Care upon me, &amp; for all I liveth in <placeName>Berthols_ dorf</placeName> I got <sic>Lieve</sic>
               <corr>Leave</corr> to partake on the Communion_ Meetings in <placeName>Hhuth</placeName>. </p>
            <p>
               <date>1747 the 22</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>d</date></hi><date> of Octob.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></date> to the greatest Joy &amp; Shame of my poor Heart, I was received
               in the Congregation in <placeName>Hhuth</placeName>, this gave one a new Spirit to lay down my whole Heart before my Redeemer as a poor Reward for his Trouble; and still I remember by
               every Reception, the Grace beflowed upon my <add>Soul</add> by this Opportunity. A.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>
               <date>1748 March 20</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi> I removed from Hh <placeName>Bertholsdorf</placeName> to <placeName>Hhuth</placeName>
            </p>
            <p>
               <date>March 25</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi> our Saviour <add>beflowed</add> the great Mercy on me to partake w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the Congregation the
               holy Sacrament of his inestimable Flesh &amp; Blood. Here all Words fall to short to express what my <note type="catchword">poor</note> poor Heart felt thereby. </p>
            <p> From that Time I passd my Time as well in the Congregation as my dear Choir <sic>chearfull</sic>
               <corr>cheerful</corr> and happy and my Heart was <sic>realy</sic>
               <corr>really</corr> attached to our dear Saviour. If some times a cloudy Hour came upon me, as whereto my poor Temper much inclined, it was soon dispersed as soon as my Heart
                  <sic>weept</sic>
               <corr>wept</corr> for our dear Saviours feet. </p>
            <p> A.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>
               <date>1756 the 14</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of March</date> I was taken among the hourly Intercessors, by this special Conversation w.<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> our dear Saviour, I had many Blessings &amp; for fo my own part many <add>delightful</add> Insights into the <unclear>Siner_ loving</unclear> Heart of our
               Redeemer. </p>
            <p> The <date>3</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of Febr</date>. a.c. I was <add>received</add> amongst the Acoluths. received. the <date>8 of July</date> as the new
               Classes who were errected I became a Help Mate in one of them. The <date>3</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of Febr</date>. I became the first time Choir Disciple
               which was a Opportunity to keep <sic>closse</sic>
               <corr>close</corr> to the Heart of my dearest Redeemer &amp; a true blessing for my poor Soul (after that this Grace happened oftener to her, and She was the last Choir Disciple.) In
               the Beginning of the <date>Year 61</date>. Our dear Saviour was very <sic>gratious</sic>
               <corr>gracious</corr> to me &amp; <sic>blest</sic>
               <corr>blessed</corr> me w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> his Nearness &amp; my constant Prayer was only: Dear Saviour remain so with me, till I see thy face to Face. <note
                  type="catchword"><date>18</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> Febr.</date></note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="page" n="5">
            <head>Page 5 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-05" />
            </head>
            <p> The <date>16</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of Febr</date>. a.c. I had the Pleasure to move in our new Choir-House. I desireth by that means by our Saviour as
               a Present a quite happy Choir Heart. (Since that I had lived in the House of my Brother.) He alone knoweth the Fears of my Heart, and I know he'll transfer me by his Mercy to his own
               &amp; holy Pleasure. </p>
            <p> So far her own Words. That our Saviour was near to our blessed Sister in her Choir-House &amp; heard her <sic>Disires</sic>
               <corr>Desires</corr> may <sic>easely</sic>
               <corr>easily</corr> be seen by the following verses, which she made on her last Birth Day the <date>28</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of May</date>: Wie dank
               ich dir mein ewger Mann for das, was du dis Jahr gethan an deinem armen sundgen Kind das nichts als Mängel an sich findt. </p>
            <figure>
               <ab>X X</ab>
            </figure>
            <div type="verse">
               <lg>
                  <l>Ich gebe deinen blutgen Fuss</l>
                  <l>den sünderhafsten Gruss und Kuss</l>
                  <l>for alle Gnade und Geduld</l>
                  <l>und fors vergeben meiner Schuld.</l>
               </lg>
               <figure>
                  <ab> X X</ab>
               </figure>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ach wie beshämt es mich so sehr</l>
                  <l>Dass ich dir noch nicht mehr zur Ehr</l>
                  <l>Schenk mir ein ganz zersehmolzen Herz</l>
                  <l>verliebt in deinen Todt und Schmerz</l>
               </lg>
               <figure>
                  <ab>X X</ab>
               </figure>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gott heilger Geist du Mutter mein</l>
                  <l>lehr mich dir recht gehorsam sein</l>
                  <l>ergiess Dich reichlich uber mich</l>
                  <l>Zum Pfingst-Fest das erwarte ich.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="6">
               <head>Page 6 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-06" />
               </head>
               <figure>
                  <ab>X X</ab>
               </figure>
               <lg>
                  <l>Und hofe auf ein seligs Jahr</l>
                  <l>Als sonsten noch Nie keines war.</l>
                  <l>O dass du mich so schmuktest aus,</l>
                  <l>Dass mich mein Mann nehm bald nach Houss.</l>
               </lg>
               <figure>
                  <ab>X X</ab>
               </figure>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wie würde doch dem Würmelein</l>
                  <l>Beym Sehn des Lams zu Muthe sein</l>
                  <l>Vielleicht ben ich heut ubers Iahr</l>
                  <l>By Ihm in seiner obern Sohaar.</l>
               </lg>
               <figure>
                  <ab>X X</ab>
               </figure>
               <lg>
                  <l>Drum soll myn Aug auf nichls mehr Sehn</l>
                  <l>Als nur auf seine Leidens Schön</l>
                  <l>Dem Ohr gefalle sonst kein Klang</l>
                  <l>als nur der Passions Gesang.</l>
               </lg>
               <p> It was very plain to be perceived, that the holy Ghost hastened with her Adornment; She could herself nothing imagine more sweet as to receive the last Kiss from the lovely Lips of
                  her Lover; and <del rend="strikethrough">this</del> her last Sickness was the Opportunity to still her <sic>Disire</sic>
                  <corr>Desire</corr>. The <date>23</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> of March</date>, She was taken by a hard fit of Colic, that She was forced to keep to her
                  Bed, but by all her Pain, the Conversation w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> our dear Saviour &amp; his Smart &amp; Sufferings made her Sick bed <sic>easly</sic>
                  <corr>easily</corr> &amp; suportable supportable to her. </p>
               <p> The <date>24</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi> She found herself very weak &amp; <note type="catchword">expected</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="7">
               <head>Page 7 <seg ana="MemBeth_0138-07" />
               </head>
               <div>
                  <p> her great Sabbath Day with extaordnary Longing took tender Leave by Words so much for Weakness' would allow to express by her Brother, Sister &amp; other
                           <sic>Aquaint</sic><sic><sic>ances</sic></sic>
                     <corr>Acquaintances</corr>, but <sic>afterwarts</sic>
                     <corr>afterwards</corr> She expressd her tender Love by a smiling Look on, [a] so She remaineth present to herself to the last Gap or Breath. When They sung verses, She refresheth
                     her Heart by and sung <add>accompanied</add> w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> a broken Voice, sometimes strechd out her Arms towards her Brautigroom! </p>
                  <p> As the last Moment came nearer, then they <sic>Blest</sic>
                     <corr>Blessed</corr> her in the Name of her Choir w.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> a <sic>un- comon</sic>
                     <corr>uncommon</corr> Feeling of the Nearness of our dear Saviour, &amp; under these Words: Ihr Glieder rein Gott ehr euch, des heilge Geist ver- klär euch. flew the
                        <date>23</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi> in the Evening her reconciled Soul happy home in the Wounds of Jesus Christ. A still &amp; blessed Peace of God
                        <sic>extented</sic>
                     <corr>extended</corr> themselves about all who were present &amp; left to her <sic>Corps</sic>
                     <corr>Corpse</corr> a lovely Prospect. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
