<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/moravianlives/master/TEI_Memoirs/XML/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lewis Thorn: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Repository Name</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033">Lewis Thorn</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-05.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-06.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>Lewis Thorn</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-01">1</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="align-right">departed May 12, 1754</hi>
                  <lb /> Lewis William Thorn was born the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of febr. 1746: His Father who is at present in Wales in the Service of our Saviour: gave him in the Childrens
                     <sic>Oeconomy</sic>
                  <corr>Economy</corr> then at Buttermare in the month of March 1749, from whence he came with the rest of the Children to Yorkshire 5 Years ago. Before his Disorder, which began in
                  the Month of March 1751, he was a very lively and brisk Child; had a tender Feeling of the wounded Person of our Saviour, and also such a very happy Turn of Mind, that his Brethren
                  give him the Testimony, that they were able by one Word spoken in Love to manage him ac, cording to their whole Wish. In March 1751 He got a swelling in his Back, which after a while
                  proved to be 2 great Holes, that grew worse evry Day notwithstanding all what B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hurlock did with great Faithfulness to help the Case. The following sum,
                  mer his Wounds began to smell so strong, that we were oblig'd to think of getting him separated from the other Children who were greatly troubled with it; but since we had in
                  Smithouse no such Thing as a Sick Room, we thro' the Direction of Br Marshall found out B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Foulers, who took it upon
                  themselves to nurse him for a weekly Payment <del>according</del> till we should be able more conveniently to do it ourselves. This Separation from the Children was a great Grief and
                  Mortification to the little Heart, and not much less to us, who were only forced to comply with necessity. In these Circumstances he remain'd till we remov'd from Smithouse to
                  Lambshill in May 1753, when we by order from our B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> in London as also according to our own Hearts and that obliga, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-02">2</head>
               <p> tion we were under on his account took him home again; as much Pain as it did cost him the first time to part with us, so much Pain it now cost him to part with his Nurse, <add
                     place="above">who had taken a tender Care of him</add> to whom he was attach'd in an uncommon Manner, and whom he <del>suposted</del>
                  <sic>suposed</sic>
                  <corr>supposed</corr> to be his natural Mother; <del>till</del> to <sic>loose</sic>
                  <corr>lose</corr> this Object of [?] his affection made him for the first Week very melancholy and even sick; till he got again into the Company of his Children, and his Heart
                     <del>met</del> got <del>[unreadable] Object of Love</del>
                  <add place="above">rid of this attachment by the Enjoyment of the Wounds of</add> his so much beloved Saviour; then he was again quite in his Element, and never from that Time
                  troubled any more about other things. Since last Christmas he had a particular Period of grace, and we felt constantly on him, that his Heart was nearly engaged with the Wounds of
                  Jesus; he oftentimes on his own accord kept little Meetings for the Children in his Room, got them together in a Ring and sung verses with them, and then told them, what a tender
                  Love our Saviour had for the Children, and how many Wounds and Bruises, he had got out of Love for them etc. At other times he got them together and prostrated with them at the Feet
                  of our dear Saviour, and sung many delightful verses with them; this he did very often and always in such a priestly and Composed Way, attended with an exceeding great Nearness of
                  the Lamb, that he gain'd all the other Childrens Love and respect in a particular Manner. A good while ago a Surgeon from Leeds M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lawman was here to see
                     B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Planta, who took him with Him in our House </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-03">3</head>
               <p>to hear his opinion of our sick Children; when he saw our little departed Heart, he said, that several Bones would come out of the Wounds, which a little while after prov'd to be
                  true; only they did not come interely entirely out, but remain'd in the Mouth of the Wounds, and stop'd <del>up</del> them <del>[?]</del> up, that they could not be cleansed any
                  more, which caused, that the Matter remain'd within and infected his inward Parts, without any body's body being able to help it: this caused him again to smell so strong, that no
                  body could scarcely bear to be near him, and at the same time made himself and us all believe that he would soon go to our Saviour.</p>
               <p> The 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May after the Childrens Meeting B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Petersen had all the little Children round about him, and spoke with them
                  about their Hearts' Connexion Connection with our Saviour; and at once there was such an emphatical Presence of our Saviour amongst them, that evry one of them wept heartily, and
                  told Br. Petersen, how happy and melted they felt their Hearts; and among the rest our little Lewis William was so affected, that he could not give over weeping for a long while; and
                  afterwards complain'd to the Chil, dren that he was not yet baptized, and wish'd so heartily, that he might soon partake of that great Happiness.</p>
               <p> The 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May I went to him and spoke with him, asking him, if he knew that he was not yet baptized; he said, he knew it very well, but long'd very
                  heartily to be baptized; I ask'd him, when he should like it. He said: O this very day. I then told him</p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-04">4</head>
               <p>(for it was already made out with the Brethren) that this grace should be bestowed upon him this very Evening; O how glad was he, and said to Br. Petersen, but do you know I shall be
                  baptized this Evening? O yes. I shall: then said Br. Petersen to him; but dear Billy? tell me in what Manner will you come to our Saviour? He said: as <del>[?]</del> Mary Magdalen,
                  who wept over his Feet, and kiss'd them and wip'd them with the Hairs of her Head; and as he said this, the Tears rolld all the while down his Cheeks, and they sung together: we are
                  thy Children small and mean who in ourselves are nought but Sin, but his Wounds Roses Fragrancy perfum'd us to a sanctuary.In the Singing Hour that same Evening after being dressed
                  in a proper Manner according to his weak Dis, position <del>and</del> he was brought into the Hall, and there in an inexpressible happy Manner overstream'd with the Blood and Water
                  out of Jesus side, and call'd Lewis William: What there was felt at this opportunity I leave to the Hearts of all the Brethren and Sisters that were present: and so he went happily
                  to Bed and slept all Night like an Angel: in the Morning we ask'd him, how it had been in his Heart at his Baptism, he said: O I can't express it, how warm and sweet it was to
                  me.</p>
               <p> The following whole Week he grew weaker and weaker, and if we ask'd him if he had much Pain? he said, no, none. but I said: dear Heart does your Breast not hurt you? no, Said he:
                  and so he laid like a Lamb all the while and smiled some</p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-05">5</head>
               <p> for himself, and if we ask'd him, what he thought about? he said: I think of our Saviour and his Wounds, and will soon go to kiss his Feet; and he said further: all my Play things
                  divide among the other Children; and then he said to Petersen: this is my <sic>Favourit</sic>
                  <corr>Favourite</corr> Verse: Thus reclining always twining etc. The 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of May in the Evening about 10 o Clock I went to see him and saw it drew nearer
                  towards his Departure: I ask'd him, if he then intended soon to leave us? yes he said very soon: for I go soon to my Saviour? but I said: dear Heart, tell me what will you do as soon
                  as you come there? He said: I will run di, rectly to kiss his thro' bored Feet; but I said, will you then do the same in our Name? He said: O yes I will; then we sang him some verses
                  and went <del>al</del> to Bed: near 1 o' Clock we were call'd up again, and then he was going , we sung him: The Lamb with all his Grief and Smart etc. Pale Lips! kiss him upon the
                  Heart! open Arms take him. during which last Words he fell sweetly and happily asleep in the Arms of his so beloved Bridegroom with this Watchword of the Day: <hi rend="underline"
                     >Get up, my beloved and beautiful one, and come to me! Here I am, my Lord and God, instruct me.</hi></p>
               <p> The happy Departure of this little Heart is for several Reasons of a very agreeable Nature; for he would never in his Life got his Health rightly again any more; and 2<hi
                     rend="superscript">dly</hi>, he was quite ripe for it, as to his <sic>Connexion</sic>
                  <corr>Connection</corr> with the Saviour; He is now out of all Danger and rests in Peace; and the several little</p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="6">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-06">6</head>
               <p> Scenes of his short Life, <del>which</del> were regulated by him, who pre, pared him for a happy Rest in his own Bosom, in such a Man, ner, that we have not the least uneasiness
                  about any Step that was taken with him, but are heartily convinced and satisfied, that the Mind and whole Aim of the Lamb is obtaind with him, <del>and wish all only that all who
                     loved him, might be as happy as he was, and find the Way into the Wounds of Jesus so surely and plainly as he has found it.</del> has been read in Okbrook Aug. the 18<hi
                     rend="superscript">th</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
