<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lewis Thorn: Memoir</title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator, 2015-2018 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Repository Name</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033">Lewis Thorn</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-05.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300033-06.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>Lewis Thorn</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-01">1</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="align-right">departed May 12, 1754</hi> Lewis William Thorn was born the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of febr. 1746: His Father who is at present in Wales in the Service
                  of our Saviour: gave him in the Childrens <sic>Oeconomy</sic>
                  <corr>Economy</corr> then at Buttermare in the month of March 1749, from whence he came with the rest of the Children to Yorkshire 5 Years ago. Before his Disorder, which began in
                  the Month of March 1751, he was a very lively and brisk Child; had a tender Feeling of the wounded Person of our Saviour, and also such a very happy Turn of Mind, that his Brethren
                  give him the Testimony, that they were able by one Word spoken in Love to manage him ac, cording to their whole Wish. In March 1751 He got a swelling in his Back, which after a while
                  proved to be 2 great Holes, that grew worse evry Day notwithstanding all what B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hurlock did with great Faithfulness to help the Case. The following sum,
                  mer his Wounds began to smell so strong, that we were oblig'd to think of getting him separated from the other Children who were greatly troubled with it; but since we had in
                  Smithouse no such Thing as a Sick Room, we thro' the Direction of Br Marshall found out B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Foulers, who took it upon
                  themselves to nurse him for a weekly Payment <del>according</del> till we should be able more conveniently to do it ourselves. This Separation from the Children was a great Grief and
                  Mortification to the little Heart, and not much less to us, who were only forced to comply with necessity. In these Circumstances he remain'd till we remov'd from Smithouse to
                  Lambshill in May 1753, when we by order from our B<hi rend="superscript">rn</hi> in London as also according to our own Hearts and that obliga, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head type="page" ana="MCH/MemLon_300033-02">2</head>
               <p> tion we were under on his account took him home again; as much Pain as it did cost him the first time to part with us, so much Pain it now cost him to part with his Nurse, who had
                  taken a tender Care of him to whom he was attach'd in an uncommon Manner, and whom he <del>suposted</del>
                  <sic>suposed</sic>
                  <corr>supposed</corr> to be his natural Mother; <del>till</del> to <sic>loose</sic>
                  <corr>lose</corr> this Object of [?] his affection made him for the first Week very melancholy and even sick; till he got again into the Company of his Children, and his Heart
                     <del>met</del> got <del>[?] [?] [?] [?] Object of Love</del>
                  <add place="above">rid of this attachment by the Enjoyment of the Wounds of</add> his so much beloved Saviour; then he was again quite in his Element, and never from that Time
                  troubled any more about other things. Since last Christmas he had a particular Period of grace, and we felt constantly on him, that his Heart was nearly engaged with the Wounds of
                  Jesus; he oftentimes on his own accord kept little Meetings for the Children in his Room, got them together in a Ring and sung verses with them, and then told them, what a tender
                  Love our Saviour had for the Children, and how many Wounds and Bruises, he had got out of Love for them etc. At other times he got them together and prostrated with them at the Feet
                  of our dear Saviour, and sung many delightful verses with them; this he did very often and always in such a priestly and Composed Way, attended with an exceeding great Nearness of
                  the Lamb, that he gain'd all the other Childrens Love and respect in a particular Manner. A good while ago a Surgeon from Leeds M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lawman was here to see
                     B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Planta, who took him with Him in our House </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
