<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sarah Verney: Memoir
            </title>
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator 2015-18 <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marita Gruner</persName>
               <orgName>University of Greifswald</orgName>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Moravian Archives, London</repository>
                  <msName type="memoir" ana="MCH/MemLon_300047">Sarah Verney memoir</msName>
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-01.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-02.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-03.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-04.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-05.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-06.jpg" />
                  <msName facs="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MCH/MemLon_300047-07.jpg" />
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="memoir">
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <div type="memoir">
            <head>Sarah Verney memoir, page 1</head>
            <div type="page" n="1">
               <head>Page 1 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-01" />
               </head>
               <p> The Life of our <hi rend="underline">late Sister <persName>Sarah Verney</persName></hi> who <hi rend="underline">departed</hi> this life <date><hi rend="underline">January 6<hi
                           rend="superscript">th</hi></hi></date> who has left the following account of herself.</p>
               <p>I was <hi rend="underline">born</hi>
                  <date>Octob<hi rend="underline">er 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1758</hi></date> at <placeName><hi rend="underline">Waltham Cross</hi></placeName> in the pa<hi rend="underline"
                     >rish</hi> of <placeName><hi rend="underline">Cheshunt</hi>
                     <hi rend="underline">Hertfordshire</hi></placeName> in my 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                  <abbr>Yr</abbr>. I lost my dear Mother as a child I was very wild, and thought little about my Souls Salvation consequently I had no inclination to attend divine Service, to which my
                  Father did not force me, but in other respects was very strict <add>with</add> me preventing me from dressing and mixing with such company as I gladly <sic>woud</sic>
                  <corr>would</corr> have done; of course I as also my 2 <abbr>Brs</abbr> and <abbr>Sr</abbr> were <abbr>obligd</abbr> to keep strictly at home. In my 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                  year I went to <placeName><hi rend="underline">London</hi></placeName> on a visit to see an acquaintance of my Fathers, who indeed <abbr>appear'd</abbr> very gay, and just as I
                     <sic>coud</sic>
                  <corr>could</corr> like to be She moreover took me to see many things in <placeName>London</placeName> and in short <abbr>gratifyd</abbr> me in every thing She was able, all which
                     <abbr>pleasd</abbr> me highly and made me wish to leave my Fathers house, merely that I might have more liber -ty the above mentioned person also <abbr>asurd</abbr> me that one
                  might very well enjoy the pleasures of this world, and yet be sincere in heart, in my 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Year my Father went to <placeName>London</placeName> on a
                  visit, and took me along with him <hi rend="underline">to <persName><abbr>B.</abbr></persName><hi rend="superscript"><persName><abbr>r</abbr></persName></hi><persName>
                        Gibb</persName>'s</hi> who <abbr>wishd</abbr> that I might stay a while with them of which I was very glad, hoping it <sic>woud</sic>
                  <corr>would</corr> prove the means of my getting entirely away from home, the next Sunday <persName><abbr>Sr</abbr>
                     <hi rend="underline">Gibbs</hi></persName> took me to the <hi rend="underline"><abbr>B.</abbr></hi><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rns</abbr></hi><hi rend="underline"> Chapel</hi>
                  which I <abbr>dislikd</abbr> very much, as that was not the way I <abbr>wishd</abbr> to steer my course, She next took me to see the <abbr><hi rend="underline">S.</hi></abbr><hi
                     rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>le</abbr></hi></hi><abbr><hi rend="underline"> Srs</hi></abbr>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="2">
               <head>Page 2 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-02" />
               </head>
               <p>who treated me with much love, so that I in time got a love for the People of the <abbr>Brn</abbr>
                  <abbr>tho</abbr> I had nothing in my heart, and as I frequented some of the meetings, and also kept up a <sic>conexion</sic>
                  <corr>connection</corr> with the <abbr>S</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> I got more and more love for them, and at last found myself very happy among them, so that
                  I thought I had now <abbr>obtaind</abbr> every thing, and simply related my happiness to any one to whom I had an opportunity of doing it, but once during a Sermon of the late
                        <persName><abbr>B.</abbr></persName><hi rend="superscript"><persName><abbr>r</abbr></persName></hi><persName> LasTrobes</persName> concerning the Sin of unbelief, I was all at
                  once <abbr>convinc'd</abbr> that I by nature was full of Sin and misery, this being quite the contra- -ry to what I had so lately felt and thought of myself it made me quite ashamed
                  to speak to any of those with whom I had formerly <abbr>conversd</abbr> thinking they woud look upon me as nothing but a hypocrite, this brought on a reservedness, which lasted many
                  Years, so that I spent my time in continual heaviness, keeping every thing to myself, I <abbr>discoverd</abbr> more and more how deeply I was Spoild by Sin, of which I felt
                     <sic>powerfull</sic>
                  <corr>powerful</corr> stirring with me, I had also many Struggles with regard to the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> and the world, wishing at times to
                  give myself up entire_ ly to our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>, and at other times to follow my natural inclination in the world, but all this I kept to
                  myself thinking if I <abbr>disclosd</abbr> the bad things I felt, I shoud be <abbr>deprivd</abbr> of all <sic>conexion</sic>
                  <corr>connection</corr> with the <abbr>B</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rn</abbr></hi> and if I told the good desires of my heart, I shoud be thought a hypocrite and thus I
                     <abbr>reasond</abbr> within myself Year after Year, in my 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year as I was at the <abbr>G.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> Sabbath
                  lovefeast, my heart was very dark, I thought there coud be no truth in our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> being a Corpse, and began to think we were
                     <abbr>decievd</abbr> in the whole affair, but as I for pon_ -dering over it, and <abbr>supposd</abbr> it might be time, I began </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="3">
               <head>Page 3 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-03" />
               </head>
               <p>to be <abbr>frighten'd</abbr> at myself, thinking how <abbr>wou'd</abbr> it be with me in this unbelieving way, <abbr>shou'd</abbr> my Soul be <abbr>calld</abbr> out of this world,
                  this <abbr>occasion'd</abbr> me to Sigh to our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> O that I <abbr>cou'd</abbr> but believe, no sooner had this sigh burst from
                  my heart, but it was as if our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>
                  <abbr>appear'd</abbr> before me in his Corpse's figure, and <abbr>asur'd</abbr> me that it was on <del>my</del> account of my Sins that He had <sic>sufford</sic>
                  <corr>suffered</corr> and <abbr>dy'd</abbr> and that he had thereby <abbr>procur'd</abbr> peace and <sic>forgivness</sic>
                  <corr>forgiveness</corr> for me, this was accompanied with such a di -vine feeling of peace that I shall never forget it. I had also several other particular visits of grace, all
                     <abbr>w</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr><hi rend="underline">ch</hi></abbr></hi> I kept quite to myself, notwithstanding the great love and kindness I <abbr>experienc'd</abbr>
                  from my Labouress, I <abbr>cou'd</abbr> not be <abbr>prevail'd</abbr> upon to open my heart, and at such <sic>opportunitys</sic>
                  <corr>opportunities</corr>
                  <abbr>cou'd</abbr> only give vent to tears, which made her think I must have something very particular upon my mind. In my 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year I went to learn the
                  Tambour work in the <orgName><abbr><hi rend="underline">S</hi></abbr></orgName><hi rend="superscript"><orgName><abbr><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></abbr></orgName></hi><orgName><hi
                        rend="underline"> House</hi></orgName>, and as I <abbr>look'd</abbr> upon them to be good <abbr>S</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> it was of us to me, as they
                  were one day in boundlike conversation among themselves to find that they also felt such things as I did which <abbr>help'd</abbr> to remove the load under which I had
                     <abbr>labour'd</abbr> so many years, after this I had a desire to move en- -tirely into the <orgName><hi rend="underline"><abbr>S</abbr></hi></orgName><hi rend="underline"><hi
                        rend="superscript"><orgName><abbr>rs</abbr></orgName></hi><orgName> House at </orgName><placeName><orgName>London</orgName></placeName></hi>, which I however cou'd not get
                  leave for, but it was made out for me to go to <placeName><hi rend="underline">Fulneck</hi></placeName> into the <hi rend="underline">Choirhouse</hi> there, this was a great trial
                  for me, hearing so much of the poverty there besides leaving all my friends and acquaintances, but our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> enabled me to
                  resolve to live for him, and in the place he had appointed, <abbr>show'd</abbr> I even have to live upon bread and water, I accordingly <abbr>arriv'd</abbr> in
                     <placeName>Fulneck</placeName>
                  <date>March 5</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> 1779</date> and found contrary to my expectation </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="4">
               <head>Page 4 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-04" />
               </head>
               <p>every thing very comfortable; and trusting in our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> I never wanted for any thing; the first year of my abode here, I met
                  with some difficulties, but the nearness of our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> comforted me, He not only made it clear to me that I was in my right
                  place, but he made me sensible that every trial I met with was with a view to establish <add>me in</add> his grace, thus I took all wish resignation as out of his hands.
                     <abbr>Oct.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> that same year I had the favor to be <abbr>reci</abbr><hi rend="underline"
                        ><abbr>ev'd</abbr> into the <abbr>Cong</abbr></hi><abbr>.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> and <date>December 2</date><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><date>d</date></hi><date> 1780</date> to be admitted for the first time to the Holy born after which I spent <hi rend="underline">5 years</hi> very comfortably in the <hi
                     rend="underline">Ch: house</hi>. <date>April 4</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date>
                     <hi rend="underline">1785</hi></date> I <abbr>mov'd</abbr> to the <orgName><abbr>S</abbr></orgName><hi rend="superscript"><orgName><abbr>rs</abbr></orgName></hi><orgName> Oecon at
                        </orgName><placeName><orgName>Wyke</orgName></placeName> to <hi rend="underline">live</hi> with the <abbr><hi rend="underline">G. G.r</hi></abbr><hi rend="underline">
                     there</hi>, the beginning of my living there was attended with some difficulties, but in time they were <abbr>remov'd</abbr>, and we <abbr>liv'd</abbr> happily together in the
                  nearness of our dear <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> till at a certain period I gave way to reasoning concerning the Labourers, and our
                     <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> leading in the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> into which I <abbr>enter'd</abbr> so far
                  that I lost <del>??</del> sight of our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> and of my call to the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi>,
                  thinking I might as well live somewhere else, this brought me into great distress as I knew not which way to do, nor <abbr>cou'd</abbr> I speak of my distress to any one for a while,
                  till <hi rend="underline"><abbr>S.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>
                     <persName>Anna Turos</persName></hi> from <placeName><hi rend="underline">Fulneck</hi></placeName> paid us a visit, I <abbr>open'd</abbr> my whole mind to her, she treated me with
                  much love, which was a comfort to me, but still I found no real help, my distress still <abbr>encreas'd</abbr>, and I began to think, was it possible that I <abbr>cou'd</abbr> ever
                  come into a happy simple track again, or was I gone too far, which indeed <abbr>seem'd</abbr> to be my case, so that I was <sic>thankfull</sic>
                  <corr>thankful</corr> when I felt a wish, and <abbr>cou'd</abbr> sigh to our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> for help, thinking he </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="5">
               <head>Page 5 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-05" />
               </head>
               <p>perhaps woud return to me, as he had done at various other times, but he found best to hide his face from me for near a year, thus I spent that time in heaviness often praying in the
                  distress of my Soul for another look of his grace, thinking at every meeting I went to, perhaps this <abbr>wou'd</abbr> be the <abbr>favor'd</abbr> time, but he <abbr>de-
                     -lay'd</abbr> it till by means of the last Synodal letter to the <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>ns</abbr></hi> he granted me to see myself in the right light,
                  worse indeed than any <add>of those</add> over whom I had <abbr>reason'd</abbr> He also gave me grace to be <sic>truely</sic>
                  <corr>truly</corr> a sinner before him and he in mercy forgave me anew, but I cannot express in words how <abbr>asham'd</abbr> I was, and <sic>truely</sic>
                  <corr>truly</corr>
                  <abbr>abas'd</abbr> before him on account of my unfaithfulness in that respect, but it had that blessed effect, that I <add>and since the end of <date>1759</date> I lived in a very
                     happy communion with him</add> Kept more sinnerlikely to him afterwards, <hi rend="underline"><date><abbr>Sep.</abbr></date><hi rend="superscript"
                        ><date><abbr>r</abbr></date></hi><date> 29 1790</date> I <abbr>rec'd</abbr></hi> a call to enter into the <hi rend="underline"><abbr>mar.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                     </abbr>State with</hi> my <hi rend="underline">late dear Husband <abbr>B.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>
                     <persName>Thomas Verney</persName></hi>, He being <abbr>call'd</abbr> to be <hi rend="underline">Labourer</hi> of the <hi rend="underline"><abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"
                           ><abbr>n</abbr></hi> at <placeName>Wyke</placeName></hi>, unfit as I felt myself for this office, yet I felt a dearness to accept of it, we were accordingly <abbr>mar.<hi
                        rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                  <date><abbr>Oct.</abbr></date><hi rend="superscript"><date><abbr>r</abbr></date></hi><date> 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1790</date> and <abbr>introduc'd</abbr> to the
                     <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> at <placeName>Wyke</placeName> on the <date>31</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>st</date></hi> the same day my dear
                  Husband was <hi rend="underline"><abbr>ordain'd</abbr> a Deacon</hi> of the <abbr>B.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rns</abbr></hi> Church by <abbr>B.</abbr><hi
                     rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>
                  <persName>Traneker</persName>, my dear Husband being of a sickly habit made it somewhat trying, but our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> nearness
                  supported us in a very gracious manner, and made the short time of our marriage a time of blessing. <date><abbr>Dec.</abbr></date><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><date><abbr>r</abbr></date></hi><date> 4</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi><date> 1791</date> I was safely <abbr>deliver'd</abbr> of a <hi rend="underline"
                     >Daughter</hi>, whom my dear Husband <abbr><hi rend="underline">baptiz'd</hi></abbr> on the <date>11</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi> by the name <persName><hi
                        rend="underline">Sarah</hi></persName> which was his last public transaction, for by this time his disorder had terminated in a Consumption </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="6">
               <head>Page 6 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-06" />
               </head>
               <p>in which he <abbr>linger'd</abbr> till <date><hi rend="underline">May 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1792</hi></date> when his happy soul took flight to its Redeemer, what I felt
                  as this period is past description, but our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> Supported me beyond what I <abbr>cou'd</abbr> have expected. <date>Aug<hi
                        rend="underline">ust 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1792</hi></date> I <abbr>mov'd</abbr> to <placeName><hi rend="underline">Fulneck</hi></placeName> with my dear Child,
                  where as well as in <placeName>Wyke</placeName> I have <abbr>experien'ed</abbr> much Sympathetic love and kindness from the <abbr>B.</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"
                           ><abbr>rn</abbr></hi></hi> and <abbr>S.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> to whom I now wish to return my hearty thanks for the same, <date>August
                     22</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>d</date></hi><date> 1794</date> I being in a poor State of health, my dear Child was <abbr>plac'd</abbr> in the Girl<hi rend="underline">s
                     Oeconomy</hi> here, <sic>painfull</sic>
                  <corr>painful</corr> as it is to me to think of leaving her entirely, our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> has enabled me to be <abbr>resign'd</abbr> to
                  his will, to leave her to the <sic>faithfull</sic>
                  <corr>faithful</corr> care of him and his dear <abbr>Cong.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi> and I now wait with longing for the happy moment when I shall be
                     <abbr>releas'd</abbr> from all pain, and see him face to face, in myself I am very poor, and destitute of every thing, therefore when I am per- -mitted to see him, I shall have
                  nothing to plead but his allsufficient merits. So far her own <abbr>acc.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>t</abbr></hi> Our late <abbr>S.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"
                        ><abbr>r</abbr></hi> having left such a candid <abbr>acc.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>t</abbr></hi> of herself tis needless to add much thereto, but we can't help saying
                  a few words of her faithfulness in whatever has been committed to her as well during the time She <abbr>liv'd</abbr> with the <abbr>G.Gr</abbr> in <placeName><hi rend="underline"
                        >Wyke</hi></placeName>, as also in the short period of her <abbr>mar.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr> State, in both which She <abbr>approv'd</abbr> herself as one who had
                  the cause of our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi>
                  <sic>truely</sic>
                  <corr>truly</corr> at heart, and he in a particular manner <abbr>bless'd</abbr> her endeavours, granting her as <abbr>tho</abbr> sometime to enjoy the love and confidence of those
                  with whom She had to do, She has for a considerable time hear <sic>lickely</sic>
                  <corr>likely</corr>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="page" n="7">
               <head>Page 7 <seg ana="MemLon_300047-07" />
               </head>
               <p>which at last terminated in a Consumption, and <abbr>tho</abbr> her attachment to her dear Child made her <add>at first</add> desirous to recover, yet our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi
                     rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> enabled her to acquiesce in his will, and She had also that comfort to know her child <abbr>wou'd</abbr> be well <abbr>car'd</abbr> for, the
                  time of her sickness She spent in <sic>stilness</sic>
                  <corr>stillness</corr>, often intonating in few words how near She felt our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi> at times, and when this was not the case, She
                  waited in stillness at his feet believing he <abbr>wou'd</abbr> not leave nor forsake her, she also bore her Sickness with much <sic>patiance</sic>
                  <corr>patience</corr>, and was glad to be visited by her <abbr>S.</abbr><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>rs </abbr></hi>
                  <date><abbr>Dec.</abbr></date><hi rend="superscript"><date><abbr>r</abbr></date></hi><date> 14</date><hi rend="superscript"><date>th</date></hi> her share of the Holy born <hi
                     rend="superscript">n</hi> was brought to her, after which She <abbr>express'd</abbr> how well She had felt, <date><abbr>Jan</abbr> 15</date><hi rend="superscript"
                     ><date>th</date></hi> being for- -sible that her end was approaching, She <abbr>desir'd</abbr> to recieve the last blessing, mentioning at the same time some <abbr>S.</abbr><hi
                     rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> who She <abbr>wish'd</abbr> to be presemt, the same was imparted to her, during a happy perception of our <abbr>Sav.</abbr><hi
                     rend="superscript"><abbr>rs</abbr></hi> divine presence, after which she said she felt very happy, and now she <abbr>long'd</abbr> for the happy moment to come when she
                     <abbr>shou'd</abbr> see her Re- -deemer face to face, which came to pass <add>about 5 o clock</add> next morning when she <abbr>expir'd</abbr> gently <hi rend="underline">Aged 36
                     years</hi> 3 months and 3 days. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
