<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="out/MoravianMemoirs.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>John Friedrich Gocht: Memoir
               <lang>English</lang>
            </title>               
            <funder>The Moravian Lives Project</funder>
            <principal><persName>Katherine Mary Faull</persName>, Principal Investigator
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lewisburg, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>faull@bucknell.edu</email>
            </principal>
            <principal><persName>Christer Ahlberger</persName>, Principal Investigator
               <orgName>University of Gothenburg</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gothenburg, Sweden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>christer.ahlberger@history.gu.se</email>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Michael McGuire</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Developer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carly Masonheimer</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Marleina Cohen</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Research Assistant and encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <orgName>The Moravian Archives</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>41 West Locust Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bethlehem, PA 18018-2757</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>info@moravianchurcharchives.org</addrLine>
               </address>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>The Moravian Lives Project</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>               
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Life of John Friedrich Gocht</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>

                 <div type="memoir">
                    <pb type="page" n="1" ana=".10199.26027"/>
            <figure n="199-01">
               <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-01.jpg"/>
               <ab type="caption">John Friedrich Gocht, Page 1</ab>
            </figure>
            
            <div type="para" n="1">
            <p>
               
               <lb /><gap></gap>Personals of our <hi rend="underline">Worthy <persName>Brother John Friedrich
                  <lb />Gocht</persName></hi> who departed this Life the <date>31<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi>. of January 1769.</date> at
               <lb /><placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName>. <gap></gap>He left the following written Account of his Path
               <lb />I was born at <placeName>Ni</placeName><hi rend="underline"><placeName>eder Oderwiz</placeName> </hi>the <date>30<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>. of December 1697</date> and
               <lb />brought up by my Parents to all good. From my Infancy I had
               <lb />no Talent for the World, yet my Corruption lay the deeper. In
               <lb />time I had an insight into the Holy Ghosts seeking my heart
               <lb />which I then did not understand. At length I became <abbr>concernd</abbr>
               <lb />for my Salvation, more particularly in my 14<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>. Year when I
               <lb />partook the Holy Sacrament the first time at which I shed many
               <lb />Tears. <gap></gap>After this I came into a Light wordly minded way and
               <lb />went on some Years under Divine Patience, <abbr>Till</abbr> Divine Love
               <lb /><abbr>Touch'd</abbr> my Heart, and convinced me of my unbelief in the time
               <lb />of <date>Lent 1719</date>. <gap></gap>In the Passion Week my Continual Prayer was,
               <lb />that our Saviour would have Mercy on me, and grant me the
               <lb /><sic>Benifit</sic> <corr>Benefit</corr> of his Precious Blood Shedding. My Request that he
               <lb />would graciously Pleased to look favourably on me was granted
               <lb />and I <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> Comfort, It came in my Mind that I could be <abbr>helpd</abbr>
               <lb />if I would apply to our Saviour as a poor Sinner. But the Sinner
               <lb />=ship was a Mystery, I rather <abbr>employ'd</abbr> myself in Reading and An=
               <lb />=xious seeking. To this was added thy intention to Marry.
               <lb />After praying to God to give me a Person wholly devoted to him, I married
               <lb />the <date>19<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>. of <abbr>Novem</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>r</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi><abbr>.</abbr> 1723</date> |:the present <sic>Widdow</sic> <corr>Widow</corr>:| Our Saviour <abbr>bless'd</abbr> us
               <lb />with 3 Sons and 1 Daughter, but has taken Them all 4 to himself
               <lb />I <abbr>endeavourd</abbr> to the Uttmost of my Power to act up to the best of my know=
               <lb />=ledge, yet my heart was without feeling, <sic>untill</sic> <corr>until</corr> Eternal Love brought
               <lb />a Text of Scripture to my Mind at the time I was <abbr>employ'd</abbr> in my
               <lb />Business the Text was this: as many as are led by the Spirit <add>they</add> are the Sons

               <pb type="double_left" n="2" ana=".10199.26028"/>
               <figure n="199-02">
                  <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-02.jpg"/>
                  <ab type="caption">John Friedrich Gocht, Page 2</ab>
               </figure>

               <lb />of God. This <abbr>caus'd</abbr> me great Concern. I <abbr>pray'd</abbr> and Sigh Shew me
               <lb />thy ways <abbr>O</abbr> Lord that I may <sic>walth</sic> <corr>walkth</corr> in thy Truth! He <abbr>answerd</abbr> me I will
               <lb />direct thee and shew the way thou shalt go, I will guide thee with my
               <lb />Eyes. About this time there was a great <abbr>awakning</abbr> at <add><placeName>Oderwitz</placeName></add> which
               <lb />I would fain have <abbr>joind</abbr>, but at first, fear of Man gave me much
               <lb />trouble, yet I was convinced in my heart that I should find what
               <lb />I sought. I went to <placeName>Berthrelsdorff</placeName> and heard <persName>Pastor Rothe</persName> preach
               <lb />|:which I had done once before:| and in his Sermon he gave me
               <lb />such a plain description of my State of Soul as <abbr>tho</abbr> I had before
               <lb />told him of it. And now the <sic>perscecution</sic> <corr>persecution</corr> began which did not
               <lb />terrifyme, I felt peculiar Grace in my heart, and had I <abbr>remaind</abbr>
               <lb />in my Simplicity, I should have avoided many a heavy hour
               <lb />But instead of that I came into self Workings, I went to the Parson
               <lb />and told him my whole State he often told me I was in the right
               <lb />way I should only pray to God to bring me further in his Grace
               <lb />but no sooner did he see that I conversed with souls who were
               <lb />convinced how wrong their former Life had been then he <abbr>indea-</abbr>
                  <lb /><abbr>=vourd</abbr> to hinder me all he could. The Meetings at <placeName>Oderwitz</placeName>
                  <lb />was forbidden, and a great Number was Arrested and taken to
                  <lb /><placeName>Zittau</placeName>. As I was much <abbr>concern'd</abbr> about these people I went a
                  <lb />few days after to enquire <sic>wether</sic> <corr>whether</corr> they were set at Liberty or
                  <lb />not. Just as I came to <persName>Gottlieb Webers</persName> House 2 Men laid
                  <lb />hold of me and would carry me before a Justice, not knowing
               <lb />for what cause, I refused to comply, they broke their Sticks
               <lb />over my head and so evil intreated me that I fell to the Earth
               <lb />without <sic>Sensce</sic> <corr>Sense</corr> or Motion, a Number of People being <abbr>gatherd</abbr> the
               <lb />Men made off, as soon as I came to myself my first thought
               <lb />was:Lord forgive them. I went home and felt very happy
               <lb />The Next day I could scarce hold up my Head for Pain. I now
               <lb /><sic>keept</sic> <corr>kept</corr> quiet at home and only went now and then to Church
               <lb />some time after the Lord of the Place sent an Officer to bring me
               <lb />before him and <abbr>ask'd</abbr> me, <sic>wether</sic> <corr>whether</corr> I acknowledged the Articles
<lb /><abbr>deliverd</abbr>

<pb type="double_right" />

               <lb />at <placeName>Zittau</placeName> against The Clergy. <gap></gap>I could not then do otherwise
               <lb />but Answer Yes. <gap></gap>Hereupon he committed me to Prison. I was
               <lb />quite alone there, and was often <abbr>ask'd</abbr> if I would not change my
               <lb />Mind, but I could not. The Justice tried the Serpents Wisdom and
               <lb />told me I should only Ask Pardon and all would be well. I was in a
               <lb />great Strait yet promised to do so. An Officer brought me then to
               <lb />the Parson to Ask his Pardon. I thought with my tongue I will do
               <lb />it, but my Heart shall not give its Consent. But no sooner had
               <lb />the Words <abbr>pass'd</abbr> my Lips then my Distress was greater than I can
               <lb />Express. I <abbr>begd</abbr> and <abbr>pray'd</abbr> Oh dearest Saviour! do not cast me off
               <lb />forever. I went to the Parson and told him how I felt since my
               <lb />Rescinding, that the blessed Application of Jesus Merrits and death
               <lb />to my heart, was now quite gone and <abbr>Vanish'd</abbr> He tried to make
               <lb />me easy by saying It would be all well again in a short time
               <lb />soon After Notice was given me by An Officer sent from the
               <lb />Lord of the Place, That I should in a short time leave the Town
               <lb />I went to <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> and found there an <sic>Habbitation</sic> <corr>Habitation</corr>. In <date>August
                  <lb />1728</date> I moved thither with my Family <abbr>altho</abbr> with a Wounded and
               <lb />grieved Heart, and went on in my Misery and Distress above
               <lb />3 Years, and then My heart was Softened and Melted <abbr>thro</abbr> the
               <lb />Love and Grace of the <sic>faithfull</sic> <corr>faithful</corr> Friend of Sinners so that I
               <lb />had some hopes of Comfort. <gap></gap>One Morning when I took my
               <lb />little <persName>Anna Rosina</persName> out of Bed I <abbr>ask'd</abbr> her what Verse she would
               <lb />give me, and she repeated such a Sweet Comfortable one
               <lb />that my Heart was enlarged so that I could lay myself as a poor
               <lb />lost Sinner at the Feet of Jesus and find all the Blame in me
               <lb />then I found enough cause to be a Sinner and obtained an insight
               <lb />into the bleeding and Sacrifice of Jesus in which alone I could obtain
               <lb />Grace Mercy and forgiveness of Sins. <gap></gap>Soon after the dear Disciple
               <lb />sent for me and <abbr>ask'd</abbr> me <sic>wether</sic> <corr>whether</corr> I was willing to be in a Band
               <lb />which <persName><abbr>Br.</abbr> Tobias Friedrick</persName> <sic>keept</sic> <corr>kept</corr>? This I <abbr>look'd</abbr> upon as a great
               <lb /><note type="catchword">Favour</note>
               <lb /><note type="catchword">and</note>

               <pb type="double_left" n="3" ana=".10199.26029"/>
               <figure n="199-03">
                  <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-03.jpg"/>
                  <ab type="caption">John Friedrich Gocht, Page 3</ab>
               </figure>

               <lb />and our Saviour <sic><abbr>oppend</abbr></sic><abbr> </abbr><corr><abbr>opend</abbr></corr> my Heart which was formerly <abbr>seald</abbr> up so
               <lb />that I could tell my whole Situation. I likewise <abbr>obtaind</abbr> the unspeak
               <lb />=able Favour to partake the Holy Sacrament with the Congregation
               <lb />That was a happy Moment. I <abbr>look'd</abbr> on myself as a poor Sinner who
               <lb /><abbr>obtaind</abbr> Salvation purely out of free Grace and Mercy and com=
               <lb />=mended myself to the failthful care and Protection of our dear
               <lb />Saviour, and the Maternal Tuition of the Holy Spirit. when I
               <lb />arose in the Morning my first thoughts were <gap></gap><abbr>O</abbr> that I might neither
               <lb />think speak or hear of any thing but thy Love and thee, <gap></gap>and his
               <lb />Grace lead me happily, yet still a time came <sic>wherin</sic> <corr>wherein</corr> I felt myself
               <lb />so cold and in such dryness that I <sic>staid</sic> <corr>stayed</corr> away from the Holy Sacra
               <lb />=ment. I was much troubled and <abbr>beg'd</abbr> our dear Saviour for forgive
               <lb />=ness, and he again <abbr>bless'd</abbr> me with his Peace. Just then the Word
               <lb />for the Day was, Ye Husbands pray without doubting My Prayer
               <lb />was. <abbr>O</abbr> let me in thy Nail <unclear>prints</unclear> see, my Pardon &amp; Election free
               <lb />and I heard the Blessed words in my Heart: behold I have gra=
               <lb />=ven thee in the Palms of my Hands. In the Year <date>1736</date> I
               <lb />was admitted among the <orgName>hourly Intercessors</orgName>. Then I experienced
               <lb />what that is to be with the Spouse quite lonely and to pray for
               <lb />the whole <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi><abbr>. Yea</abbr> for our dear Saviours whole Kingdom.
               <lb />3 Years after I became Sick Waiter. I <abbr>beg'd</abbr> our Saviour to give me
               <lb />wisdom and an humble lowly Sinner Heart I was in this
               <lb />Important Office near 10 Years and <abbr>perform'd</abbr> it with great Will
               <lb />=ingness. In the Year <date>1741</date> the <orgName>Priesterly Office of Night Watch
                  <lb />=man</orgName> came to be my Lot. My Bodily Weakness made me
               <lb />at first somewhat <sic>Scrupelous</sic> <corr>Scrupulous</corr> but I soon <sic>recolected</sic> <corr>recollected</corr> the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><abbr>.</abbr>
               <lb />has <sic>apointed</sic> <corr>appointed</corr> the to it, if it is our dear Saviours Will that
               <lb />thou shalt serve him in this Office he will give the Strength
               <lb />to execute it, I therefore undertook it in his Name on the
               <lb /><date>7<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>. of August</date> I <abbr>resign'd</abbr> myself to our Saviours Grace and the
               <lb />Angels Protection: And our dear Saviour gave me his poor
               <lb />Sinner who had nothing but his Grace to feel and see that

<pb type="double_right"/>

               <lb />He was with me and supported me. <gap></gap>Soon after the Office of
               <lb /><abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi><abbr>.</abbr> <sic>Desciples</sic> <corr>Disciples</corr> being introduced My Wife and I had the
               <lb />favour of being the first Married Pair that had this
               <lb />Priesterly <sic>Honnour</sic> <corr>Honour</corr> this <abbr>bow'd</abbr> my heart in Dust before our
               <lb />Saviour. <gap></gap>And Since then, as Often as I have had the fa=
               <lb />=vour of being Congregation or Choir Disciple, My heart
               <lb />has <abbr>enjoyd</abbr> a new Blessing and my Cheeks has been wetted
               <lb />with Sinner Tears. <gap></gap>In the Month of <date>June 1760</date> such
               <lb />a Weakness came over me, that I was obliged to resign
               <lb />my important <orgName>Office of Watchman</orgName> in <placeName>Herrnhuth</placeName> the <date>15<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>.
                  <lb />of June</date> being the last Night in which I <abbr>watch'd</abbr>. My
               <lb />Weakness <abbr>increas'd</abbr> so, that I was in great hopes I should
               <lb />soon depart from this Vale of Tears, but that Hour is not
               <lb />yet come. I have been obliged to miss many fine Meetings it
               <lb />is true yet his sweet Nearness has often made me many a
               <lb />Happy Hour in my Chamber the <date>15<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>. of February 1762</date> I had
               <lb />a most peculiar Hour of Grace which I no more expected in
               <lb />this Life, which was that <persName><abbr>Br.</abbr> Gregor</persName> <abbr>surrender'd</abbr> the Con=
               <lb />=gregation Discipleship to me in my Sick Chamber It was
               <lb />as <abbr>tho</abbr> a Stream of Mercy and Grace was <abbr>pourd</abbr> out over me
               <lb />and I <abbr>receiv'd</abbr> that favour with Sinner Shame &amp; bowedness
               <lb />and with many Tears! <gap></gap>Thus far his Own Words.
            </p>
            </div>
                    <div type="para" n="2">
                       <p>
               <lb />Our dear Brothers <sic>Charactor</sic> <corr>Character</corr> is known to the whole Congregation.
               <lb />He was indeed a faithful Heart, quite in Love with the most
               <lb />Fairest and Beauteous Saviour He was Legitimated as such
               <lb />and we can give him the Attestation of his being a true
               <lb />Liturgus. <gap></gap>He <abbr>pray'd</abbr> without ceasing, and made it his
               <lb />real concern to Commend to our dear Lords Blessing and
               <lb />Protection the increase of his Kingdom The whole <abbr>Brns told</abbr>
               <lb/><note type="catchword">the</note>


                          <pb type="page" n="4" ana=".10199.26030"/>
                          <figure n="199-04">
                             <graphic url="http://moravianlives.bucknell.edu/MAB/MemBeth_0199a-04.jpg"/>
                             <ab type="caption">John Friedrich Gocht, Page 4</ab>
                          </figure>

               <lb />the Congregation and Choirs and especially the Directorium. He
               <lb />often <abbr>express'd</abbr> how weighty the <orgName>Office of Watchman</orgName> had been
               <lb />to him. <gap></gap><abbr>Thro</abbr> our Saviours Grace every Night for 19 Years
               <lb />he <abbr>watchd Pray'd</abbr> and <abbr>perform'd</abbr> the High priestly office of off=
               <lb /><sic>=ring</sic> <corr>=ering</corr> the Incense of Tears &amp; Supplications and edified the
               <lb /><abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi><abbr>.</abbr> with his agreeable Singing which has often been a means
               <lb />to make Strangers praise the Name of the Lord, He has <abbr>refreshd</abbr>
               <lb />the Sick in their sleepless Nights and reminded them of the
               <lb />faithful Keeper of Israel the Watchman of Soul &amp; Body. The
               <lb />more this Office was of Weight to him, the greater was his Grief
               <lb />that his weakly Body obliged him to give the Post of Watchman
               <lb />to the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><abbr>.</abbr> He then went on his Path in Converse with the
               <lb />Man of Sorrows which <abbr>shorten'd</abbr> the days of his waiting at the
               <lb />healing Ponds. <gap></gap>About 3 Months ago <gap></gap>he was out the last
               <lb />time and <abbr>refresh'd</abbr> his Heart at the Post Communion in the
               <lb />Hall. Since then he spent his time in Stillness hoping and
               <lb />Longing for departure and as often as he was <abbr>askd</abbr> how he
               <lb />found himself his Answer was that he was happy in the Wounds
               <lb />of Jesus- <gap></gap>The <date>31<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi>. of January</date> his last Hour <abbr><sic>aproachd</sic> <corr>approachd</corr></abbr>
               <lb /><persName><abbr>Br.</abbr> John Nitschman</persName> held him a much blessed Liturgy
               <lb />and imparted to him the Blessing of the <abbr>Cong</abbr><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><abbr>n</abbr></hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"></hi><abbr>.</abbr> and his
               <lb />Choir- During the Singing Hour his Soul took its flight
               <lb />to Jesus Arms and Bosom and left the Body a fine Priestly
               <lb />Countenance after have dwelt in this Mortal Tent near
               <lb />72 Years. -
            </p>
            </div>
                 </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
